<chapter id="gossawfish-1">
  <title>Working With Windows</title>
  <highlights>
	 <para>The information in this chapter describes how to use windows in the
		GNOME desktop. This chapter describes the functions that are associated with
		the <application>Sawfish</application> window manager. </para>
  </highlights>
  <sect1 id="gossawfish-712">
	 <title>Windows, Workspaces, and Viewports</title>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>windows</primary>
		<secondary>introduction</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>workspaces</primary>
		<secondary>introduction</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>viewports</primary>
		<secondary>introduction</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <para>You can display many windows at the same time on your desktop. You
		can run different applications in each window in the following desktop areas:
		</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Workspaces</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Viewports</para>
		</listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	 <para>You can subdivide your desktop into separate workspaces. You can
		display only one workspace at a time, but you can have windows open in all your
		other workspaces. You can divide your workspaces into subdivisions that are
		called viewports. You can display only one viewport at a time, but you can have
		windows open in all of your other viewports.</para>
	 <para>The <application>Desk Guide</application> applet displays a visual
		representation of your windows, workspaces, and viewports.
		<xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-717"/> shows the <application>Desk
		Guide</application> applet when your desktop has four workspaces with four
		viewports in each workspace.</para>
	 <figure id="gossawfish-FIG-717">
		<title>Desk Guide Applet</title>
		<screenshot> 
		  <mediaobject> 
			 <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/dguide_vports_applet.png" format="PNG"/> 
			 </imageobject> 
			 <textobject> 
				<phrase>Screenshot of Desk Guide applet</phrase> 
			 </textobject> 
		  </mediaobject> 
		</screenshot>
	 </figure>
	 <para>In the first workspace, the four viewports contain one window each.
		Windows can straddle viewports. That is, part of a window can appear in one
		viewport, and the other part of the window can appear in an adjacent viewport.
		In the second workspace in <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-717"/>, a window
		straddles the first two viewports.</para>
	 <para>Each workspace and viewport has the same panels, desktop background
		objects, and background as all other workspaces and viewports. Your workspaces
		are arranged in a list. You can view the workspace list in the 
		<guimenu>Root </guimenu> menu. By default, your workspace list contains
		four workspaces, with one viewport in each workspace.</para>
	 <para>You can use the <application>Sawfish window manager</application>
		capplet to specify the default number of workspaces. You can also add more
		workspaces at any time. When you add a workspace, the new workspace is inserted
		immediately next to the current workspace.</para>
	 <para>You can move your workspaces to rearrange the order of workspaces in
		the workspace list. The order of the workspace list affects where the
		workspaces are located in the <application>Desk Guide</application> applet. The
		order of the workspace list also affects the list order in the 
		<guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu. You can also move or copy windows to other
		workspaces.</para>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-15">
		<title>Window Manager Behavior</title>
		<para>A window manager controls how windows appear and behave on your
		  desktop. The window manager manages where your windows are located, which
		  window has focus, and the style of the frame on the windows. The window frame
		  contains buttons that enable you to perform standard actions such as moving,
		  closing, and resizing windows.</para>
		<para>You can work with many different window managers in your desktop.
		  You can choose which window manager to use in the <application>Window Manager
		  </application> capplet. You must use a GNOME-compliant window manager, such as
		  <application>Sawfish</application>, for all GNOME features to function
		  correctly.</para>
		<para>You can configure many window management settings in the
		  <application> Sawfish</application> window manager. This manual describes the
		  functions that are associated with the default configuration of the
		  <application>Sawfish </application> window manager. The default configuration
		  is specified in the <application> Sawfish window manager</application> capplet.
		  This manual also describes the default functions of the Crux frame
		  style.</para>
	 </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gossawfish-713">
	 <title>Types of Window</title>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>windows</primary>
		<secondary>types of</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <para>The desktop features the following types of windows: </para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Application windows </para>
		  <para>When you start an application, an application window opens. The
			 window manager applies a frame to the application window.</para>
		  <para>The titlebar along the top edge of the window frame contains
			 buttons that you can use to work with the window. The titlebar contains one
			 button on the left side and three on the right side. </para>
		  <para>The following figure shows a typical application window. </para>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/gedit_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of a typical application window</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>Dialog windows</para>
		  <para>A dialog window is a popup window in which you enter information
			 or commands. The dialog appears within a window frame.</para>
		  <para>You can use the titlebar along the top edge of the dialog window
			 frame to work with the window. You can use the titlebar to move the dialog
			 around the desktop. The titlebar also contains a button that enables you to do
			 the following:</para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Close the dialog window</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Open the 
				  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu </para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		  <para>Typically you open a dialog window from an application window.
			 When you open a dialog window, the window is usually raised and has focus. Some
			 dialog windows do not allow you to use the application until you close the
			 dialog. Both of these behaviors are options that you can select in the
			 <application> Sawfish window manager</application> capplet. </para>
		  <para>The following figure shows a typical dialog window. </para>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/gedit_pref_dialog.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of a typical dialog window</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		</listitem>
	 </itemizedlist>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-16">
		<title>Window Frames</title>
		<para>A window frame is a border around a window. The window frame
		  contains a titlebar. The titlebar normally contains buttons that you can use to
		  work with the window.</para>
		<para>You can apply several styles of window frame to your windows. The
		  style of a window frame determines how the frame looks and which buttons are on
		  the frame. You can choose a default frame style for all your windows in the
		  <application> Sawfish window manager</application> capplet. You can also choose
		  a different frame style for each individual window. </para>
		<para>The default frame style is Crux. This manual describes the
		  functions that are associated with the Crux frame style. </para>
		<para>Other frame styles have a different visual design to the Crux frame
		  style. For example, <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-4"/> shows an application
		  window in the MicroGUI frame style.</para>
		<figure id="gossawfish-FIG-4">
		  <title>Application Window in MicroGUI Frame Style</title>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/gedit2_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of an application window in MicroGUI frame
					 style</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		</figure>
		<para><xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-5"/> shows a dialog window in the
		  MicroGUI frame style. </para>
		<figure id="gossawfish-FIG-5">
		  <title>Dialog Window in MicroGUI Frame Style </title>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/gedit_pref2_dialog.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of a dialog window in MicroGUI frame
					 style</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		</figure>
		<para>Application windows in the Crux and MicroGUI frame styles have four
		  buttons in the titlebar. Other frame styles can have a different number of
		  buttons in the titlebar. For example, application windows in the smaker frame
		  style have only two buttons.</para>
		<para>Other frame styles can assign different functions to the buttons in
		  the titlebar. For example, in the Crux frame style, if you click on the button
		  on the left of the titlebar the window closes. In the smaker frame style, if
		  you click on the button on the left of the titlebar the window minimizes.
		  </para>
		<para>You can view tooltips for the buttons and other control elements on
		  window frames. Tooltips appear when you point to the control element. The
		  following shows the tooltip for the 
		  <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button. </para>
		<figure id="gossawfish-FIG-703">
		  <title>Tooltip for Maximize Button</title>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/sample_tooltip.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of tooltip for Maximize button</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		</figure>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-17">
		  <title>Window Frame Control Elements</title>
		  <para>You can use the window frame to perform various actions with the
			 window. In particular, the titlebar contains various active control elements.
			 The following figure shows the titlebar of an application window in the Crux
			 frame style.</para>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/titlebar_anno_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Annotated screenshot of an application window</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		  <para>Dialog windows also contain some of the window frame control
			 elements. <xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-1"/> describes the active control
			 elements on window frames in the Crux frame style, from left to right.</para>
		  <table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-1">
		  <title>Window Frame Control Elements</title>
		  <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
			 colwidth="41.65*"/><colspec colwidth="58.35*"/>
			 <thead>
				<row rowsep="1">
				  <entry>
					 <para>Control Element</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Description </para></entry>
				</row>
			 </thead>
			 <tbody>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>The button on the left of the titlebar. Click on the
						button to close the window. If the window is in a window group, press 
						<keycap>Shift </keycap> then click on the 
						<guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button to close all
						windows in the group. </para>
					 <para>You can also right-click on the
						<guibutton> Close Window</guibutton> button to open the 
						<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. </para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Titlebar</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>You can use the titlebar to perform the following
						actions: </para>
					 <itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To give focus to the window click on the
							 titlebar.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To move the window grab the titlebar and drag the
							 window to the new location. </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To shade the window, double-click on the titlebar. To
							 unshade the window, double-click on the titlebar again.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To resize the window vertically middle-click and hold
							 the titlebar, then drag up or drag down. </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>If the window is at the top of the 
							 <glossterm>stacking order </glossterm>, right-click on
							 the titlebar to lower the window to the bottom. If the window is not at the top
							 of the stacking order, right-click on the titlebar to raise the window to the
							 top. The raise and lower operations work within 
							 <glossterm>layers</glossterm>. </para>
						</listitem>
					 </itemizedlist></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button </para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para> The first button in the group of three buttons on the
						right side of the titlebar. Click on the 
						<guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button to minimize the
						window. You can also right-click on the 
						<guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button to open the 
						<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button </para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para> The second button in the group of three buttons on the
						right side of the titlebar. Use the 
						<guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button to perform the
						following actions: </para>
					 <itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To maximize the window click on the 
							 <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button. To restore the
							 window click on the 
							 <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button again. </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To maximize the window vertically, middle-click on
							 the 
							 <guibutton> Maximize</guibutton> button. To restore the
							 window click on the 
							 <guibutton> Maximize</guibutton> button again.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To maximize the window horizontally, right-click on
							 the 
							 <guibutton> Maximize</guibutton> button. To restore the
							 window click on the 
							 <guibutton> Maximize</guibutton> button again. </para>
						</listitem>
					 </itemizedlist></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guibutton>Shade</guibutton> button </para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para> The third button in the group of three buttons on the
						right side of the titlebar. Click on the button to shade the window. To unshade
						the window click on the button again.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Border</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>The border around the window. Use the border to perform
						the following actions: </para>
					 <itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To resize the window grab the border and drag the
							 border to the new size. </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>To move the window middle-click and hold the border
							 and drag the window to the new location. </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>If the window is at the top of the stacking order,
							 right-click on the border to lower the window to the bottom. If the window is
							 not at the top of the stacking order, right-click on the border to raise the
							 window to the top. The raise and lower operations work within layers. </para>
						</listitem>
					 </itemizedlist></entry>
				</row>
			 </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		  </table>
		</sect3>
	 </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gossawfish-714">
	 <title>Applets and Menus for Working With Windows, Workspaces, and
		Viewports </title>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>windows</primary>
		<secondary>applets and menus for working with</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <para>This section describes the applets and menus that you can use to work
		with windows, workspaces, and viewports.</para>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-18">
		<title>Tasklist Applet</title>
		<para>The <application>Tasklist</application> applet displays a button
		  for each window that is open. The <application>Tasklist</application> applet
		  enables you to perform the following tasks:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Minimize and restore windows.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Give focus to windows.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Shade and unshade windows.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Stick and unstick windows.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Close and kill windows.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>When you open a window, the <application>Tasklist</application>
		  applet displays a button that represents the window. The tasklist buttons show
		  which windows are open. You can view which windows are open, even if some
		  windows are minimized, or other windows overlap a window. The
		  <application>Tasklist </application> applet can display buttons for the windows
		  in your current workspace and viewport, or in all workspaces and viewports. To
		  select this option, you must change the properties of the
		  <application>Tasklist</application> applet.</para>
		<para><xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-8"/> shows the
		  <application>Tasklist</application> applet when the following windows are
		  open:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para><application>gedit</application></para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para><application>GHex</application></para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para><application>Netscape Navigator</application></para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para><application>Netscape Messenger</application></para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para><application>Netscape Composer</application></para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para><application>GNOME Terminal</application></para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<figure id="gossawfish-FIG-8">
		  <title>Tasklist Applet</title>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/tasklist_group_applet.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of Tasklist applet</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		</figure>
		<para>The buttons in the applet show the status of your windows.
		  <xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-3"/> explains the information that the tasklist
		  buttons provide about the window. The examples in
		  <xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-3"/> refer to <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-8"/>.
		  </para>
		<table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-3">
		<title>Window Status Information on Tasklist Buttons</title>
		<tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="33*"/><colspec
		  colwidth="33*"/>
		  <colspec colwidth="33*"/>
		  <thead>
			 <row rowsep="1">
				<entry>
				  <para>State</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para>Description </para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para>Example</para></entry>
			 </row>
		  </thead>
		  <tbody>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>Tasklist button is pressed in</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Indicates that the window has focus.</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para><application> GHex</application></para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>No square brackets around window title </para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Indicates that the window is on the desktop and is not
					 minimized. </para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para><application>gedit</application></para>
				  <para><application>GHex </application></para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>Square brackets around window title </para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Indicates that the window is minimized.</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para><application> [Terminal]</application></para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>Number in parentheses before window title </para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para>Indicates that the button represents a group of windows
					 that have the same name. The number in parentheses indicates the number of
					 windows in the task group.</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para><application>(3) Netscape</application></para></entry>
			 </row>
		  </tbody>
		</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>You can use the <application>Tasklist</application> applet to
		  perform the following actions on windows:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window has focus, click on the button that represents
				the window to minimize the window.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is minimized, click on the button that represents
				the window to restore the window.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is not minimized and not in focus, click on the
				button that represents the window to give focus to the window.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-19">
		  <title>Task Menu</title>
		  <para>A task menu contains menu items that enable you to perform
			 various tasks on windows. For example, task menu items enable you to minimize
			 and restore a window. To open a task menu, right-click on the button that
			 represents the window with which you want to work.</para>
		  <para>The items that appear on the menu depend on the state of the
			 window that the tasklist button represents. For example, if the window is not
			 shaded, the popup menu contains a 
			 <guimenuitem>Shade</guimenuitem> item. If the window is shaded, the
			 popup menu contains an 
			 <guimenuitem>Unshade</guimenuitem> item. </para>
		  <para><xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-4"/> lists the items that you can
			 choose from a task menu.</para>
		  <table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-4">
		  <title>Task Menu</title>
		  <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
			 colwidth="32.98*"/><colspec colwidth="67.02*"/>
			 <thead>
				<row rowsep="1">
				  <entry>
					 <para>Menu Item</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Description </para></entry>
				</row>
			 </thead>
			 <tbody>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Iconify</guimenuitem> or 
						<guimenuitem>Restore </guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>To minimize the window to the <application>
						Tasklist</application> applet, choose 
						<guimenuitem>Iconify</guimenuitem>. If the window is already
						minimized, choose 
						<guimenuitem>Restore</guimenuitem> to restore the
						window.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Shade</guimenuitem> or 
						<guimenuitem>Unshade </guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>To reduce the window so that only the titlebar is
						visible, choose 
						<guimenuitem>Shade</guimenuitem>. If the window is already
						shaded, choose 
						<guimenuitem>Unshade</guimenuitem> to display the full
						window.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Stick</guimenuitem> or 
						<guimenuitem>Unstick </guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>To set the window to display in any workspace or viewport
						that you view, choose 
						<guimenuitem>Stick</guimenuitem>. If the window is already
						set to stick, choose 
						<guimenuitem>Unstick</guimenuitem> to set the window to
						display only in the current workspace or current viewport. </para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Close window</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para> To close the window choose 
						<guimenuitem>Close window</guimenuitem>.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Kill app</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para> To close all windows that are open for the application,
						choose 
						<guimenuitem> Kill app</guimenuitem>.</para>
					 <note>
						<para>If you choose 
						  <guimenuitem>Kill app</guimenuitem> on a dialog window, any
						  other windows that were opened by the application are closed.</para>
					 </note></entry>
				</row>
			 </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		  </table>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-708">
		  <title>Task Groups</title>
		  <para>The <application>Tasklist</application> applet allows you to
			 group tasks of the same name into a single tasklist button. You click on the
			 button to display a list of the tasks in the task group. The following figure
			 shows a task group list.</para>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/tasklist_group2_applet.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of a task group list</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		  <para>The task group list uses the same notation as the tasklist
			 buttons. </para>
		  <para>You can use a task group list to perform the following actions on
			 windows: </para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Restore the window if the window is minimized. Click on the
				  tasklist button to display the task group list. Click on the item that
				  represents the window to restore the window.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Give focus to the window, if the window is not minimized and
				  not in focus. Click on the tasklist button to display the task group list.
				  Click on the item that represents the window to give focus to the window.
				  </para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		  <para>You can also use the task menu to perform actions on windows in
			 task groups. You can open a task menu in the following ways:</para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Click on the tasklist button to display the task group list,
				  then right-click on an item in the task group list.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Right-click on the button that represents the task group.
				  When you open the task menu from a task group, the menu items apply to all
				  windows in the task group. For example, you can choose 
				  <guimenuitem>Shade All</guimenuitem> to shade all windows in the
				  task group.</para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</sect3>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-20">
		<title>Desk Guide Applet</title>
		<para>The <application>Desk Guide</application> applet displays a visual
		  representation of your workspace list and your viewports. Your workspaces
		  appear as buttons on the applet. Your viewports appear as subdivisions of the
		  workspace buttons on the applet. To switch to another workspace or viewport,
		  click on the workspace or viewport.</para>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-21">
		  <title>Desk Guide Applet and Workspaces</title>
		  <para><xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-12"/> shows the <application>Desk
			 Guide </application> applet when your desktop has four workspaces.</para>
		  <figure id="gossawfish-FIG-12">
			 <title>Desk Guide Applet With Workspaces</title>
			 <screenshot> 
				<mediaobject> 
				  <imageobject>
					 <imagedata fileref="figures/dguide_wspaces_anno_applet.png" format="PNG"/> 
				  </imageobject> 
				  <textobject> 
					 <phrase>Annotated screenshot of Desk Guide with
						workspaces</phrase> 
				  </textobject> 
				</mediaobject> 
			 </screenshot>
		  </figure>
		  <para>The button that represents the current workspace is pressed in.
			 The current workspace in <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-12"/> is the workspace
			 at the left. To switch to another workspace click on the workspace. </para>
		  <para>The position of workspaces in the <application>Desk
			 Guide</application> applet follows a table structure. The workspace at the top
			 left of the following figure corresponds to the workspace at the top of the
			 workspace list.</para>
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/dguide_wspaces_applet.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of Desk Guide</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		  <para>The workspace at the top right corresponds to the second
			 workspace. The workspace at the bottom left corresponds to the third workspace,
			 and so on. The <application>Desk Guide</application> applet places workspaces
			 from left to right across the <application>Desk Guide</application> rows. When
			 the applet reaches the end of a row, the next workspace is placed at the
			 beginning of the next row.</para>
		  <para>To specify the table structure for the applet you change the
			 properties for the applet. For example <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-12"/>
			 shows the <application> Desk Guide</application> applet when the table
			 structure is two rows and two columns of workspaces. </para>
		  <para>The table structure of the <application>Desk Guide</application>
			 applet determines the position of workspaces when you add, move, or copy
			 workspaces. </para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-22">
		  <title>Desk Guide Applet and Viewports</title>
		  <para><xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-13"/> shows the <application>Desk
			 Guide </application> applet when your desktop has four workspaces with four
			 viewports in each workspace.</para>
		  <figure id="gossawfish-FIG-13">
			 <title>Desk Guide Applet With Viewports</title>
			 <screenshot> 
				<mediaobject> 
				  <imageobject>
					 <imagedata fileref="figures/dguide_vports_anno_applet.png" format="PNG"/> 
				  </imageobject> 
				  <textobject> 
					 <phrase>Annotated screenshot of Desk Guide with
						viewports</phrase> 
				  </textobject> 
				</mediaobject> 
			 </screenshot>
		  </figure>
		  <para>The current viewport is highlighted with a checked background.
			 The current viewport in <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-13"/> is the viewport in
			 the top left of the current workspace. To switch to another viewport click on
			 the viewport.</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-23">
		  <title>Desk Guide Tasklist</title>
		  <para>The <application>Desk Guide</application> tasklist lists the
			 tasks currently running in your session. To open the <application>Desk
			 Guide</application> tasklist click on the tasklist arrow button. To switch to a
			 task click on the task in the tasklist.</para>
		</sect3>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-24">
		<title>Window Menu</title>
		<para>The 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu is a menu of commands and submenus that
		  you can use to perform actions on your windows. To open the 
		  <guimenu> Window</guimenu> menu perform one of the following
		  actions:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Right-click on the 
				<guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button on the window that you
				want to work with.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Press-and-hold the modifier key then middle-click on any part
				of the window that you want to work with. The default modifier key is the meta
				key.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para><xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-25"/> describes the commands and
		  submenus in the 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu.</para>
		<table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-25">
		<title>Window Menu Commands and Submenus</title>
		<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
		  colwidth="32.34*"/><colspec colwidth="67.66*"/>
		  <thead>
			 <row rowsep="1">
				<entry>
				  <para>Menu Item</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para>Function </para></entry>
			 </row>
		  </thead>
		  <tbody>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guimenuitem>Minimize</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Minimizes the window.</para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guimenuitem>Maximize</guimenuitem> or 
					 <guimenuitem>Unmaximize </guimenuitem></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para>Maximizes the window horizontally and vertically. If the
					 window is already maximized, choose 
					 <guimenuitem>Unmaximize </guimenuitem> to restore the window to
					 its previous horizontal and vertical size. </para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Closes the window.</para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Toggle</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu of various states that you can switch on
					 and switch off for the window. </para>
				  <para>The submenu contains the following items: </para>
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Sticky</guimenuitem>: Select this option to
						  set the window to stick. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Shaded</guimenuitem>: Select this option to
						  shade the window. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Ignored</guimenuitem>: Select this option if
						  you want the window manager to ignore the window.</para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Focusable</guimenuitem>: Deselect this option
						  if you do not want the window to be able to receive focus. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Cyclable</guimenuitem>: Deselect this option
						  if you do not want the window to appear when you cycle through your windows.
						  </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>In window list</guimenuitem>: Deselect this
						  option if you do not want the window to appear in the 
						  <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu or on the <application>Desk
						  Guide</application> display.</para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>In GNOME task list</guimenuitem>: Deselect
						  this option if you do not want the window to appear in either the <application>
						  Tasklist</application> applet or the <application>Desk Guide</application>
						  applet.</para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>In Group</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu of the window groups on your desktop. A
					 radio button indicates which group the window belongs to.</para>
				  <para>To add the window to another window group choose the other
					 window group from the submenu. </para>
				  <para> To remove the window from the window group choose 
					 <guimenuitem>New group</guimenuitem>. </para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Send Window To</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu that contains items that you can use to
					 send the window to another workspace.</para>
				  <para>The submenu contains the following items: </para>
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Previous workspace</guimenuitem>: Choose this
						  item to send the window to the workspace before the current workspace. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Next workspace</guimenuitem>: Choose this item
						  to send the window to the workspace after the current workspace. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Copy to previous</guimenuitem>: Choose this
						  item to create a copy of the window in the workspace before the current
						  workspace, and switch to that workspace. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Copy to next</guimenuitem>: Choose this item
						  to create a copy of the window in the workspace after the current workspace,
						  and switch to that workspace. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Left</guimenuitem>: </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Right</guimenuitem>: </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Up</guimenuitem>: </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Down</guimenuitem>: </para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Stacking</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu that contains items that you can use to
					 change the position of the window in the stacking order. </para>
				  <para>The submenu contains the following items: </para>
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Raise</guimenuitem>: Choose this item to move
						  the window to the top of the stacking order within the layer. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Lower</guimenuitem>: Choose this item to move
						  the window to the bottom of the stacking order within the layer. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Upper layer</guimenuitem>: Choose this item to
						  increment the layer that the window is in by one.</para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Lower layer</guimenuitem>: Choose this item to
						  decrement the layer that the window is in by one.</para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Frame Type</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu that contains items that you can use to
					 change the window type. The window type determines what frame appears on the
					 window. </para>
				  <para> The submenu contains the following items: </para>
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Normal</guimenuitem>: Choose this item if you
						  want the window to have an application window titlebar and borders.</para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Title-only</guimenuitem>: Choose this item if
						  you want the window to have an application window titlebar and no borders.
						  </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Border-only</guimenuitem>: Choose this item if
						  you want the window to have a dialog window titlebar and borders. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Top-border</guimenuitem>: Choose this item if
						  you want the window to have a dialog window titlebar and no borders. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>None</guimenuitem>: Choose this item if you
						  want the window to have no titlebar and no borders. </para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Frame style</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu of frame styles. Choose the style that you
					 want from the submenu. To return to the default frame style choose 
					 <guimenuitem>Default</guimenuitem>. </para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>History</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Opens a submenu that contains items that you can use to
					 save the current settings of the window. The next time that you open the
					 application, the window uses these settings. The items in the 
					 <guisubmenu>History</guisubmenu> submenu are useful if, for
					 example, you want an application window to open as follows: 
					 <itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
						  <para>The window is in a specified location.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>The window is a specified size.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
						  <para>The window has particular attributes selected.</para>
						</listitem>
					 </itemizedlist></para>
				  <para>The submenu contains the following items: </para>
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Remember position</guimenuitem>: Choose this
						  item to save the location of the window on the desktop. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Remember dimensions</guimenuitem>: Choose this
						  item to save the dimensions of the window. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Remember attributes</guimenuitem>: Choose this
						  item to save the attributes that are set in the 
						  <guisubmenu>Toggle</guisubmenu>, 
						  <guisubmenu> Frame type</guisubmenu>, and 
						  <guisubmenu>Frame style</guisubmenu> submenus. </para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
						  <guimenuitem>Forget saved state</guimenuitem>: Choose this
						  item to discard all saved settings. The settings of the window are reset to the
						  default location, dimensions, and attributes.</para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist></entry>
			 </row>
		  </tbody>
		</tgroup>
		</table>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-26">
		<title>Root Menu</title>
		<para>You can use the 
		  <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu to navigate between windows and
		  workspaces. To open the 
		  <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu middle-click on the desktop background.
		  The following figure shows the 
		  <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu.</para>
		<screenshot> 
		  <mediaobject> 
			 <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/root_windows_submenu.png" format="PNG"/> 
			 </imageobject> 
			 <textobject> 
				<phrase>Screenshot of Root menu</phrase> 
			 </textobject> 
		  </mediaobject> 
		</screenshot>
		<para><xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-702"/> describes the items that the 
		  <guimenu> Root</guimenu> menu contains.</para>
		<table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-702">
		<title>Root Menu</title>
		<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
		  colwidth="32.32*"/><colspec colwidth="67.68*"/>
		  <thead>
			 <row rowsep="1">
				<entry>
				  <para>Item</para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para>Function</para></entry>
			 </row>
		  </thead>
		  <tbody>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Windows</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Enables you to view a list of open windows, and to switch
					 between windows. For more information on the window list, see
					 <xref linkend="gossawfish-718"/>. </para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Workspaces</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Enables you to perform workspace-related tasks. For
					 example the workspace list enables you to switch to another workspace. For more
					 information on the workspace list, see <xref linkend="gossawfish-719"/>.
					 </para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Programs</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Identical to the 
					 <guimenu>Programs</guimenu> menu.</para></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Customize</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Provides access to the configuration functions for the
					 <application>Sawfish </application> window manager. </para>
				  <note>
					 <para>The <application>Sawfish window manager</application>
						capplet includes an option that enables you to select whether the 
						<guisubmenu>Customize</guisubmenu> menu items open the 
						<guilabel> Sawfish configurator</guilabel> dialog or the
						<application>Control Center </application><application>Sawfish window
						manager</application> capplet.</para>
				  </note></entry>
			 </row>
			 <row>
				<entry>
				  <para>
					 <guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu></para></entry>
				<entry>
				  <para> Provides links to help on the
					 <application>Sawfish</application> window manager and help on GNOME. The 
					 <guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu> submenu also provides links to
					 the websites for <application>Sawfish</application> and GNOME.</para></entry>
			 </row>
		  </tbody>
		</tgroup>
		</table>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-718">
		  <title>Using the Root Menu to Work With Windows</title>
		  <para>From the 
			 <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu, you can view a list of all windows that
			 are currently open. You can also choose a window to give focus to. To view the
			 window list, middle-click on the desktop background to open the 
			 <guimenu> Root</guimenu> menu, then choose 
			 <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem>.
			 <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-10"/> shows an example of the window list that is
			 displayed from the 
			 <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu:</para>
		  <figure id="gossawfish-FIG-10">
			 <title>Window List</title>
			 <screenshot> 
				<mediaobject> 
				  <imageobject>
					 <imagedata fileref="figures/root_windows2_submenu.png" format="PNG"/> 
				  </imageobject> 
				  <textobject> 
					 <phrase>Screenshot of window list</phrase> 
				  </textobject> 
				</mediaobject> 
			 </screenshot>
		  </figure>
		  <para>The window list enables you to give focus to windows that are
			 open in all workspaces and viewports. </para>
		  <para>A radio button that is selected indicates which window has focus.
			 For example, in <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-10"/>
			 <application>gedit</application> has focus. If an application has more than one
			 window open, the application name appears as a submenu in the window list. For
			 example, in <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-10"/> the
			 <application>Netscape</application> application is a submenu from which you can
			 choose one of the <application>Netscape</application> application windows. That
			 is, you can choose to give focus to the browser, Composer, or Mail &amp;
			 Newsgroup windows. </para>
		  <para>The window list also uses a system of notation to indicate the
			 status of windows. <xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-720"/> describes this
			 notation. The examples in <xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-720"/> refer to
			 <xref linkend="gossawfish-FIG-10"/>. </para>
		  <table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-720">
		  <title>Notation on Window List</title>
		  <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="COLSPEC0"
			 colwidth="33.70*"/>
			 <colspec colname="COLSPEC1" colwidth="37.87*"/><colspec
			 colname="COLSPEC2" colwidth="27.43*"/>
			 <thead>
				<row rowsep="1">
				  <entry>
					 <para>Notation</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Description </para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Example</para></entry>
				</row>
			 </thead>
			 <tbody>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>No notation</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Indicates that the window is not minimized and does not
						have focus.</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guilabel> The GIMP</guilabel></para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry colname="COLSPEC0">
					 <para>At the left of the window title, a radio button that is
						selected</para></entry>
				  <entry colname="COLSPEC1">
					 <para>Indicates that the window has focus.</para></entry>
				  <entry colname="COLSPEC2">
					 <para>
						<guilabel> gedit</guilabel></para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Brackets around window title</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para> Indicates that the window is minimized.</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guilabel> [Terminal]</guilabel></para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry colname="COLSPEC0">
					 <para>Parentheses around window title</para></entry>
				  <entry colname="COLSPEC1">
					 <para>Indicates that the window is in another workspace and is
						not minimized.</para></entry>
				  <entry colname="COLSPEC2">
					 <para>
						<guilabel> (Control Center)</guilabel></para></entry>
				</row>
			 </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		  </table>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-719">
		  <title>Using the Root Menu to Work With Workspaces</title>
		  <para>The workspace list enables you to do the following: </para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>View the list of workspaces.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Switch between workspaces.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Perform other workspace-related tasks, such as inserting
				  workspaces. </para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		  <para>The following figure shows the default workspace list.</para> 
		  <screenshot> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject>
				  <imagedata fileref="figures/root_workspaces_submenu.png" format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Screenshot of workspace list</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </screenshot>
		  <para><xref linkend="gossawfish-TBL-721"/> describes the items on the
			 workspace list.</para>
		  <table frame="topbot" id="gossawfish-TBL-721">
		  <title>Workspace List</title>
		  <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
			 colwidth="50*"/><colspec colwidth="50*"/>
			 <thead>
				<row rowsep="1">
				  <entry>
					 <para>Item</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Description </para></entry>
				</row>
			 </thead>
			 <tbody>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Workspace List</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>A list of the workspaces on your desktop. Choose a
						workspace from this list to switch to that workspace. You can use the
						<application>Sawfish window manager</application> capplet to change the names
						of the workspaces.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Insert workspace</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to insert a workspace after the current
						workspace. </para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Select next
						  workspace</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to switch to the next workspace.
						</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Select previous
						  workspace</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to switch to the previous
						workspace.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Merge with next</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to copy the windows from the current
						workspace to the next workspace. If the number of workspaces on your desktop is
						greater than the minimum number of workspaces, the current workspace is
						deleted.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Merge with previous</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to copy the windows from the current
						workspace to the previous workspace. If the number of workspaces on your
						desktop is greater than the minimum number of workspaces, then the current
						workspace is deleted. </para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Move workspace
						  right</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to swap the position of the current
						workspace with the position of the next workspace. </para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guimenuitem>Move workspace left</guimenuitem></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Choose this item to swap the position of the current
						workspace with the position of the previous workspace.</para></entry>
				</row>
			 </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		  </table>
		</sect3>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-27">
		<title>Using the Menu Panel to Work With Windows</title>
		<para>From the Menu Panel, you can view a list of all windows that are
		  currently open. You can also choose a window to give focus to. To view the
		  window list, click on the icon at the extreme right of the Menu Panel. The
		  following figure shows an example of the window list that is displayed from the
		  Menu Panel: </para>
		<screenshot> 
		  <mediaobject> 
			 <imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/openwindows_menu.png" format="PNG"/> 
			 </imageobject> 
			 <textobject> 
				<phrase>Screenshot of Menu Panel window list</phrase> 
			 </textobject> 
		  </mediaobject> 
		</screenshot>
		<para>The icon that you click on to display the window list changes when
		  you change focus. The icon represents the window that currently has focus. To
		  give focus to a window, choose that window from the window list.</para>
		<para>The window list lists the windows in all workspaces. The windows in
		  all workspaces other than the current workspace, are listed below a separator
		  line.</para>
		<para>You cannot move the icon that you click on to display the window
		  list. </para>
		<para>You can also use the 
		  <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu to display a window list, and give focus
		  to windows.</para>
	 </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gossawfish-715">
	 <title>Manipulating Windows</title>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>windows</primary>
		<secondary>manipulating</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <para>This section describes how to manipulate windows.</para>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-28">
		<title>To Give Focus to a Window</title>
		<para>A window that has focus can receive input from the mouse and the
		  keyboard. Only one window can have focus at a time. The window that has focus
		  has a different appearance than other windows. </para>
		<para>You can give focus to a window in any of the following ways:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the mouse </para>
			 <para>Click on the window to which you want to give focus, if the
				window is visible. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use a shortcut key</para>
			 <para>You can use a shortcut key to switch between the windows that
				are open in the current workspace or viewport. The default shortcut key to
				switch between windows is 
				<keycombo><keycap>Modifier</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>. To give focus to a window, release the
				keys.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the window list from the Menu Panel</para>
			 <para>Click on the icon at the extreme right of the Menu Panel to
				open a window list. Choose the window that you want to give focus to from the
				menu.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the window list from the 
				<guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu </para>
			 <para>Middle-click on the desktop background to open the 
				<guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu, then choose 
				<guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem>. A list of your windows is
				displayed. Choose the window that you want to give focus to from the list.
				</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the <application>Tasklist</application> applet </para>
			 <para>Double-click on the button that represents the window in the
				<application> Tasklist</application> applet.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the <application>Desk Guide</application> applet</para>
			 <para>Open the <application>Desk Guide</application> tasklist, then
				choose the window that you want to give focus to from the <application>Desk
				Guide </application> tasklist.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-29">
		<title>To Minimize a Window</title>
		<para>To minimize a window perform one of the following actions: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Click on the 
				<guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button on the window frame.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu, then choose 
				<guimenuitem> Minimize</guimenuitem>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window has focus, click on the button that represents
				the window in the <application>Tasklist</application> applet. If the window
				does not have focus, double-click on the button that represents the window.
				</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Right-click on the button that represents the window in the
				<application> Tasklist</application> applet. Choose 
				<guimenuitem>Iconify</guimenuitem>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-30">
		<title>To Maximize a Window</title>
		<para>When you maximize a window, the window expands as much as possible.
		  If the maximize mode of a panel specifies that windows can cover the panel, the
		  maximized window can cover the panel.</para>
		<para>To maximize a window perform one of the following actions: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To maximize the window vertically and horizontally, click on
				the 
				<guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button on the window frame. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To maximize the window vertically only, middle-click on the 
				<guibutton> Maximize</guibutton> button on the window frame.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To maximize the window horizontally only, right-click on the 
				<guibutton> Maximize</guibutton> button on the window frame.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To maximize the window vertically and horizontally, open the 
				<guimenu> Window</guimenu> menu. Choose 
				<guimenuitem>Maximize</guimenuitem>.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-31">
		<title>To Restore a Window</title>
		<para>To restore a window perform one of the following actions: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is maximized, click on the 
				<guibutton>Maximize </guibutton> button on the window frame.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is maximized, open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. Choose 
				<guimenuitem>Unmaximize</guimenuitem>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is minimized, click on the button that represents
				the window in the <application>Tasklist</application> applet.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is minimized, right-click on the button that
				represents the window in the <application>Tasklist</application> applet. Choose
				
				<guimenuitem> Restore</guimenuitem>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-32">
		<title>To Close a Window</title>
		<para>To close a window perform one of the following actions: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Click on the 
				<guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button on the window
				frame.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. Choose 
				<guimenuitem> Close</guimenuitem>.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>In the <application>Tasklist</application> applet, right-click
				on the button that represents the window. A popup menu opens. Choose 
				<guimenuitem> Close Window</guimenuitem>.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you have unsaved data in the window, you are prompted to save
		  your data.</para>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-33">
		<title>To Kill a Window</title>
		<para>To send a kill signal to a window, right-click on the button that
		  represents the window in the <application>Tasklist</application> applet. A
		  popup menu opens. Choose 
		  <guimenuitem>Kill app</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<note>
		  <para>If you choose 
			 <guimenuitem>Kill app</guimenuitem> on a dialog window, any other
			 windows opened by the application close also. </para>
		</note>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-34">
		<title>To Resize a Window</title>
		<para>To resize a window perform one of the following actions:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To resize a window vertically and horizontally point to a
				corner of the window. The mouse pointer changes to indicate that you can resize
				the window. Grab the corner and drag the window to the new size.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To resize a window horizontally point to one of the horizontal
				borders of the window. The mouse pointer changes to indicate that you can
				resize the window. Grab the corner and drag the window to the new size.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To resize a window vertically perform one of the following
				actions: 
				<itemizedlist>
				  <listitem>
					 <para>Point to one of the vertical borders of the window. The
						mouse pointer changes to indicate that you can resize the window. Grab the
						corner and drag the window to the new size.</para>
				  </listitem>
				  <listitem>
					 <para>Middle-click and hold on the titlebar, then drag the
						window to the new size.</para>
				  </listitem>
				</itemizedlist></para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<note>
		  <para>You cannot resize some dialog windows. Also, some application
			 windows have a minimum size below which you cannot reduce the window.</para>
		</note>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-35">
		<title>To Move a Window</title>
		<para>To move a window perform one of the following actions: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Grab the titlebar of the window and drag the window to the new
				location. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Point to a corner or an edge of the window. The mouse pointer
				changes to indicate that you can resize the window. Middle-click and hold to
				grab the window, move the window to the new location.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Press-and-hold the modifier key then grab any part of the
				window that you want to move. Drag the window to the new location. The default
				modifier key is the meta key.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-36">
		<title>To Shade a Window</title>
		<para>You can shade and unshade windows as follows:</para>
		<informaltable frame="topbot">
		  <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
			 colwidth="24.94*"/><colspec colwidth="75.06*"/>
			 <tbody>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Shade</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Reduce the window so that only the titlebar is
						visible.</para></entry>
				</row>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Unshade</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Switch a window from a shaded state so that the full
						window is displayed.</para></entry>
				</row>
			 </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		</informaltable>
		<para>To shade a window perform one of the following actions: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Click on the 
				<guibutton>Shade</guibutton> button. To unshade the window, click
				on the 
				<guibutton>Shade</guibutton> button again. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Double-click on the titlebar of the window. To unshade the
				window, double-click on the titlebar again.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Shaded</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. To unshade the window, choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Shaded</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> again.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Right-click on the button that represents the window in the
				<application> Tasklist</application> applet. A popup menu opens. Choose 
				<guimenuitem>Shade </guimenuitem>. To unshade the window,
				right-click on the button that represents the window, then choose 
				<guimenuitem>Unshade </guimenuitem>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-14">
		<title>To Change the Layer of a Window</title>
		<para>Your desktop is structured as a sequence of layers. Each user
		  interface item, such as a window or a panel, is a member of a layer. Each layer
		  has a layer number. A layer number is an integer that represents the position
		  of a layer in the stacking order. Items with a higher layer number always
		  appear above items with a lower layer number. For example, a panel in layer
		  four always appears above a window in layer zero.</para>
		<para>The stacking order is the order in which windows are stacked on top
		  of one another on your screen. The position of a window in the stacking order
		  depends on the following:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>The layer of which the window is a member.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>The position of the window in the order of windows within the
				layer.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The window manager controls the sequence of windows on the desktop.
		  When you open a window, the window manager assigns the window to a layer. The
		  window manager usually assigns new windows to layer four.</para>
		<para>The raise and lower operations work within layers. You can raise
		  windows to the top of the stacking order within a layer. You can lower windows
		  to the bottom of the stacking order within a layer. You can not raise a window
		  above a window in a higher layer. Similarly, you can not lower a window below a
		  window in a lower layer. </para>
		<para>Panels and desktop background objects are also members of layers.
		  You can change the layer or level that a panel resides in. In this way, you can
		  specify whether you want the panel to be above or below windows.</para>
		<para>Use the <application>Desk Guide</application> tasklist to view
		  which layer your windows, panels, and desktop icons are in.</para>
		<para>To change the layer that a window is in perform the following
		  steps: </para>
		<orderedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To increment the layer that the window is in by one, choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Stacking</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Upper layer</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.</para>
			 <para>To decrement the layer that the window is in by one, choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Stacking</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Lower layer</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.</para>
			 <note>
				<para>The desktop is in layer zero. If you decrease the layer that
				  a window is in to below zero, the window is no longer visible on the desktop.
				  However, a button that represents the window appears on the <application>
				  Tasklist</application> and <application>Desk Guide</application> applets. You
				  can use the <application>Tasklist</application> applet to close the window.
				  </para>
			 </note>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-37">
		<title>To Raise and Lower a Window</title>
		<para>The raise and lower operations work within layers. You can raise
		  windows to the top of the stacking order within a layer. You can lower windows
		  to the bottom of the stacking order within a layer. You can not raise a window
		  above a window in a higher layer. Similarly, you can not lower a window below a
		  window in a lower layer. </para>
		<para>To raise a window to the top of the stacking order perform one of
		  the following actions:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Right-click on the titlebar or the border of the window.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu, then choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Stacking</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Raise</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>To lower a window to the bottom of the stacking order perform one
		  of the following actions:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>If the window is at the top of the stacking order, right-click
				on the titlebar or the border of the window.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu, then choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Stacking</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Lower</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you want your windows to rise when they receive focus, configure
		  your desktop in the <application>Sawfish window manager</application> capplet
		  as follows:</para>
		<informaltable frame="topbot">
		  <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
			 colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
			 <colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
			 <thead>
				<row rowsep="1">
				  <entry>
					 <para>Dialog</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Option</para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Set To</para></entry>
				</row>
			 </thead>
			 <tbody>
				<row>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guilabel>Focus behavior</guilabel></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guilabel> Focus</guilabel></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>
						<guilabel>Raise windows when they are focused
						  </guilabel></para></entry>
				  <entry>
					 <para>Selected</para></entry>
				</row>
			 </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-704">
		<title>To Ignore a Window</title>
		<para>You can configure a window so that the window manager ignores the
		  window. When the window manager ignores a window, the window does not have a
		  frame. </para>
		<para>To configure a window so that the window manager ignores the
		  window, open the 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. Choose 
		  <menuchoice>
			 <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
			 <guimenuitem>Ignored</guimenuitem>
		  </menuchoice>.</para>
		<para>To reconfigure a window so that the window manager does not ignore
		  the window, open the 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. To open the 
		  <guimenu>Window </guimenu> menu, press-and-hold the modifier key then
		  middle-click on any part of the window. The default modifier key is the meta
		  key.</para>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-38">
		<title>To Set a Window to Stick</title>
		<para>When a window is set to stick, the window appears in any workspace
		  or viewport that you view. </para>
		<para>To set a window to stick, perform one of the following
		  actions:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Sticky</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. To set the window to appear only in the current
				workspace or viewport, choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Sticky</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> again.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Right-click on the button that represents the window in the
				<application> Tasklist</application> applet, then choose 
				<guimenuitem>Stick</guimenuitem>. To set the window to appear only
				in the current workspace or viewport, right-click on the button that represents
				the window, then choose 
				<guimenuitem>Unstick </guimenuitem>.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-39">
		<title>To Group Windows</title>
		<para>You can group windows so that you can minimize and restore several
		  windows at one time. You can use window groups to group windows in different
		  applications. You work with window groups from any 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. To display a list of your window
		  groups, open a 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu then choose 
		  <guimenuitem> In group</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<para>When you open a window on the desktop, a window group is created
		  for the window. The window is the sole member of this window group. You can add
		  the window to another group. You can also remove a window from a group.</para>
		<para>You can use the <application>Sawfish window manager</application>
		  capplet to create a 
		  <glossterm>persistent window group</glossterm>. A persistent window
		  group remains in your window group list even after you end and restart a
		  session. </para>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-40">
		  <title>To Create a Persistent Window Group</title>
		  <para>A persistent window group remains in your window group list even
			 after you end and restart a session. You can create a persistent window group,
			 and then assign windows to be part of the group. You can also configure your
			 desktop to apply certain actions that you perform on one window to all windows
			 in the group.</para>
		  <para>To create a persistent window group perform the following
			 steps:</para>
		  <orderedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>To start the <application>Control Center</application> open
				  the 
				  <guimenu>Global Menu</guimenu>, then choose 
				  <menuchoice>
					 <guimenu>Programs</guimenu>
					 <guisubmenu>Settings</guisubmenu>
					 <guisubmenu>Sawfish window manager</guisubmenu>
					 <guimenuitem>Miscellaneous</guimenuitem>
				  </menuchoice>. You use the 
				  <guilabel>Persistent group ids</guilabel> list box to create
				  persistent window groups.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>To create a persistent window group, click on the 
				  <guibutton> Add</guibutton> button to display the 
				  <guilabel>Add</guilabel> dialog. Use the 
				  <guilabel>Add</guilabel> drop-down combination box to specify a
				  name for the group. Click 
				  <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
				<para>To edit the name of a persistent window group, click on the 
				  <guibutton> Edit</guibutton> button to display the 
				  <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> dialog. Use the 
				  <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> drop-down combination box to specify a
				  name for the group. Click 
				  <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
				<para>To delete a persistent window group, select the group in the 
				  <guilabel> Persistent group ids</guilabel> list box. Click on the
				  
				  <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> option to delete the selected
				  group.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>Click 
				  <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save your changes. </para>
			 </listitem>
		  </orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-41">
		  <title>To Add a Window to a Window Group</title>
		  <para>To add a window to another window group open the 
			 <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu for the window. Choose 
			 <guimenuitem>In group</guimenuitem>. A list of all the available
			 window groups is displayed. Choose the window group to which you want to add
			 the window.</para>
		  <note>
			 <para>A window can only be in one window group at a time.</para>
		  </note>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-42">
		  <title>To Remove a Window From a Window Group</title>
		  <para>To remove a window from a window group open the 
			 <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu for the window. Choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>In group</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>New group</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>. A new window group is created for the window. The
			 window is the sole member of this window group. The new window group has the
			 same name as the window that you remove from the window group.</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-43">
		  <title>To Minimize a Window Group</title>
		  <para>You can configure your desktop so that when you minimize one
			 window in a window group, all windows are minimized. Configure your desktop in
			 the <application> Sawfish window manager</application> capplet as
			 follows:</para>
		  <informaltable frame="topbot">
			 <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
				colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<thead>
				  <row rowsep="1">
					 <entry>
						<para>Dialog</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Option</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Set To</para></entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
				  <row>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Minimizing and
							 Maximizing</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Minimizing</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Iconifying a window also iconifies the
							 </guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Group</guilabel></para></entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			 </tgroup>
		  </informaltable>
		  <para>To minimize all windows in the window group, minimize one of the
			 windows. </para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-44">
		  <title>To Restore a Minimized Window Group</title>
		  <para>You can configure your desktop so that when you restore one
			 window in a window group, all windows are restored. Configure your desktop in
			 the <application> Sawfish window manager</application> capplet as
			 follows:</para>
		  <informaltable frame="topbot">
			 <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
				colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<thead>
				  <row rowsep="1">
					 <entry>
						<para>Dialog</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Option</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Set To</para></entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
				  <row>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Minimizing and
							 Maximizing</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Minimizing</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Uniconifying a window also uniconifies
							 the</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Group</guilabel></para></entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			 </tgroup>
		  </informaltable>
		  <para>To restore all windows in the window group, restore one of the
			 windows. </para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-45">
		  <title>To Close a Window Group</title>
		  <para>To close all windows in a window group press 
			 <keycap>Shift</keycap> then click on the 
			 <guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button on the window
			 frame.</para>
		</sect3>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-705">
		<title>Creating a Matched Window</title>
		<para>You can configure a window to have particular characteristics when
		  you open the window. For example, you can configure a window to open maximized,
		  in a particular workspace, with a particular frame style. To configure a window
		  that opens with particular characteristics, you must create a matched window.
		  </para>
		<para>To create a matched window, you use the 
		  <guilabel>Matched Windows</guilabel> dialog in the <application>Sawfish
		  window manager</application> capplet. In the dialog, you specify the name of
		  the window to match, and characteristics to assign to that window. When a
		  window opens, <application>Sawfish</application> checks whether the window
		  corresponds to a matched window in the 
		  <guilabel> Matched Windows</guilabel> dialog. If the window does
		  correspond to a matched window, the window opens with the characteristics
		  assigned to the matched window.</para>
		<para>You can also create a matched window to match properties of the
		  window other than the name. For example, you can create a matched window to
		  match the class of the window or the name of the window icon.</para>
		<para>You can assign many characteristics to the matched window. You can
		  assign characteristics such as placement behavior, focus behavior, frame style,
		  and other miscellaneous characteristics.</para>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-46">
		<title>To Move a Window to Another Workspace</title>
		<para>You can move a window to another workspace in either of the
		  following ways:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu </para>
			 <para>Open the 
				<guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu. To move the window to the next
				workspace choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Send window to</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem> Next workspace</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. To move the window to the previous workspace choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Send window to</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem> Previous workspace</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Drag the window to another workspace</para>
			 <para>You can drag a window to another workspace if you configure the
				edge flip feature appropriately. The edge flip feature enables you to select
				another workspace when you point to the edge of the screen. To use the edge
				flip feature you must configure your desktop in the <application>Sawfish window
				manager </application> capplet as follows:</para>
			 <informaltable frame="topbot">
				<tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="COLSPEC0"
				  colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC1" colwidth="25*"/><colspec
				  colname="COLSPEC2" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC3" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <thead>
					 <row rowsep="1">
						<entry>
						  <para>Dialog</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Option</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Set To</para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </thead>
				  <tbody>
					 <row>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC0">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC1">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC2">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Select the next desktop when the pointer hits
								the screen edge</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC3">
						  <para> Selected</para></entry>
					 </row>
					 <row>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Hitting the screen edge selects the
								next</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> workspace</guilabel></para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </tbody>
				</tgroup>
			 </informaltable>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The configuration of your desktop can mean that when you move a
		  window to another workspace, a workspace is added.</para>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-47">
		<title>To Copy a Window to Another Workspace</title>
		<para>You can use the 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu to copy a window to another workspace.
		  When you copy a window to another workspace, the window appears in the
		  workspace when you switch to the workspace. The window sticks to the workspace
		  that you copy the window to, and the workspace that you copy the window
		  from.</para>
		<para>To copy a window to the next workspace, open the 
		  <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu, then choose 
		  <menuchoice>
			 <guimenu>Send window to</guimenu>
			 <guimenuitem> Copy to next</guimenuitem>
		  </menuchoice>. </para>
		<para>To copy a window to the previous workspace, open the 
		  <guimenu>Window </guimenu> menu, then choose 
		  <menuchoice>
			 <guimenu>Send window to</guimenu>
			 <guimenuitem>Copy to previous</guimenuitem>
		  </menuchoice>. </para>
		<para>To remove all copies of a window except one, open the 
		  <guimenu>Window </guimenu> menu from the window that you want to
		  retain. Choose 
		  <menuchoice>
			 <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
			 <guimenuitem>Sticky</guimenuitem>
		  </menuchoice>, then choose 
		  <menuchoice>
			 <guimenu>Toggle</guimenu>
			 <guimenuitem>Sticky </guimenuitem>
		  </menuchoice> again.</para>
		<para>The configuration of your desktop can mean that when you copy a
		  window to another workspace, a workspace is added. For more information, see
		  <xref linkend="gossawfish-710"/>.</para>
		<note>
		  <para>When you copy a window to another workspace, only the window in
			 the current workspace is represented in the <application>Desk
			 Guide</application> applet.</para>
		</note>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-48">
		<title>To Move a Window Between Viewports</title>
		<para>You can move a window between viewports in the same workspace. You
		  can move a window between viewports in the following ways: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Drag the window to the viewport</para>
			 <para>Drag the window to the edge of the screen next to the viewport
				to which you want to move the window. Drag the window past the edge of the
				screen so that the window straddles the current viewport and the next viewport.
				Click on the viewport to which you want to move the window. Drag the window the
				rest of the way into the viewport.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the edge flip feature</para>
			 <para>You can drag a window to another viewport if you configure the
				edge flip feature appropriately. The edge flip feature enables you to select
				another viewport when you point to the edge of the screen. To use this edge
				flip feature you must configure your desktop in the <application>Sawfish window
				manager </application> capplet as follows:</para>
			 <informaltable frame="topbot">
				<tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="COLSPEC4"
				  colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC5" colwidth="25*"/><colspec
				  colname="COLSPEC6" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC7" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <thead>
					 <row rowsep="1">
						<entry>
						  <para>Dialog</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Option</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Set To</para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </thead>
				  <tbody>
					 <row>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC4">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC5">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC6">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Select the next desktop when the pointer hits
								the screen edge</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC7">
						  <para> Selected</para></entry>
					 </row>
					 <row>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Hitting the screen edge selects the
								next</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> viewport</guilabel></para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </tbody>
				</tgroup>
			 </informaltable>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Drag the window in the <application>Desk Guide</application>
				applet: </para>
			 <para>Find the button that represents the window that you want to
				move in the <application>Desk Guide</application> applet. Middle-click and hold
				on the button and drag the button to the new location. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gossawfish-716">
	 <title>Manipulating Workspaces and Viewports</title>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>workspaces</primary>
		<secondary>manipulating</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <indexterm>
		<primary>viewports</primary>
		<secondary>manipulating</secondary>
	 </indexterm>
	 <para>This section describes how to manipulate workspaces and
		viewports.</para>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-49">
		<title>To Switch Between Workspaces</title>
		<para>You can switch between workspaces in any of the following ways:
		  </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the <application>Desk Guide</application> applet: Click on
				the workspace that you want to switch to in the <application>Desk Guide
				</application> applet.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the 
				<guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu: Middle-click on the desktop
				background to open the 
				<guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu, then choose 
				<guimenuitem> Workspaces</guimenuitem>. This action opens a list of
				your workspaces and workspace-related menu items. Choose the workspace that you
				want to switch to from the list. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use a shortcut key: The default shortcut keys to switch between
				the workspaces are: 
				<itemizedlist>
				  <listitem>
					 <para>
						<keycombo><keycap>Modifier</keycap><keycap>Right arrow key</keycap></keycombo>: Select the next
						workspace. </para>
				  </listitem>
				  <listitem>
					 <para>
						<keycombo><keycap>Modifier</keycap><keycap>Left arrow key</keycap></keycombo>: Select the
						previous workspace. </para>
				  </listitem>
				</itemizedlist></para>
			 <para>The default modifier key is the meta key.</para>
			 <note>
				<para>The configuration of your desktop can mean that when you use
				  a shortcut key to select a workspace, another workspace is added. For more
				  information, see <xref linkend="gossawfish-710"/>.</para>
			 </note>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the edge flip feature: Move the mouse pointer to the edge
				of the screen. To use this edge flip feature you must configure your desktop in
				the <application>Sawfish window manager</application> capplet as follows:
				</para>
			 <informaltable frame="topbot">
				<tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="COLSPEC8"
				  colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC9" colwidth="25*"/><colspec
				  colname="COLSPEC10" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC11" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <thead>
					 <row rowsep="1">
						<entry>
						  <para>Dialog</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Option</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Set To</para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </thead>
				  <tbody>
					 <row>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC8">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC9">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC10">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Select the next desktop when the pointer hits
								the screen edge</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC11">
						  <para> Selected </para></entry>
					 </row>
					 <row>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Hitting the screen edge selects the
								next</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> workspace</guilabel></para></entry>
					 </row>
					 <row>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC8">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC9">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC10">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Only flip when interactively moving a
								window</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC11">
						  <para>Unselected </para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </tbody>
				</tgroup>
			 </informaltable>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-50">
		<title>To Add Workspaces</title>
		<para>You can add workspaces to your desktop in the following ways:
		  </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Use the 
				<guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu: For more information see
				<xref linkend="gossawfish-709"/>.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Specify a minimum number of workspaces for your desktop: For
				more information see <xref linkend="gossawfish-710"/>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Configure your desktop to add workspaces automatically when you
				perform particular actions: For more information see
				<xref linkend="gossawfish-711"/>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-709">
		  <title>To Add a Workspace Using the Root Menu</title>
		  <para>To add a workspace to your workspace list middle-click on the
			 desktop background to open the 
			 <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu. Choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu> Workspaces</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Insert workspace</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>. The new workspace is inserted to the right of the
			 current workspace.</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-710">
		  <title>To Specify a Minimum Number of Workspaces</title>
		  <para>You can use the <application>Sawfish window manager</application>
			 capplet to specify the minimum number of workspaces that appear on your desktop
			 when you start a session. To specify a minimum number of workspaces, configure
			 your desktop in the <application>Sawfish window manager</application> as
			 follows: </para>
		  <informaltable frame="topbot">
			 <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
				colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<thead>
				  <row rowsep="1">
					 <entry>
						<para>Dialog</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Option</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Set To</para></entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
				  <row>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Required number of workspaces</para></entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			 </tgroup>
		  </informaltable>
		  <para>If the number of workspaces you specify is greater than the
			 current number of workspaces, the extra workspaces are added to the desktop. If
			 the number of workspaces you specify is less than the current number of
			 workspaces, the extra workspaces remain on the desktop.</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="gossawfish-711">
		  <title>To Add Workspaces Automatically</title>
		  <para>You can configure the <application>Sawfish window
			 manager</application> capplet to add a workspace automatically in particular
			 situations. A workspace can be added automatically when the current workspace
			 is first or last in your workspace list, and you perform particular
			 actions.</para>
		  <para>A workspace is added if you perform one of the following
			 actions:</para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>If the workspace is first, and you perform one of the
				  following actions: 
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>Move the workspace to the left.</para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>Send or copy a window to the previous workspace with
						  the 
						  <guimenu> Window</guimenu> menu.</para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist></para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>If the workspace is last, and you perform one of the
				  following actions: 
				  <itemizedlist>
					 <listitem>
						<para>Move the workspace to the right.</para>
					 </listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>Send or copy a window to the next workspace with the 
						  <guimenu> Window</guimenu> menu.</para>
					 </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist></para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		  <para>To add workspaces when you select or move workspaces, configure
			 your desktop in the <application>Sawfish window manager</application> capplet
			 as follows:</para>
		  <informaltable frame="topbot">
			 <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec
				colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="25*"/><colspec colwidth="25*"/>
				<thead>
				  <row rowsep="1">
					 <entry>
						<para>Dialog</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Option</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Set To</para></entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
				  <row>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>When passing the first or last workspace
							 </guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> keep-going </guilabel></para></entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			 </tgroup>
		  </informaltable>
		  <para>In this configuration, a workspace is added if you perform one of
			 the following actions:</para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>If the workspace is first, and you select the previous
				  workspace or move the workspace to the left.</para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>If the workspace is last, and you select the next workspace
				  or move the workspace to the right.</para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		  <para>To add a workspace when you point to the edge of the screen,
			 configure your desktop in the <application>Sawfish window manager</application>
			 capplet as follows:</para>
		  <informaltable frame="topbot">
			 <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="COLSPEC0"
				colwidth="25*"/>
				<colspec colname="COLSPEC1" colwidth="25*"/><colspec
				colname="COLSPEC2" colwidth="25*"/>
				<colspec colname="COLSPEC3" colwidth="25*"/>
				<thead>
				  <row rowsep="1">
					 <entry>
						<para>Dialog</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Option</para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>Set To</para></entry>
				  </row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
				  <row>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel>When passing the first or last workspace
							 </guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry>
						<para>
						  <guilabel> keep-going </guilabel></para></entry>
				  </row>
				  <row>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC0">
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC1">
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC2">
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Select the next desktop when the pointer hits
							 screen edge </guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC3">
						<para> Selected</para></entry>
				  </row>
				  <row>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC0">
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC1">
						<para>
						  <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC2">
						<para>
						  <guilabel>Hitting the screen edge selects the
							 next</guilabel></para></entry>
					 <entry colname="COLSPEC3">
						<para>
						  <guilabel> workspace</guilabel></para></entry>
				  </row>
				</tbody>
			 </tgroup>
		  </informaltable>
		  <para>In this configuration, a workspace is added if you perform one of
			 the following actions:
			 <itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				  <para>If the workspace is first, and you point to the left edge
					 of the screen.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				  <para>If the workspace is last, and you point to the right edge
					 of the screen.</para>
				</listitem>
			 </itemizedlist></para>
		</sect3>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-51">
		<title>To Name Workspaces</title>
		<para>The default names of your workspaces are <literal>space
		  1</literal>, <literal> space 2</literal>, <literal>space 3</literal>, and so
		  on. You can assign names to your workspaces in the <application>Sawfish window
		  manager</application> capplet. </para>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-52">
		<title>To Merge Workspaces</title>
		<para>When you merge a workspace the windows in the workspace are moved
		  to another workspace, and the empty workspace is deleted.</para>
		<para>To merge a workspace, middle-click on the desktop background to
		  open the 
		  <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu. Choose 
		  <guimenu>Workspaces</guimenu>, then perform one of the following
		  actions: 
		  <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem>
				<para>To merge the workspace with the next workspace choose 
				  <guimenuitem> Merge with next</guimenuitem>. The empty workspace
				  is deleted. </para>
			 </listitem>
			 <listitem>
				<para>To merge the workspace with the previous workspace choose 
				  <guimenuitem> Merge with previous</guimenuitem>. The empty
				  workspace is deleted.</para>
			 </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist></para>
		<note>
		  <para>The number of workspaces on your desktop is never less than the
			 minimum number of workspaces that is specified in the <application>Sawfish
			 window manager</application> capplet. If you merge workspaces, the empty
			 workspace might not be deleted because your desktop must always have the
			 minimum number of workspaces.</para>
		</note>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-53">
		<title>To Move a Workspace</title>
		<para>To move a workspace middle-click on the desktop background to open
		  the 
		  <guimenu> Root</guimenu> menu. Choose 
		  <guimenu>Workspaces</guimenu>, then perform one of the following
		  actions:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To move the workspace to the right of the current workspace
				choose 
				<guimenuitem>Move workspace right</guimenuitem>. The workspace
				swaps position with the next workspace. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To move the workspace to the left of the current workspace
				choose 
				<guimenuitem>Move workspace left</guimenuitem>. The workspace swaps
				position with the previous workspace. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>When you move a workspace, all the windows in the workspace are
		  moved. The name of the workspace does not move. For example, if you move
		  <literal> space 1</literal> to the right, the windows move to the next
		  workspace. The workspace takes the name of the next workspace, <literal>space
		  2</literal>. In summary, when you move <literal>space 1</literal> to the right,
		  all the windows in <literal>space 1</literal> move to <literal>space
		  2</literal>. </para>
		<para>The configuration of your desktop can mean that when you move a
		  workspace, another workspace is added.</para>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-54">
		<title>To Switch Between Viewports</title>
		<para>You can switch between viewports in either of the following
		  ways:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Click on the viewport in the <application>Desk
				Guide</application> applet.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Move the mouse pointer to the edge of the screen. To use this
				edge flip feature you must configure your desktop in the <application>Sawfish
				window manager</application> capplet as follows:</para>
			 <informaltable frame="topbot">
				<tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><colspec colname="COLSPEC8"
				  colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC9" colwidth="25*"/><colspec
				  colname="COLSPEC10" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <colspec colname="COLSPEC11" colwidth="25*"/>
				  <thead>
					 <row rowsep="1">
						<entry>
						  <para>Dialog</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Tabbed Section </para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Option</para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>Set To</para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </thead>
				  <tbody>
					 <row>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC8">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC9">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC10">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Select the next desktop when the pointer hits
								the screen edge</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC11">
						  <para> Selected </para></entry>
					 </row>
					 <row>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Hitting the screen edge selects the
								next</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry>
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> viewport</guilabel></para></entry>
					 </row>
					 <row>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC8">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Workspaces </guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC9">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel> Edge Flipping</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC10">
						  <para>
							 <guilabel>Only flip when interactively moving a
								window</guilabel></para></entry>
						<entry colname="COLSPEC11">
						  <para>Unselected </para></entry>
					 </row>
				  </tbody>
				</tgroup>
			 </informaltable>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 </sect2>
	 <sect2 id="gossawfish-55">
		<title>To Add Viewports</title>
		<para>To add viewports to your workspaces follow these steps: </para>
		<orderedlist>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>To start the <application>Control Center</application> open the
				
				<guimenu>Global Menu</guimenu>, then choose 
				<menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Programs</guimenu>
				  <guisubmenu>Settings</guisubmenu>
				  <guisubmenu>Sawfish window manager</guisubmenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Workspaces</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>. </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>On the 
				<guilabel>Workspaces</guilabel> tabbed section, use the 
				<guilabel>Columns</guilabel> and 
				<guilabel>Rows</guilabel> spin boxes to specify the following:
				<itemizedlist>
				  <listitem>
					 <para>The number of viewports in each workspace.</para>
				  </listitem>
				  <listitem>
					 <para>The structure of the viewports in each workspace in the
						<application> Desk Guide</application> applet.</para>
				  </listitem>
				</itemizedlist></para>
			 <para>For example, if you want four viewports in your workspaces, and
				you want the <application>Desk Guide</application> to display the viewports as
				two columns and two rows. To specify this configuration, enter <literal>2
				</literal> in both the 
				<guilabel>Columns</guilabel> and 
				<guilabel>Rows</guilabel> spin boxes.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
			 <para>Click 
				<guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save your changes. </para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<note>
		  <para>If you do not want any viewports, specify <literal>1</literal> in
			 both the 
			 <guilabel>Columns</guilabel> and 
			 <guilabel>Rows</guilabel> spin boxes.</para>
		</note>
	 </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter> 