<chapter id="gosoverview-1">
  <title>Overview of the GNOME Desktop</title>
  <highlights>
    <para>This chapter introduces you to the features and main components
of the GNOME Desktop. Before you start to use the desktop environment read
this chapter to familiarize yourself with the various features, and how the
main components work. The desktop environment is very configurable, so this
chapter describes the typical default configuration, covering the following
topics.</para>
  </highlights>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-5">
    <title>Introducing Desktop Environment Components</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>desktop environment components, introducing</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>When you start a desktop environment session for the first
time, you should see a default startup screen, with panels, windows, and various
icons. <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-1"/> shows a typical desktop environment. </para>
    <figure id="gosoverview-FIG-1">
      <title>A Typical Desktop Environment</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/typical_anno_desktop.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>A typical desktop environment. Callouts: Menu Bar, Top edge panel, Desktop, Windows, Window List applet, Bottom edge panel, Workspace Switcher applet.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>The major components of the desktop environment are as follows: <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Panels</para><para>Panels are areas in your desktop environment from which you can access
all of your system applications and menus. Panels are very configurable. A
particularly important panel in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-1"/> is the
top edge panel. The top edge panel includes the <application>Menu Bar</application>.
The <application>Menu Bar</application> contains two special menus, as follows:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu: Contains all applications
and configuration tools. This menu also includes the file manager and the
help browser. To start the file manager, choose <guimenuitem>Home Folder</guimenuitem>
from the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu: Contains various commands
that perform desktop environment functions, for example <guimenuitem>Search
for Files</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Log Out</guimenuitem>. </para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Click on the icon at the extreme right of the top edge panel to display
a list of all open windows.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Menus</para><para>You can access all desktop environment functions through menus. The
top edge panel contains menus, so you can use a combination of menus and panels
to perform your tasks. You can use the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu
and the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu to access almost all of the standard
applications, commands, and configuration options. </para><para>You can also access almost all of the standard applications, commands,
and configuration options from the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>. You can access
the items in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
menus from the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>. You can add the <guimenu>Main
Menu</guimenu> as a button to your panels.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Windows</para><para>You can display many windows at the same time. You can run different
applications in each window. The window manager provides frames and buttons
for windows. The window manager enables you to perform standard actions such
as move, close, and resize windows. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Workspaces</para><para>You can subdivide your desktop environment into separate <firstterm>workspaces</firstterm>. A workspace is a discrete area in which you can work.
You can specify the number of workspaces in your desktop environment. You
can switch to a different workspace, but you can only display one workspace
at a time.</para></listitem><listitem><para><application>Nautilus</application> file manager</para><para>The <application>Nautilus</application> file manager provides an integrated
access point to your files and applications. You can display the contents
of your files within a file manager window, or open the files in the appropriate
application from the file manager. You can use the file manager to manage
your files and folders. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Desktop</para><para>The desktop is behind all of the other components on the desktop. The
desktop is an active component of the user interface. You can place objects
on the desktop to quickly access  your files and directories, or to start
applications that you use often. You can also right-click on the desktop to
open a menu.</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location</para><para>The <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location provides an access point
to some of the key features of the desktop environment. You can access your
GNOME applications and configuration tools from the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel>
location. You can also access programs that enable you to configure your system
as a server, and to choose other system settings.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Desktop environment preferences</para><para>The desktop environment contains dedicated <firstterm>preference tools</firstterm>. Each tool controls a particular part of the behavior of the
desktop environment. To start a preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>Desktop Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Choose the item that you want to configure from the submenus.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
    <para>The most powerful features of the desktop environment are the high degree
of configurability and the multiple ways that you can perform tasks.</para>
    <para>The desktop environment provides interoperability of the desktop environment
components. Usually, you can perform the same action in several different
ways. For example, you can start applications from panels, from menus, or
from the desktop.</para>
    <para>Your system administrator can make configuration changes to suit your
needs, so that the desktop environment might not be exactly the same as described
in this chapter. Nevertheless, this chapter provides a useful quick guide
to how to work with the desktop environment. </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-502">
    <title>Panels</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>panels</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>You can add or delete panels at any time. When you start a session for
the first time, the desktop environment usually contains a panel at the top
edge of the screen, and a panel at the bottom edge of the screen. </para>
    <para>You can perform the following actions with panels:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create panels.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Delete panels.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hide panels.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add objects to panels.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Manipulate panel objects.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-26">
      <title>To Create Panels</title>
      <para>To add a panel, right-click on a vacant space on any panel, then choose <guimenuitem>New Panel</guimenuitem>. The new panel is added to your desktop environment.
The new panel contains no objects. You can customize the new panel to suit
your preferences. You can add objects to the panel to fit your own requirements.
You can also change the background of the panel. You can create as many panels
as you want.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-508">
      <title>To Delete Panels</title>
      <para>To delete a panel, right-click on the panel then choose <guimenuitem>Delete This Panel</guimenuitem>.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-24">
      <title>To Hide Panels</title>
      <para>Panels can have hide buttons at each end of the panel. You click on
the hide buttons to hide or show the panel.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-4">
      <title>To Add Objects to Panels</title>
      <para>A panel can hold several types of objects. The panel in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-28"/>
contains each type of panel object. </para>
      <figure id="gosoverview-FIG-28">
        <title>A Panel With Various Panel Objects</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/sample_anno_panel.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>A panel with various panel objects. Callouts: Calculator launcher, Menu, CD Player applet, Drawer, Lock button.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>You can add any of the following objects to all types of panels:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Applets</para>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>applets</primary>
            <secondary>overview</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para><firstterm>Applets</firstterm> are small, interactive applications that
reside within a panel, for example <application>CD Player</application> in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-28"/>. Each applet has a simple user interface that
you can operate with the mouse or keyboard. The following applets appear in
your panels by default:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><application>Menu Bar</application>: Provides access to the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu and the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu. You can
use the menus to access your applications, preference tools, and other desktop
environment tasks.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><application>Window List</application>: Displays a button
for each window that is open. You can click on a window list button to minimize
and restore windows. By default, <application>Window List</application> appears
in the edge panel at the bottom of the screen.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><application>Workspace Switcher</application>: Displays a
visual representation of your workspaces. You can use <application>Workspace
Switcher</application> to switch between workspaces. By default, <application>Workspace Switcher</application> appears in the edge panel at the bottom of
the screen.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>To add an applet to a panel, right-click on a vacant space on the panel,
then choose <guimenuitem>Add to Panel</guimenuitem>. Choose the applet that
you require from one of the following submenus:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Accessories</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Amusements</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Internet</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Multimedia</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Utility</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Launchers</para>
          <para>A <firstterm>launcher</firstterm> starts a particular application, executes
a command, or opens a file. The calculator icon in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-28"/>
is a launcher for the <application>Calculator</application> application. A
launcher can reside in a panel or in a menu. Click on the launcher to perform
the action that is associated with the launcher.</para>
          <para>You can create your own launchers for applications. For example, you
can create a launcher for a word processor application that you use frequently,
and place the launcher in a panel for convenient access. To add a new launcher
to a panel, right-click on a vacant space on the panel, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Launcher</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. </para>
          <para>Alternatively, to add a launcher from a menu, right-click on a vacant
space on the panel, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Launcher from menu</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Choose
the launcher to add from the submenus.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Buttons</para>
          <para>You can add buttons to your panels to provide quick access to common
functions. You can add the following buttons to your panels:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Force Quit</guibutton>: Use this button to terminate
applications that do not respond to your commands.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Lock</guibutton>: Click on this button to lock
your screen. The lock icon in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-28"/> is the <guibutton>Lock</guibutton> button. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Log Out</guibutton>: Click on this button to end
your session</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Run</guibutton>: Click on this button to open the <guilabel>Run Application</guilabel> dialog, from which you can run commands.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Screenshot</guibutton>: Click on this button to
take a screenshot of the screen.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Search</guibutton>: Click on this button to open
the <application>Search Tool</application> application, from which you can
search for files. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Show Desktop</guibutton>: Click on this button
to minimize all windows and show the desktop.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>To add the buttons to a panel, right-click on a vacant space on the
panel, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Actions</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You can then choose the button you require. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Menus</para>
          <para>You can access all desktop environment functions through menus. The
default panels contain menus, so you can use a combination of menus and panels
to perform your tasks. To open a menu from a panel, click on the icon that
represents the menu. To open a menu from the <application>Menu Bar</application>,
click on the text that represents the menu. </para>
          <para>Menus that you add to your panels are represented by an icon with an
arrow. The arrow indicates that the icon represents a menu. The icon in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-28"/> is the icon that is displayed when you add the <guimenuitem>Desktop Preferences</guimenuitem> menu to a panel.</para>
          <para>You can add the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> to any of your panels.
To add the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> to a panel, right-click on a vacant
space on the panel, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Main Menu</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          <para>You can also add the <application>Menu Bar</application> to any of your
panels. To add the <application>Menu Bar</application> to a panel, right-click
on a vacant space on the panel, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Menu Bar</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Drawers</para>
          <para><firstterm>Drawers</firstterm> are sliding extensions to a panel that
you can open or close from a drawer icon, as shown in <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-28"/>.
 Drawers can help you to organize your work when you run a lot of applications
simultaneously. You can place all the same functional elements in a drawer
that you can put in any other type of panel. </para>
          <para>To add a drawer to a panel, right-click on a vacant space on the panel,
then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Drawer</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. </para>
          <para>To open a drawer click on the drawer. To close a drawer click on the
drawer again.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-21">
      <title>To Manipulate Panel Objects</title>
      <para>You can manipulate panel objects in the following ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move objects within a panel, or to another panel.</para>
          <para>You can move any object to another location in the panel. You can also
move an object from one panel to another panel. Use the middle mouse button
to drag the panel object to the new location.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Copy menu items to a panel.</para>
          <para>Drag the item from the menu to the panel. Alternatively, if the menu
item is a launcher right-click on the menu item, then choose <guimenuitem>Add this launcher to panel</guimenuitem>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-42">
    <title>Menus</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>menus</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>You can access all desktop environment functions through menus. Your
default panels contain menus, so you can use a combination of menus and panels
to perform your tasks. The top edge panel contains the <application>Menu Bar</application>. The <application>Menu Bar</application> contains <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menus. </para>
    <para>You can use the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu and the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu to access almost all of the standard applications,
commands, and configuration options. You can also access the items in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menus from the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>.</para>
    <para>To add a <application>Menu Bar</application> to a panel, right-click
on the panel then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Menu Bar</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
    <para>To add a <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> to a panel, right-click on the
panel then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu><guimenuitem>Main Menu</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> is
represented by a stylized footprint, as follows:</para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/footprint_icon.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Main Menu icon.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Click on the <guibutton>Main Menu</guibutton> button on a panel to open
the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>. </para>
    <para>You can add as many additional menus as you want to any of your panels.
To open a menu that you add to a panel, click on the menu icon on the panel.
You can perform other actions on your menus, such as copy menu items to panels.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-18">
    <title>Windows</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>windows</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>You can display many windows at the same time in your desktop environment.
Each window has a frame. The window frame contains active control elements
that you can use to work with the window.</para>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-16">
      <title>Types of Windows</title>
      <para>The desktop environment features the following types of window:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Application windows</para>
          <para>When you run an application, a frame usually borders the window. The
top edge of the application window contains a titlebar. The titlebar contains
buttons that you can use to work with the window. The buttons in an application
window frame enable you to perform actions such as open the <guimenu>Window
Menu</guimenu>, or close the window. The <guimenu>Window Menu</guimenu> provides
commands that you can perform on the window.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Dialog windows</para>
          <para>Dialog windows are associated with interactive processes. A dialog window
consists of the window frame, and a single interactive pane that provides
information and controls for the user. This manual refers to the interactive
part of a dialog window as a dialog. The frame of a dialog window contains
buttons that enable you to open the <guimenu>Window Menu</guimenu>, or to
close the dialog window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-32">
      <title>To Manipulate Windows</title>
      <para>You use the frame of an application window or dialog window to perform
various actions with the window. Most of the control elements are located
on the top edge of the window frame. <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-33"/> shows
the top edge of a frame for a typical application window.</para>
      <figure id="gosoverview-FIG-33">
        <title>Top Edge of Frame for a Typical Application Window</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/titlebar_anno_window.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Top edge of application window frame. Callouts: Window Menu button, Titlebar, Minimize, Maximize, Close Window buttons.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>The active control elements of the window frame are as follows: </para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="41.65*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="58.35*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Control Element</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Description </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para><guibutton>Window Menu</guibutton>
button</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>Click on
the <guibutton>Window Menu</guibutton> button to open the <guimenu>Window
Menu</guimenu>. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Titlebar</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>You can use the titlebar to move and shade the window. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para><guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Click on the <guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button
to minimize the window. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para><guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>You can use the <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton>
button to maximize and restore the window.</para>
                <para>To maximize a window
click on the <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button. To restore the window
click on the <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton> button again. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para><guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Click on the <guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button to close the window. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para>Border</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para>Right-click on the border to open the <guimenu>Window Menu</guimenu>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>To change the size of windows grab the border of the window, but not
the titlebar. Drag the border until the window is the size that you require.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-20">
      <title>To Give Focus to a Window</title>
      <para>A window that has focus can receive input from the mouse and the keyboard.
Only one window can have focus at a time. The window that has focus has a
different appearance than other windows. </para>
      <para>You can use the following elements to give focus to a window:</para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33.62*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="66.38*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Element</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Action</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Mouse</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>Click on the window, if the window is visible. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>Shortcut keys</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>Use shortcut keys to switch between
the windows that are open. To give focus to a window, release the keys. The
default shortcut keys to switch between windows are <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <application>Window List</application>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>Click on the button that represents the window in <application>Window List</application>. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>
                  <application>Workspace Switcher</application>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>Click on the window that you want to give focus to in the <application>Workspace
Switcher</application> display.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-39">
    <title>Workspaces</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>workspaces</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>You can display many windows at the same time in your desktop environment.
Your windows are displayed in subdivisions of your desktop environment that
are called workspaces. A workspace is a discrete area in which you can work. </para>
    <para>Every workspace contains the same desktop, the same panels, and the
same menus. However, you can run different applications, and open different
windows in each workspace. You can display only one workspace at a time in
your desktop environment but you can have windows open in other workspaces.
 </para>
    <para>Workspaces enable you to organize the desktop environment when you run
many applications at the same time. When your current workspace becomes crowded
with windows, you can move your work to another workspace. You can also switch
to another workspace then start more applications.</para>
    <para>Workspaces are displayed in the <application>Workspace Switcher</application>
applet. In <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-42"/>, <application>Workspace Switcher</application> contains four workspaces. The first three workspaces contain
open windows. The last workspace does not contain currently active windows.</para>
    <figure id="gosoverview-FIG-42">
      <title>Workspaces Displayed in Workspace Switcher</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/workspace_switcher_applet.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Workspace Switcher. The context describes the graphic.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-41">
      <title>To Switch Between Workspaces</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>workspaces</primary>
        <secondary>switching between</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>You can switch between workspaces in the following ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In <application>Workspace Switcher</application>, click on
the workspace where you want to work.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>right arrow</keycap></keycombo> to switch to the workspace on the right of the current
workspace.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>left arrow</keycap></keycombo> to switch to the workspace on the left of the current
workspace.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-40">
      <title>To Add Workspaces</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>workspaces</primary>
        <secondary>specifying number of</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>To add workspaces to your desktop environment, right-click
on the <application>Workspace Switcher</application> applet, then choose <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>. The <guilabel>Workspace Switcher Preferences</guilabel>
dialog is displayed. Use the <guilabel>Number of workspaces</guilabel> spin
box to specify the number of workspaces that you require.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-56">
    <title>Nautilus File Manager</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Nautilus file manager</primary>
      <see>file manager</see>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The <application>Nautilus</application> file
manager provides an integrated access point to your files, applications, FTP
sites, and URIs. To open a file manager window, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>Home Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
The following figure shows a file manager window that displays the contents
of a folder.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/naut_iconview_window.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>A sample file manager window. The context describes the graphic.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>A file manager window contains the following panes:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Side pane</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enables you to navigate
through your files. This pane also displays information about the current
file or folder. The side pane is on the left side of the window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>View pane</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Displays the contents
of files and folders. The view pane is on the right side of the window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para><application>Nautilus</application> enables you to do
the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>View files and folders</para>
        <para>You can view your files and folders as icons or as a list. You can view
the contents of some types of file within a file manager window. Alternatively,
you can open the files in the appropriate application from the file manager. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Manage your files and folders</para>
        <para>You can use the file manager to create, move, copy, rename, and remove
files and folders.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run scripts</para>
        <para>You can run scripts from the file manager, and you can select files
and folders on which to run your scripts.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Customize your files and folders</para>
        <para>You can add emblems to your files and folders to indicate particular
states. For example, you can add an <guilabel>Important</guilabel> emblem
to a file to indicate that the file is important. You can also customize folders
in the following ways: <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Add a note to a folder.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Specify a custom background pattern for a folder.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Specify a zoom setting for a folder.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open special <firstterm>Uniform Resource Identifiers</firstterm>
(URIs)</para>
        <para>The GNOME Desktop contains special URIs that enable you to access particular
functions from the file manager. For example, to access the preference tools,
you can access the <command>preferences:///</command> URI in the file manager.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Write CDs</para>
        <para>The file manager provides a special location where you can copy files
and folders that you want to write to a CD. You can write the contents of
the location to a CD easily.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The file manager also creates the desktop.</para>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-58">
      <title>To Open Files From the File Manager</title>
      <para>To navigate to the folder where the file that you want to open resides,
double-click on the folder icons in the view pane. When the file that you
want to open is displayed, double-click on the file icon to open the file.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-57">
      <title>To Move Files Between Folders</title>
      <para>You can move files between folders by opening two or more file manager
windows. Open a different folder in each window, then drag the files from
one window to the other. </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosgetstarted-11">
    <title>Desktop and Desktop Objects</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Nautilus desktop</primary>
      <see>desktop</see>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>desktop</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The desktop is an active component of the desktop. You can use the desktop
to perform the following actions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Start your applications, and open your files and folders. </para>
        <para>You can add <firstterm>desktop objects</firstterm> for convenient access
to the files, folders, and applications that you use frequently. For example,
you add a launcher for an application that you use often.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open the <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu> menu.</para>
        <para>Right-click on the desktop to open the <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu> menu.
You can use the <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu> menu to perform actions on the
desktop.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The file manager manages the desktop.</para>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-29">
      <title>To Open Desktop Objects</title>
      <para>To open an object from the desktop, double-click on the object. You
can set your preferences in a <application>Nautilus</application> window so
that you click once on an object to execute the default action.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-19">
      <title>To Add Objects to the Desktop</title>
      <para>You can add desktop objects for convenient access to files, folders,
and applications that you use frequently. You can add objects to your desktop
in the following ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu> menu to add a launcher
to the desktop.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Drag an object from a file manager window to the desktop.
For example, you can create a symbolic link to a file that you use often,
then drag the link to your desktop. The icon for the link is moved to the
desktop. To open the file, double-click on the icon. You can also drag files
and folders to the desktop. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Drag an application launcher from a menu to the desktop. For
example, you can open a menu that contains a launcher for an application that
you use often, then drag the launcher to your desktop. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-509">
    <title>Start Here Location</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/naut_starthere_launcher.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Start Here icon.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Start Here location</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>Start Here
location</secondary>
      <see>Start Here location</see>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location enables you to access the following functions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Applications</guilabel>
        </para>
        <para>Double-click on <guilabel>Applications</guilabel> to access your key
GNOME applications. You can also access the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
menu through the <application>Menu Bar</application> and the <guimenu>Main
Menu</guimenu>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Desktop Preferences</guilabel>
        </para>
        <para>Double-click on <guilabel>Desktop Preferences</guilabel> to customize
your desktop environment. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Programs that enable you to configure your system as a server,
and to choose other system settings.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>You can access the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location in the following
ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From a file manager window</para>
        <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu><guimenuitem>Start Here</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The contents of the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel>
location are displayed in the window.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the desktop</para>
        <para>Double-click on the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> object on the desktop.
The contents of the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location are displayed
in a file manager window.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-55">
    <title>Desktop Environment Preferences</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>preference tools</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>You can use desktop environment preference tools to configure
almost every feature of the desktop environment. Each tool controls a particular
part of the behavior of the desktop environment. For example, you can use
a preference tool to select a theme for your desktop environment. A <firstterm>theme</firstterm> is a group of coordinated settings that specify the visual
appearance of a part of your interface. </para>
    <para>For convenience, the tools are grouped under the following headings:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Basic</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>You can open your desktop environment preference tools in either of
the following ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>Desktop Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Choose the item
that you require from the submenus. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Double-click on the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> object
on the desktop. A <application>Nautilus</application> window opens at the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location. Double-click on the <guilabel>Desktop Preferences</guilabel> object in the <application>Nautilus</application> window to display
the preference tools. Double-click on the item that you require.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-54">
    <title>Applications</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>applications</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The applications that are provided with the GNOME Desktop
share several characteristics. For example, the applications have a consistent
look-and-feel. The applications share characteristics because the applications
use the same programming libraries. An application that uses the standard
GNOME programming libraries is called a <firstterm>GNOME-compliant application</firstterm>. For example, <application>Nautilus</application> and the <application>gedit</application> text editor are GNOME-compliant applications.</para>
    <para>GNOME provides libraries in addition to the libraries provided by your
operating system. The libraries enable GNOME to run your existing applications
as well as GNOME-compliant applications. For example, if your operating system
is UNIX-based, you can run your current X11 applications and Motif applications
from the GNOME Desktop.</para>
    <para>Some of the features of GNOME-compliant applications are as follows:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Consistent look-and-feel</para>
        <para>GNOME-compliant applications have a consistent look-and-feel. GNOME-compliant
applications use the look-and-feel settings that you specify in the preference
tools. You can use the following tools to change the look-and-feel of your
GNOME-compliant applications:<itemizedlist><listitem><para><application>Menus &amp; Toolbars</application> preference
tool</para></listitem><listitem><para><application>Theme</application> preference tool</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Menubars, toolbars, and statusbars</para>
        <para>Most GNOME-compliant applications have a menubar, a toolbar, and a statusbar.
The menubar always contains a <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu and a <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu. The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu always contains an <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> menu item, and the <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu always
contains an <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
        <para>A <firstterm>toolbar</firstterm> is a bar that appears under the menubar.
A toolbar contains buttons for the most commonly-used commands. A <firstterm>statusbar</firstterm> is a bar at the bottom of a window that provides information
about the current state of what you are viewing in the window. GNOME-compliant
applications might also contains other bars. For example, <application>Nautilus</application> contains a location bar.</para>
        <para>Some of the bars in GNOME-compliant applications are detachable. That
is, the bar has a handle that you can grab then drag the bar to another location.
You can drag the bar to snap to another side of the window, or to another
part of the screen. For example, you can detach the menubar, toolbar, and
location bar in the file manager. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Default shortcut keys</para>
        <para>GNOME-compliant applications use the same shortcut keys to perform the
same actions. For example, to quit a GNOME-compliant application, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>. To undo an action in a GNOME-compliant
application, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Drag-and-drop</para>
        <para>GNOME-compliant applications use the same protocol to implement drag-and-drop
operations. Therefore, GNOME-compliant applications provide consistent feedback
when you drag-and-drop items.</para>
        <para>The use of the same protocol also enables GNOME-compliant applications
to interoperate in a sophisticated manner. For example, GNOME-compliant applications
recognize the format of the items that you drag. When you drag a HTML file
from a <application>Nautilus</application> window to a web browser, the file
is displayed in HTML format in the browser. However, when you drag the HTML
file to a text editor, the file is displayed in plain text format in the text
editor. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="gosoverview-12">
    <title>To Find Out More</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>help</primary>
      <secondary>how to find</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The desktop environment provides help if you want to find out more about
the following areas: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Desktop environment topics</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Applets</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Applications</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <sect2 id="gosoverview-31">
      <title>To Find Out More About Desktop Environment Topics</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>help</primary>
        <secondary>starting help system</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>help</primary>
        <secondary>desktop environment
topics</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>You can find out more about particular
desktop environment topics in the integrated <application>Yelp</application>
help system. To start the <application>Yelp</application> help system, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosgetstarted-33">
      <title>To Find Out More About Applets</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>applets</primary>
        <secondary>getting help</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>help</primary>
        <secondary>applets</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>To find out more about a specific applet, right-click on the applet,
then choose <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>. </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gosgetstarted-35">
      <title>To Find Out More About Applications</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>applications</primary>
        <secondary>help</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>help</primary>
        <secondary>applications</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>To find out more about a specific application, start the application,
then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu><guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, start the application then press <keycap>F1</keycap>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
