<part id="part2-1"><title>Customizing Your GNOME Desktop</title><partintro><para>You can customize many of the characteristics of your desktop
environment. The customization of each aspect of the desktop environment is
controlled by a dedicated software tool that is called a desktop environment
preference tool. For convenience, the preference tools are grouped under the
following headings:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Basic</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel></para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Advanced</guilabel></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>You can open your preference tools in either of the following ways:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>Desktop Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Choose the tool
that you require from the submenus. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Double-click on the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> object
on the desktop. A <application>Nautilus</application> window opens at the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location. Double-click on the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> object in the <application>Nautilus</application> window to display
your preference tools. Double-click on the tool that you require.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>This section describes how to configure the desktop environment in the
following chapters. </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Using the Basic Preference Tools</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out how to customize your desktop background,
and how to configure your keyboard settings and your mouse settings. This
chapter also describes how to configure shortcut keys, how to set your sound
preferences, and how to configure your network proxy. This chapter also contains
information on how to customize your screensaver, and how to set your screen
resolution. This chapter also describes how to choose a theme and fonts for
your desktop environment, and how to customize your application menubars and
toolbars. This chapter also contains information on how to customize
window focus behavior.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Using the Advanced Preference Tools</emphasis></para><para>This chapter describes how to configure file types, your preferred applications,
and your panels. This chapter also contains information on how to customize
your sessions and startup programs. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Using the Accessibility Preference Tools</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out how to use the accessibility features
of the desktop environment. This chapter describes how to set assistive technology
preferences and how to use the keyboard accessibility features.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></partintro>&goscustdesk;
&goscustlookandfeel;
&goscustaccess;</part>
