


<part id="part1-1">
<title>A Tour of the GNOME Desktop</title>
<partintro><para>This section introduces the core GNOME components. This section
also provides information that helps you to start working with the desktop.
The desktop is very configurable, therefore this section covers the main functional
possibilities of the desktop features. If you want to find out how to implement
the various configuration possibilities that are mentioned in this section,
see <xref linkend="part2-1"/>. The chapters in this section are as follows: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gosbasic-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out about mouse usage, shortcut keys, basic
window skills, and basic dialog skills. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gosoverview-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter for an introduction to the major components and functions
 of the desktop. If you do not read anything else in this manual, read this
chapter.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gosgetstarted-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter for information about how to start, manage, and end
desktop sessions. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gospanel-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out more about using panels in the desktop.
Panels are a key component of the desktop. This chapter tells you how to use
the different parts of your panels, and how to invoke the available functions
of the desktop using panels.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="goseditmainmenu-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out more about using menus in the desktop. 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gosmetacity-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out more about using windows in the desktop.
This chapter describes basic windows functions such as moving and resizing.
 This chapter also describes the controls that you use with windows. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gosnautilus-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out more about the <application>Nautilus</application>
file manager. This chapter describes how to use <application>Nautilus</application>
to work with your file system. This chapter also describes how to customize <application>
Nautilus</application>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="gosdeskback-1"/></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out more about using the desktop background.
This chapter describes how to use the desktop background to start applications,
and open your files and folders. The chapter also describes how to use <guilabel>
Trash</guilabel> from the desktop, how to use the <guimenu>Desktop
Background</guimenu> menu, and how to customize the desktop background.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</partintro>&gosbasic;
&gosoverview;
&gosstartsession;
&gospanel;
&goseditmainmenu;
&gosmetacity;
&gosnautilus;
&gosdeskback;
</part>

