<part id="part1-1"><title>A Tour of the GNOME Desktop</title><partintro><para>A <firstterm>desktop environment</firstterm> desktop environment
is a windows-based environment for users. The desktop environment is the sum
of all the parts of your working environment. This section introduces the
core components in the GNOME Desktop environment. </para><para>The GNOME Desktop is very configurable, therefore this section covers
the main functional possibilities of the GNOME Desktop features.
If you want to find out how to implement the various configuration possibilities
that are mentioned in this section, see <emphasis>Customizing Your GNOME Desktop</emphasis>. </para><para>The chapters in this section are as follows: </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Basic Skills</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out about mouse usage, shortcut keys, basic
window skills, and basic dialog skills. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Overview of the GNOME Desktop</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter for an introduction to the major components and functions
 of the desktop environment. If you do not read anything else in this manual,
read this chapter.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>GNOME Desktop Sessions</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter for information about how to start, manage, and end
GNOME Desktop sessions. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Working With Panels</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out more about using panels. Panels are a
key component of the GNOME Desktop. This chapter tells you how to use the
different parts of your panels, and how to invoke the available functions
of the desktop environment using panels.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Working With Menus</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out more about using menus. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Working With Windows</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out more about using windows. This chapter
describes basic windows functions such as moving and resizing.  This chapter
also describes the controls that you use with windows. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Nautilus File Manager</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out more about the <application>Nautilus</application>
file manager. This chapter describes how to use the file manager to work with
your file system. This chapter also describes how to customize the file manager.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Using Your Desktop</emphasis></para><para>Read this chapter to find out more about using the <firstterm>desktop</firstterm>. The desktop is the part of the desktop environment where there
are no interface graphical items, such as panels and windows. This chapter
describes how to use the desktop to start applications, and open your files
and folders. The chapter also describes how to use <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>
from the desktop, how to use the <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu> menu, and how
to customize the desktop.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></partintro>&gosbasic;
&gosoverview;
&gosstartsession;
&gospanel;
&goseditmainmenu;
&gosmetacity;
&gosnautilus;
&gosdeskback;</part>
