<!-- converted from Solbook 2.2 SGML to Docbook 4.2 XML
# Generator: s2d v1.4 2002-09-19
#   Jay Han (jhan@acm.org)/Lightsaber Computing (http://www.lightsaber.com)
-->
<part id="part2-1"><title>Customizing Your GNOME Desktop</title><partintro><para>You can customize many of the characteristics of your desktop.
The customization of each aspect of the desktop is controlled by a dedicated
software tool that is called a desktop preference tool. For convenience, the
preference tools are grouped under the following headings:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Basic</para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel></para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Advanced</guilabel></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>You can open your preference tools in either of the following ways:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>Desktop Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Choose the tool
that you require from the submenus. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Double-click on the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> object
on the desktop background. A <application>Nautilus</application> window opens
at the <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location. Double-click on the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> object in the <application>Nautilus</application> window
to display your preference tools. Double-click on the tool that you require.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>This section describes how to configure the desktop in the following
chapters. </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Using the Basic Preference Tools</emphasis></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out how to customize your desktop background.
This chapter also contains information on how to configure your keyboard settings
and your mouse settings. This chapter also describes how to configure shortcut
keys, how to set your sound preferences, and how to configure your network
proxy. This chapter also contains information on how to choose a theme and
fonts for your desktop, and how to customize your application menubars and
toolbars. This chapter also describes how to customize window focus behavior.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Using the Advanced Preference Tools</emphasis></para>
<para>This chapter describes how to configure file types, your preferred applications,
and your panels. This chapter also contains information on how to customize
your sessions and startup programs. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Using the Accessibility Preference Tools</emphasis></para>
<para>Read this chapter to find out how to use the accessibility features
of the desktop. This chapter describes how to use the keyboard accessibility
features.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></partintro>&goscustdesk;
&goscustlookandfeel;
&goscustaccess;</part>


