<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="themes-0">
  <title>Installing Themes</title>
  <highlights>
    <para>This chapter describes the types of theme that are available
in the GNOME desktop, how to install themes, and how to create a custom theme.</para>
  </highlights>
  <sect1 id="themes-1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>themes</primary>
      <secondary>introduction</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>A theme is a group of coordinated settings that specifies the visual
appearance of a part of the GNOME desktop. Users can choose themes to change
the appearance of the desktop. </para>
    <para>The following types of theme affect different parts of the GNOME desktop:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Desktop themes</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>desktop
themes</primary>
            <see>themes</see>
          </indexterm>
          <para>Desktop themes determine
the visual appearance of windows, panels, and applets. Desktop themes also
determine the visual appearance of the GNOME-compliant interface items that
appear on windows, panels, and applets, such as menus, icons, and buttons.
Some of the desktop themes that are available in GNOME are designed for special
accessibility needs. Users can choose a desktop theme from the <guilabel>Widget Theme</guilabel> tabbed section in the <application>Theme</application>
preference tool.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Window frame themes</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>window frame themes</primary>
            <see>themes</see>
          </indexterm>
          <para>Window frame
themes determine the appearance of the frames around windows only. Users can
choose a window frame theme from the <guilabel>Window Frames</guilabel> tabbed
section in the <application>Theme</application> preference tool.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="themes-3">
    <title>To Install a Desktop Theme</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>themes</primary>
      <secondary>desktop theme, installing</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Desktop themes reside in the <filename>/usr/share/themes</filename> directory. The typical structure of a desktop theme in the file
system is as follows:</para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="19.19*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="80.81*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Theme file</para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <filename>/usr/share/themes/<replaceable>theme_name</replaceable>/gtk-2.0/gtkrc</filename>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Image files</para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <filename>/usr/share/themes/<replaceable>theme_name</replaceable>/pixmaps/*.*</filename>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>Typically, a new desktop theme is supplied as a <filename>.tar.gz</filename>
file. To install the new desktop theme, unzip the <filename>.tar.gz</filename>
file, then untar the <filename>.tar</filename> file into the <filename>/usr/share/themes</filename> directory.</para>
    <para>If a user adds a desktop theme, the theme is stored in the <filename>$HOME/.themes</filename> directory.</para>
    <para>Users can install their own desktop themes. If a user installs a desktop
theme, the theme is stored in the <filename>$HOME/.themes</filename> directory.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="themes-5">
    <title>To Install a Window Frame Theme</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>themes</primary>
      <secondary>window frame theme, installing</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Window frame themes reside in the <filename>/usr/share/themes/<replaceable>theme_name</replaceable>/metacity-1</filename>
directory. The typical structure of a window frame theme in the file system
is as follows:</para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="19.19*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="80.81*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Theme file</para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <filename>/usr/share/themes/<replaceable>theme_name</replaceable>/metacity-1/metacity-theme-1.xml</filename>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>Image files</para>
            </entry>
            <entry valign="top">
              <para>
                <filename>/usr/share/themes/<replaceable>theme_name</replaceable>/metacity-1/*.*</filename>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>Typically, a new window frame theme is supplied as a <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file. To install the new window frame theme, unzip the <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file, then untar the <filename>.tar</filename> file into
the <filename>/usr/share/themes</filename> directory.</para>
    <para>Users can install their own window frame themes. If a user installs
a window frame theme, the theme is stored in the <filename>$HOME/.themes</filename>
directory.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="themes-11">
    <title>Installing Icons for Themes</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>themes</primary>
      <secondary>installing icons</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The GNOME desktop provides several themes that are designed
for users with special visual needs. For example, some of the themes are designed
for users with low vision. The themes contain several versions of each icon
so that the icon can be displayed in each theme.</para>
    <para>You might need to install a new icon for an application. When you install
a new icon, you must create several versions of the icon, so that the icon
displays correctly in the themes. You can create the icons in several formats,
for example Portable Network Graphic (PNG) format. The suggested size of icons
for the GNOME desktop is 48 pixels by 48 pixels. At this size, most themes
can rescale the icons.</para>
    <para>When you install a new icon, create the following 48 &times; 48 pixel
versions of the icon:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Regular icon</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Low contrast icon</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>High contrast icon</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Inverse high contrast icon</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>If possible, create 16 &times; 16 pixel versions of the each of the
icons above also, for themes that do not require large print.</para>
    <para>Install the icons to the image files location that is specified for
the theme in <xref linkend="themes-3"/> or <xref linkend="themes-5"/>. For example,
to add icons to the HighContrast theme, add the icons to the <filename>/usr/share/themes/HighContrast/pixmaps</filename> directory. Add references to the icons to the relevant theme files.
For example, to add icons to the HighContrast theme, add references to the
icons to the <filename>/usr/share/themes/HighContrast/gtk-2.0/gtkrc</filename>
file. </para>
    <para>The instructions above apply only to the following types of icon:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Icons that are used within applications in the GNOME desktop.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Icons that are used internally by GTK+ applications, or GTK+
stock icons.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For more information on how to create icons for application launchers
and for panels, see <ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/standards/icon-theme-spec.html">http://www.freedesktop.org/standards/icon-theme-spec.html</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="themes-15">
    <title>To Create a Custom Desktop Theme</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>themes</primary>
      <secondary>creating custom desktop</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>If the desktop themes that the GNOME desktop provides are
not suitable for the needs of your users, you can create a custom desktop
theme. To create a custom desktop theme, perform the following steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a directory structure for the theme in the <filename>/usr/share/themes</filename> directory. Use the same directory structure that
other themes use. For example, to create a theme that is called SmallPrint,
create the following directories:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <filename>/usr/share/themes/SmallPrint/gtk-2.0</filename>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <filename>/usr/share/themes/SmallPrint/pixmaps</filename>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Locate the <filename>gtkrc</filename> theme file that is closest
to meeting the needs of your users. Copy the file to the <filename>gtk-2.0</filename> directory of your new theme.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open the <filename>gtkrc</filename> file in a text editor,
 and modify the attributes of the interface elements as required. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the new theme includes images, install the images for the
new theme in the <filename>pixmaps</filename> directory of your new theme.
If the new theme uses images from another theme, you do not need to create
copies of the images for the new theme. Instead, ensure that the reference
to the images in the <literal>pixmap_path</literal> entry in the <filename>gtkrc</filename> file is correct.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Users can now choose the new theme.</para>
    <para>For more information on <filename>gtkrc</filename> files, see <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/index.html">http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/index.html</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
