<chapter id="enabling-accessibility" status="writing">
<title>Enabling Accessibility Tools</title>

<para>
Before moving forward, be sure you are familiar with these essential GNOME commands:
</para>
<para>
<keycap>Alt-F1</keycap> - display and activate the GNOME Desktop menu bar. This grants access to the <guilabel>Applications</guilabel>, <guilabel>Places</guilabel> and <guilabel>System</guilabel> menu bar items.
</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris systems, this key is <keycap>Ctrl-Esc</keycap> (as with Microsoft Windows).
</para>
</note>
<para>
<keycap>Alt-F2</keycap> - summons the <emphasis>Run</emphasis> dialog, where you can issue terminal commands with or without parameters. If a file needs to be passed as one of these parameters, use the <guilabel>Run With File</guilabel> button to easily locate the file needed. This dialog also presents an alternate list of known applications which may be easier to navigate for some than the typical <keycap>Alt-F1</keycap> approach.
</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris systems, this key is <keycap>Meta-R</keycap> (as with Microsoft Windows). A meta- or super-key is an OS-logo shift key.
</para>
</note>
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap> and <keycap>Shift-Tab</keycap> - move focus within an application between controls; use <keycap>Tab</keycap> to cycle forward through controls and <keycap>Shift-Tab</keycap> to cycle backwards. Controls are any user-interactive element that you can manipulate, such as buttons, drop-down lists, text fields, etc. <keycap>Ctrl-Tab</keycap> and <keycap>Shift-Ctrl-Tab</keycap> are used instead where <keycap>Tab</keycap> and <keycap>Shift-Tab</keycap> are reserved for use by the focused control.
</para>
<para>
<keycap>Alt-Tab</keycap> and <keycap>Shift-Alt-Tab</keycap> - switches between currently running applications. If you have multiple programs running, use <keycap>Alt-Tab</keycap> to cycle forward through the applications and <keycap>Alt-Shift-Tab</keycap> to cycle backwards. <keycap>Alt-Esc</keycap> and <keycap>Shift-Alt-Esc</keycap> also cycle between applications, but without an application preview window.
</para>
<!--
<para>
Knowing how to interact with common GNOME-standard user controls (such as text boxes, drop-down lists and radio groups) is also essential - review the

ulink url="ghelp:general#kevnav-0">User Controls section</ulink>
  
o to become familiar with these elements and how to quickly and efficiently navigate them.
</para>
-->
<section id="enable-gok">
<title>GOK (GNOME Onscreen Keyboard)</title>
<para>
You must enable the assistive technology services before you are able to use many of the accessibility tools available.
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>System</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Assistive Technologies</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Select <guilabel>Enable assistive technologies
</guilabel> and then press <guibutton>Close and Log Out</guibutton>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Log back in. The assistive technology services will be started automatically.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>

<para>
The next steps enable <application>gok</application> (GNOME Onscreen Keyboard). These steps are not necessary for Solaris and target Debian platforms (Ubuntu, etc.). See further down for rpm-based distributions (RedHat, Fedora, etc.).
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Accessories</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>sudo apt-get install gok</userinput>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>gok</userinput>
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<para>
If the Sticky Keys feature is not yet enabled, <application>gok</application> will do so the first time it runs.
</para>
<para>
TESTING -- Installing gok for rpm-based systems (specifically, Fedora RedHat):
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Download <ulink 
url="http://rpmfind.net/linux/rpm2html/search.php?query=gnome-common">the gok RPM package</ulink>.
</para>
<figure id="enable-gok-fig1">
<title>RPM Search Results</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/RPM_search_gnome_common.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Package listing</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Accessories</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</step>

<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>rpm -Uvh your_downloaded_file.rpm</userinput>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
You will need to install several additional files from the RedHat distribution:
</para>
<para>
<userinput>cd /distro_path/redhat-8.0/RedHat/RPMS</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh perl-SGMLSpm-1.03ii-6.noarch.rpm</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh docbook-style-dsssl-1.76-6.noarch.rpm</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh docbook-utils-0.6.11-2.noarch.rpm</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh gtk-doc-0.9-5.noarch.rpm</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh at-spi-1.0.1-4.i386.rpm</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh at-spi-devel-1.0.1-4.i386.rpm</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>rpm -Uvh libwnck-devel-0.17-1.i386.rpm</userinput>
</para>
</step>

<step>
<para>
Install the latest version of <application>gok</application> from GNOME CVS:
</para>
<note>
<para>
When prompted for a password, press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
</note>
<para>
<userinput>
cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@anoncvs.gnome.org:
/cvs/gnome login
</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>
cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@anoncvs.gnome.org:/cvs/gnome -z3 checkout gok
</userinput>
</para>
<note>
<para>
To update this release, use the terminal command <userinput>cvs -q up -P -d</userinput>
</para>
</note>
</step>

<step>
<para>
Run the autogen script:
</para>
<para>
<userinput>cd gok/</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>./autogen.sh</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>make</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>su -</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>make install</userinput>
</para>
<para>
<userinput>gok</userinput>
</para>
<note>
<para>
Because <application>gok</application> does not install <application>gconf</application> settings for individual users, run as root instead of an unpriviledged user.
</para>
</note>
</step>
</procedure>
</section>

<section id="enable-orca">
<title>Orca</title>
<para>
For a text-only guided setup, open a terminal session (<keycap>Alt-F1 : Applications - Accessories - Terminal</keycap>) and use the command <userinput>orca --text-setup</userinput> <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
Alternatively, use <keycap>Alt-F2</keycap> to bring up the <emphasis>Run</emphasis> dialog, type in <literal>orca</literal> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
The first time <application>Orca</application> is launched you will be asked a few questions:
</para>
<para>
First you will be presented with a list of languages to choose from; there are currently about 45 languages supported. Most of this list will scroll off the screen, so you may have to use the terminal's scrollbar to view earlier parts of the list. Type in the number of your language choice (e.g., 7 for American English) and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
You are next asked to set <guilabel>Echo By Word</guilabel>. This option instructs <application>Orca</application> to speak words as you finish typing them. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
The next item is <guilabel>Key Echo</guilabel>. This option will speak all keys as they are pressed. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
Now select your desired keyboard layout; generally, you will want to choose the layout that matches your keyboard type - 1 for Desktop or 2 for Laptop. This choice will determine what key will act as the <application>Orca</application> modifier key. The Desktop layout uses <keycap>Insert</keycap> while the Laptop layout uses <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>. A system, host, shift or modifier key is one which is used in conjunction with other keys, enabling keyboard access to most program functions.
</para>
<para>
Next, specify if you require Braille output. This functionality assumes a brlTTY-compatible device is available. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
Lastly, indicate whether you want an on-screen Braille output monitor. This is mostly for developers who need to verify brlTTY output, but may also be useful in other situations, such as visually diagnosing or verifying Braille output. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
That's it! <application>Orca</application> is now ready for use. If accessibility was not yet enabled, <application>Orca</application> does so now and asks you to logout and back in for the services to start. Type <keycap>y</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to restart your login session.
</para>
<para>
After completing the first-time <application>Orca</application> settings, use <keycap>Alt-F2</keycap> to bring up the <emphasis>Run</emphasis> dialog, type in <literal>orca</literal> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>. Accessibility functions should now be active.
</para>
</section>

<section id="enable-dasher">
<title>Dasher</title>
<para>
Dasher is an information-efficient text-entry interface, driven by natural continuous pointing gestures. Dasher is a competitive text-entry system wherever a full-size keyboard cannot be used - for example on a palmtop or wearable computer, or when operating any computer one-handed (by joystick, touchscreen or mouse) or zero-handed (eg, by head-mouse or eye-tracker).
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Accessories</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>sudo apt-get install dasher
</userinput>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>dasher</userinput>
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<para>
Dasher may also be installed from the <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add/Remove</guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog. In either case, it may later be launched in these ways:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Alt-F2</keycap> for the <emphasis>Run</emphasis> dialog, type <userinput>dasher</userinput> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Accessories</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and execute <userinput>dasher</userinput>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Alt-F1</keycap> and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Universal Access</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Dasher</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</chapter>
