<chapter id="enabling-accessibility" status="writing">
<title>Enabling Accessibility Tools</title>
<para>
You must enable the assistive technology services before you are able to use many of the accessibility tools available.
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>System</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Assistive Technologies</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Select <guilabel>Enable assistive technologies
</guilabel> and then press <guibutton>Close and Log Out</guibutton>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Log back in. The assistive technology services will be started automatically.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<para>
Once basic assistive technology support is
enabled, it is possible to start accessibility
services such as <application>Orca</application>, a fully GNOME-compliant application for speech, magnification, Braille output and other accessibility tools.
</para>
<para>
Getting started with <application>Orca</application> is quite painless. Use <keycap>Alt-F2</keycap> to bring up a Run dialog and type in <userinput>orca</userinut>. You can also press the up arrow to cycle through previous Run dialog entries. When the text box contains the word <userinput>orca</userinut>, press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
To adjust <application>Orca</application> for your requirements, <keycap>Alt-Tab</keycap> to the Orca main window and then press <keycap>Tab</keycap> by itself until <application>Orca</application> announces the Preferences button. Press Enter and you are presented with the GUI configuration dialog.
<note>
If you are using large print fonts, the entire Preferences configuration dialog may not fit on your screen. You may have to temporarily downsize to another theme or adjust your monitor resolution before effectively using the Preferences dialog. [Orca may later employ a fully scrollable window (with both vertical and horizontal scroll bars) or the GNOME Desktop itself may add this windowing feature (perhaps by panelizing all child controls). This particular window behavior is currently developer-dependent.]
</note>
</para>
<para>
The GUI configuration dialog is made up of several sections, each denoted by a notebook tab at the top of the dialog. These tabs can be navigated with the left/right arrow keys when the tabstrip has focus. Press the down arrow or <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move from the tabstrip into the options area for the currently highlighted tab/section. To return to the tabstrip, use <keycap>Shift-Tab</keycap> until the tabstrip is selected again.
<note>
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Orca Preferences - General Section</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
Keyboard Layout - this radio group offers two mutually-exclusive options for indicating which keyboard layout applies to you.
</para>

</chapter>
