<chapter id="low-vision">
<title>Low Vision or Blindness</title>
<para>
From low vision to blindness, the range of visual limitations is broad. Symptoms of low vision include dimness, haziness, extreme far-/near-sightedness, color blindness, and tunnel vision, among others. People with these disabilities are concerned with being able to see text or images on a computer screen and being able to perform tasks that 
require eye-hand coordination, such as moving a computer mouse. Text size and color can make a big difference in legibility for people with low vision.
</para>
<para>
The technologies that can assist those with low vision or blindness are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Screen Magnifier</emphasis> - this is like a magnifying glass. People using them 
are able to control what area of the computer screen they want enlarged, and can move the magnifier to view different areas of the screen. They are also known as screen enlargers or large print programs.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Screen Reader</emphasis> - this makes on-screen information available as 
synthesized speech and/or a refreshable Braille display. They generally only translate text-based information. Graphics and other non-textual objects can be 
translated if there is alternative text 
describing the item. They are also known as 
blind access utilities or screen reviewers.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Desktop Appearance Enhancement</emphasis> - users can configure the desktop to be easy to read; for example, by increasing text size and using high-contrast themes.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section id="ats-2">
<title>Screen Reader and Magnifier</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>Screen Reader and Magnifier</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>Orca</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The <application>Orca Screen Reader and Magnifier</application> application enables users with limited or no vision to use the GNOME Desktop and associated applications. <application>Orca</application> provides the following functionality: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Screen Reader
</para>
<para>
The screen reader enables non-visual access to standard applications in the GNOME Desktop by using speech and Braille output.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Magnifier
</para>
<para>
The magnifier provides automated focus tracking and full-screen magnification to aid low-vision users.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
The following sections provide information about <application>Orca</application> and how to use it.
</para>

<section>
<title>Introduction to Orca</title>
<section>
<title>What is Orca?</title>
<para>
Orca is a flexible, extensible, and powerful assistive technology for people with visual impairments. Using various combinations of speech synthesis, Braille and magnification, Orca helps provide access to applications
and toolkits that support the AT-SPI (e.g., the GNOME Desktop). <application>Orca</application> is also free open source software.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Why the name Orca?</title>
<para>
One of the first DOS screen readers was Flipper, made by Omnichron Corporation in Berkeley, CA. It was named Flipper in part because the blind wife of the programmer 
envisioned computers as being programmed by flipping switches (an accurate image of a bygone era). Then came another DOS screen reader, this one from Henter-Joyce in 
Florida - "Jobs Access With Speech" (or JAWS). And so on....
</para>
<para>
Although no obvious connection exists between blindness and creatures from the sea, there is certainly a naming tradition for screen-reader software. Hence <application>Orca</application>, which is a lot tougher-sounding than Nemo, Ariel, Willy, or Mr. Limpet.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>What's the schedule?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> is part of the GNOME platform and <application>Orca</application>'s releases are coupled with the releases of the GNOME platform.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How do I request a new feature?</title>
<para>
<ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/buglist.cgi?query=product:orca+">Bugs</ulink> and feature/enhancement requests (RFEs) 
should be reported to the <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org">GNOME Bug Tracking System
</ulink>. Patches are always welcome, and instructions for creating patches can be found in the <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/tools/svn.html">
GNOME Introduction to Subversion (SVN)
</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Where is the discussion list?</title>
<para>
You can get in touch with developers and other users by <ulink url="mailto:orca-list@gnome.org">sending an e-mail</ulink> to the <ulink url="http://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/orca-list">Orca mailing list</ulink> 
(
<ulink url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/orca-list">Archives</ulink>).
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Is Braille supported?</title>
<para>
Yes! Braille is supported via BrlTTY and it is tightly integrated with Orca. BrlTTY offers support for nearly every refreshable Braille display known to man. Refer to the 
<ulink url="ghelp:orca#braille">Braille page
</ulink> for more information.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Are Grade 2 Braille contractions supported?</title>
<para>
Yes, <application>Orca</application> fully supports contracted Braille output.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>What voices are available?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> provides interfaces to both <userinput>gnome-speech</userinput> and <userinput>emacspeak</userinput> speech services. As such, the available voices for <application>Orca</application> are only restricted by the speech engines supported by the available speech services. For free speech engines, you typically have a choice of the eSpeak, Festival, and FreeTTS speech engines. For commercial engines, you have a choice of 
additional engines such as Fonix DECtalk, Loquendo, Eloquence, Cepstral and IBMTTS, with others on the way. Periodically check the <userinput>gnome-speech</userinput> package for more progress in this area.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>What languages are supported?</title>
<para>
The <ulink url="http://l10n.gnome.org/teams">
GNOME translation teams</ulink> are composed of many passionate volunteers from around the world. These teams do a great job and keep an up-to-date status report. See the <ulink url="http://l10n.gnome.org/module/orca">
Orca translation status page</ulink> for the large number of languages into which <application>Orca</application> has been translated.
</para>
<para> 
Note: support for a language also depends on 
the speech synthesis engine also supporting the same language.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How well does magnification work?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> currently uses the <userinput>gnome-mag</userinput> 
magnification service. <userinput>gnome-mag</userinput> has incorporated support for smoother full-screen magnification, which 
relies upon newer extensions in the X Window System server. These extensions do not always function well on all platforms, so smooth full-screen magnification may not always work.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How is web access coming along?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> targets the <application>Firefox</application> web browser (version 3) for providing accessible web browsing. Both the <application>Orca</application> and <application>Firefox</application> teams are fully dedicated in this cooperative effort.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Using Orca</title>
<section>
<title>Initial Setup</title>
<para>
When you run <application>Orca</application> for the first time, it will automatically enter setup mode. If you want to run setup 
at some later point, you can pass the
<userinput>--setup</userinput> option to <application>Orca</application> the next 
time you run it. Furthermore, while <application>Orca</application> is running, 
you can press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> to bring up the <application>Orca</application> setup window. Finally, <application>Orca</application> provides a text setup utility that you can start by passing the 
<userinput>--text-setup</userinput> option to <application>Orca</application>. All of these options will create a <userinput>~/.orca/user-settings.py</userinput> file that holds your preferences and will also enable the accessibility infrastructure. You need to log out and log back in for the new settings to take effect.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How do I run Orca?</title>
<para>
Run <application>Orca</application> by typing <userinput>orca</userinput> in a terminal session window. You can do so from a virtual 
console window if you do not yet have access to the GUI. With the GUI installed you can also press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> to bring up the Run dialog and then enter <userinput>orca</userinput> as the command (followed by any optional parameters). <application>Orca</application> will automatically enter text setup mode if you run it from a virtual console window or your GUI environment is not yet set up for accessibility.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Quitting Orca</title>
<para>
To quit <application>Orca</application>, press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>. A confirmation dialog will appear. Select <guilabel>Yes</guilabel> to quit. If the system seems unresponsive, you can try a few things:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Run <userinput>orca --quit</userinput> from a terminal window, such as a virtual console; press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap>
</keycombo> (on most Linux platforms) to get to a virtual console, enter your commands, and then use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo> to get back to the desktop. This will kill the <application>Orca</application> process and reclaim system resources. You can then 
rerun <application>Orca</application> using the previously outlined methods.
</para>
<para>
Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Backspace</keycap>
</keycombo> to end your login session and get back to the graphical login prompt (not implemented in all Linux distributions).
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Customizing Orca</title>

<section>
<title>How do I define my own keybindings?</title>
<para>
You can redefine your key bindings for <application>Orca</application> in two main ways. The first way is to choose between the 
Desktop and Laptop layouts, which can be selected on the General page of the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog (press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> to bring up Orca Preferences). For more refined 
control, you can set individual key bindings 
on the Key Bindings page of the <application>Orca</application> configuration 
dialog.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Use a keyboard command to make Orca speak or Braille-output the current date and time</title>
<para>
Place the following lines in <userinput>~/.orca/orca-customizations.py</userinput>. If this file doesn't exist yet, go ahead and create it.
</para>
<screen>
<![CDATA[
import orca.input_event
import orca.keybindings
import orca.orca
import orca.speech
import orca.braille
import re
]]>
<![CDATA[
myKeyBindings = orca.keybindings.KeyBindings()
]]>
<![CDATA[
def sayTime(script, inputEvent=None):
  import time
  message = time.strftime("%a, %d %b %Y %H:%M:%S", time.localtime())
  orca.speech.speak(message)
  orca.braille.displayMessage(message)
  return True
]]>
<![CDATA[
sayTimeHandler = orca.input_event.InputEventHandler(
  sayTime,
  "Presents the time.")
]]>
<![CDATA[
myKeyBindings.add(orca.keybindings.KeyBinding(
  "d",
  1 << orca.settings.MODIFIER_ORCA,
  1 << orca.settings.MODIFIER_ORCA,
  sayTimeHandler))
]]>
<![CDATA[
orca.settings.keyBindingsMap["default"] = myKeyBindings
]]>
</screen>

<para>
Note that in this case <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo> will be used to report current information about the time and date.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How do I set up my own custom scripts?</title>
<para>
Create an empty file named 
<userinput>~/.orca/orca-scripts/__init__.py</userinput> and place your custom scripts in 
<userinput>~/.orca/orca-scripts</userinput>
, <application>Orca</application> will pick up any scripts from there before looking in the installed area.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Orca Configuration</title>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog allows you to customize 
the behavior and features of <application>Orca</application>, such as speech, Braille, and magnification. For example, you can select which speech synthesis engine you want to use, whether 
Braille is enabled or not, and which magnification preferences you want. You can select between Laptop/Desktop keyboard 
layouts and you can also examine and modify the existing keyboard layout with granular 
control. To bring up the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog, press 
<keycombo><keycap>&lt;ORCA MODIFIER&gt;</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, where <userinput>&lt;ORCA MODIFIER&gt;</userinput> is <keycap>Insert</keycap> 
when you use the Desktop key bindings, and 
<keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> when you use the Laptop key bindings.
</para>

<para>
The <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog is a multi-tab 
container for several pages, each of which is 
described in the following sections.
</para>

<section>
<title>General Page</title>
<para>The General page allows you to customize general aspects of <application>Orca</application>. These include the following:
</para>

<section>
<title>Keyboard Layout</title>
<para>
The keyboard layout section lets you choose between a small keyboard layout (Laptop) or large keyboard layout with a numeric keypad (Desktop). If you choose Laptop the <application>Orca</application> system key is CapsLock; for the Desktop layout the system key is Insert.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Show Orca Main Window</title>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> main window provides you with a graphical way 
to display the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog (also obtained by <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>). Many users do not like the <application>Orca</application> main window because it shows up in the window manager's tab order when you press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> to switch windows. By deselecting the <guilabel>Show Orca Main Window</guilabel> option, you can tell <application>Orca</application> to not show its main window.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Quit Orca without Confirmation</title>
<para>
Normally when you press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> or press the <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> button in the <application>Orca</application> main window,  a confirmation dialog will prompt if you really want to quit. Unchecking this option prevents the confirmation window from appearing.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Disable gksu keyboard grab</title>
<para>
When running system administration commands from the launch menu, many distributions use an application known as <application>gksu</application> to authorize the user to run these commands (<application>gksu</application> is the dialog that asks you for your password). When it runs, <application>gksu</application> enables what is known as a "keyboard grab," which is a 
feature to prevent keyboard actions from going to any other application on the desktop, including <application>Orca</application>. The result of a keyboard grab is that <application>Orca</application> will not receive any keyboard events, preventing <application>Orca</application> from functioning normally.
</para>
<para>
By selecting the <guibutton>Disable gksu Keyboard Grab</guibutton> button, you will turn off the keyboard grab behavior, 
allowing <application>Orca</application> to function normally with system administration applications.
</para>

<note>
<para>
The keyboard grab is a security attempt by
<application>gksu</application> to prevent malicious applications from "sniffing" the keyboard and obtaining your password. Please be advised that disabling <application>gksu</application>'s keyboard grab feature can expose you to such nefarious behavior.
</para>
<para>
If you do not feel comfortable with this, you can always use the root account for system administration purposes. To do so, you need to enable the root account for login, and then log out and back in again as root whenever you want to perform a system administration command.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Present Tooltips</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell <application>Orca</application> to present information about tooltips when they appear as the result of mouse hovering. Specific actions to force tooltips to appear, such as pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> when an object has focus, will always result in tooltips being presented, regardless of this setting.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speech Page</title>
<para>
The speech page allows you to customize how <application>Orca</application> uses speech synthesis.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable Speech</title>
<para>
The first control of note on the speech page is the <guilabel>Enable Speech</guilabel> check box. This check box toggles whether or not <application>Orca</application> will make use of a speech synthesizer. This option, along with the ability to enable Braille and magnifier support, allows <application>Orca</application> to be tailored to meet the specific needs of a wide variety of users.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speech System and Speech Synthesizer</title>
<para>
The next two controls deal with selecting the speech system and synthesizer. <application>Orca</application> provides support for a growing number of speech systems. At the time of this writing these include GNOME-speech, Emacspeak, and an
experimental backend for Speech Dispatcher. Depending on how your machine is configured, you may have all or none of these options. Typically, you will only have GNOME-speech available.
</para>

<para>
First, determine which speech system you would like to use - GNOME-speech works best at this time. After making your selection, tab to the speech synthesizer combo box 
and choose from the list of available synthesizers.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Voice Settings</title>
<para>
If your synthesizer supports it, <application>Orca</application> can utilize multiple voices in order to identify special cases within an application, such as hyperlinks or uppercase text. The voice settings and person combo boxes can be 
adjusted to customize these settings to your liking. For example, assume you were using Fonix DECtalk and wanted the Betty voice to denote uppercase. To accomplish this, you could do the following:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
<listitem>
<para>
Tab to the voice settings combo box, and press the down arrow until the uppercase voice is selected.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Tab to the person combo box, and press the down arrow to choose the Betty voice.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
The next three sliders in the tab order allow adjustment of the synthesizer's rate, pitch and volume, respectively.
</para>
<para>
Note that you can quickly raise/lower the pitch by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Up Arrow</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Down Arrow</keycap></keycombo>. You can also modify the speaking rate by pressing 
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Left Arrow</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Right Arrow</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Punctuation Level</title>
<para>
The <guilabel>Punctuation Level</guilabel> radio button group is used to adjust the amount of punctuation spoken by the synthesizer. The available levels are 
None, Some, Most and All.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Verbosity</title>
<para>
The Verbosity setting determines the amount of information that will be spoken in certain situations. For example, if it is set to <guilabel>Verbose</guilabel>, the synthesizer
will speak shortcut keys for items in pull-down menus. When it is set to <guilabel>Brief</guilabel>, these shortcut keys are not announced.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Table Row Speech</title>
<para>
The table row speech option determines the way in which <application>Orca</application> will read items within tables. The available 
settings are <guilabel>Speak Current Row
</guilabel> or <guilabel>Speak Current Cell</guilabel>. The ability to adjust this behavior can be useful in many situations. For example, consider the process of 
browsing email messages in Evolution. In this instance it may be preferable to set table speech to <guilabel>Speak Current Row</guilabel>, so arrowing through the list of messages causes all relevant info, such as the sender, subject, and whether the message has attachments, is read automatically. 
While the current row setting is active, it is still possible to read individual cells by using the left and right arrows.
</para>
<para>
Note that you can quickly toggle this behavior by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>F11</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak Indentation</title>
<para>
When working with code or editing documents, it is often desirable to be aware of justification as well as indentation. Selecting the <guilabel>Speak Indentation and Justification</guilabel> check box will cause <application>Orca</application> to provide this information.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak Blank Lines</title>
<para>
Some users desire to hear the word "blank" when navigating through empty lines in a document. Other users do not. If the    
<guilabel>Speak Blank Lines</guilabel> 
check box is selected, <application>Orca</application> will announce any blank lines.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Braille Page</title>
<para> 
The Braille page allows you to customize various aspects of Braille output. 
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable Braille Support</title>
<para>
The first control on the Braille page is the 
<guilabel>Enable Braille Support</guilabel> check box. This toggles whether or not <application>Orca</application> will make use of a Braille display. This option, along with the ability to enable Braille and magnifier support, allows <application>Orca</application> to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of users. By default, this check box is enabled. If BrlTTY is not running, <application>Orca</application> will recover gracefully and will not communicate with the Braille display. If you configure BrlTTY later on, you need to restart <application>Orca</application> in
order for it to use Braille.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enable Braille Monitor</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application>'s Braille monitor provides an on-screen representation of what takes place on the Braille display. This feature is mostly for demonstration
purposes, but is also useful for <application>Orca</application> developers who do not have access to a Braille display.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Abbreviated Role Names</title>
<para>
The <guilabel>Abbreviated Role Names</guilabel> check box determines the manner in which role names are displayed and can be used to help conserve real estate on the Braille display. This option is best explained by example:
</para>
<para>
Let us assume that a slider had focus, and that the abbreviated role names box was not checked. In that case, the word "slider" would be shown on the display, to reflect the fact that the current control was indeed 
a slider. If the abbreviated role names box was checked, the word "slider" would be abbreviated to "sldr".
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Verbosity</title>
<para>
The <guilabel>Verbosity</guilabel> radio button group determines the amount of information that will be output to Braille in certain situations. For example, if it is set to Verbose, keyboard shortcut and role name 
information is displayed. This information is not displayed in Brief mode.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Key Echo Page</title>
<para>
The Key Echo page allows you to specify the behavior of <application>Orca</application> when pressing keys on the page and whether 
words are spoken as you complete them.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable Key Echo</title>
<para>
The first control on the key echo page is the 
<guilabel>Enable Key Echo</guilabel> check box. When this box is checked, five additional check boxes become available. These are <guilabel>Enable Alphanumeric and Punctuation Keys</guilabel>, <guilabel>Enable Modifier Keys</guilabel>, <guilabel>Enable Locking Keys</guilabel>, <guilabel>Enable Function Keys</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Enable Action Keys</guilabel>.
</para>
<para>
The alphanumeric and punctuation option determines if letter, number and punctuation characters are echoed as you type them.
</para>
<para>
Modifier keys are those such as <keycap>Shift</keycap>,
<keycap>Control</keycap>, and 
<keycap>Alt</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
Locking keys include 
<keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>, 
<keycap>Scroll Lock</keycap>, and 
<keycap>Num Lock</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
Enabling function key echo will announce F1 - F12 when they are pressed.
</para>

<para>
The action keys group consists of keys that perform some logical action, as 
<keycap>Backspace</keycap>, 
<keycap>Return</keycap> and 
<keycap>Tab</keycap>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enable Echo by Word</title>
<para>
The last toggle on the Key Echo page is the 
<guilabel>Enable Echo by Word</guilabel> check box. This option is always available, regardless of whether any of the key echo options are checked. When enabled, whole words are spoken as typing progresses.
</para>

<para>
In summary, the Key Echo scheme can offer a great deal of flexibility. For example, one user might choose to enable all Key Echo options, while another might prefer to use word echo, but only have locking keys
announced.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Magnifier Page</title>
<para>
The magnifier page allows you to enable/disable magnification and specify how magnification is performed.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable Magnifier</title>
<para>
The first control on the magnifier page is the <guilabel>Enable Magnifier</guilabel> check box. This toggles whether or not <application>Orca</application> will provide magnification. This option, along with the ability to enable speech and Braille support, allow <application>Orca</application> to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of users.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cursor Settings</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Enable Cursor</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Color</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Custom Size and Width</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cross-Hair Settings</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Enable Cross-Hair and Size</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Enable Cross-Hair Clip</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Zoomer Settings</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Scale factor</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Invert Colors</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Zoomer Position</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Top, Left, Right, Bottom</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Smoothing</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Mouse Tracking Mode</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Source Display - X Window System display of
what should be magnified. Typically 
<userinput>:0</userinput>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Target Display - X Window System display of
where to put the magnified area. Typically 
<userinput>:0</userinput>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Key Bindings Page</title>
<para>
The key bindings page allows you to examine and modify the key bindings for <application>Orca</application>.
</para>

<section>
<title>Orca Modifier Key(s)</title>
<para>
The first control on the Key Bindings page allows you to examine which key (or keys) acts as the "Orca modifier" (<application>Orca</application> system key). The <application>Orca</application> modifier is the key that you press and hold in conjunction with other 
keys to give commands to <application>Orca</application>. For Desktop keyboards, the modifier defaults to <keycap>Insert</keycap>. 
For Laptop keyboards, the modifier defaults to the <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> key.
</para>
<para>
You cannot modify the <application>Orca</application> modifier key(s) using the configuration dialog at this time.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Key Bindings Table</title>
<para>
The key bindings table provides a list of <application>Orca</application>
operations and the keys that are bound to them.
</para>
<para>
The "Function" column header is a description of the operation to be performed.
</para>
<para>
The "Key Binding" header is the primary way to
invoke the function from the keyboard. Note that the function description may include the word <literal>Orca</literal>. This indicates that the <application>Orca</application> modifier key should be held down along with the other key(s).
</para>
<para>
The "Alternate" header provides an alternate
mechanism for invoking the function from the
keyboard.
</para>
<para>
To modify either the "Key Binding" or the
"Alternate" bindings, arrow to the cell and press <keycap>Return</keycap>. Then, press a key combination and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to confirm the new combination. When you do so, the new keystroke will be saved and the check box in the <guilabel>Modified</guilabel> column will indicate that the key binding has been modified.
</para>
<para>
To undo a modified keybinding, arrow to the modified column, uncheck the checkbox, and press the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>).
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Text Attributes Page</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> will speak known text attribute information about an object when you press 
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> (<keycombo>
<keycap>Caps Lock</keycap><keycap>F</keycap>
</keycombo> for Laptop systems).
</para>
<para>
Because the number of text attributes is large, and not everyone cares about every attribute, the "Text Attributes" tab of the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog allows you to customize which text attributes will be presented.
</para>
<para>
On this tab is a text attribute list, where each row consists of three columns:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
<listitem>
<para>
A checkbox which the user can set to indicate
whether this text attribute should be spoken or not.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The name of the text attribute.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
An editable "Spoken unless" string value. By
default, not all text attributes will have this set. If present, what it means (assuming the user wants this text attribute spoken) is that the value of the attribute will only be spoken if it's a different value than this value.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
For example, by default the "underline" text
attribute has a value of "none". If the user has this attribute checked and the user presses <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> and the text in question is not underlined, then this attribute is not spoken. If you always want 
this attribute to be spoken regardless of whether the text is underlined, then the attribute should be checked and the "Spoken unless" value cleared.
</para>
<para>
There is also a <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>R</keycap></keycombo>) that will set the list values back to their initial state when the dialog was first displayed.
</para>
<para>
When you initially display the text attribute pane, all your checked attributes are put at the top of the list. They are given in the order that they will be spoken and output to Braille.
</para>
<para>
If you decide to check others or wish to adjust the order, there are four buttons to help you do this:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><guibutton>Move to Top</guibutton> ( 
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>T</keycap>
</keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute to the top of the list.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guibutton>Move Up One</guibutton> ( 
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>U</keycap>
</keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute up one row.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guibutton>Move Down One</guibutton> ( 
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>D</keycap>
</keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute down one row.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><guibutton>Move to Bottom</guibutton> (  
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>B</keycap>
</keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute to the bottom of the list.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Text attributes can also be set on an individual application basis. The text attribute pane is also part of the application specific settings dialog that is 
started when you give a particular application focus and press <keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Application-Specific Information</title>
<section>
<title>Accessible Applications</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> is designed to work with applications and toolkits
that support the Assistive Technology Service Provider Interface (AT-SPI). This includes the GNOME Desktop and its bundled applications: OpenOffice, Firefox, and the Java platform. Some applications work better than others, however, and the <application>Orca</application> community continually works to provide superior access to more and more applications.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Using Adobe's Acrobat Reader</title>
<para>
We are currently working on a script for Adobe's Acrobat Reader, and the initial version has been contributed to <application>Orca</application> v2.17.5. Note that there is still work to do, and we are very encouraged by Adobe's commitment to accessibility.
</para>

<section>
<title>Installation</title>
<para>
If you get Adobe Acrobat Reader directly from the <ulink url='http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html'>Adobe site</ulink>,
you may find that the software will not
launch. If launched from the Applications
menu, it may appear that nothing has happened, or if launched from a terminal window you may receive a long series of 
syntax error messages. Should this occur, you will need to edit your /usr/bin/acroread file as described in this <ulink url='http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php
?t=233514'>Ubuntu forum thread</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
If you instead choose to install Acrobat Reader from your distribution's packages, be sure to install both <application>acroread</application> and <application>acroread-plugins</application>. Without the plugins 
package, you will not have the access to the "Reading" category in the <menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>Edit-</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> dialog.
</para>
<para>
Note: If you use Ubuntu and cannot locate the
<application>acroread</application> package, you will likely need to edit your
/etc/apt/sources.list to include the 'multiverse' repository. Then run 
<userinput>apt-get update</userinput>. 
Having done so, you should then be able to install both <application>acroread</application> and <application>acroread-plugins</application>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enabling Accessibility and Caret Navigation</title>
<para>
Once you've installed Reader, you need to enable accessibility:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
<listitem>
<para>
In the "Accessibility" category of the 
<menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>Edit-</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> dialog, make sure 
<guilabel>Always display the keyboard selection cursor</guilabel> (<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap>
</keycombo>) is checked.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the "Reading" category of the 
<menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>Edit-</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> dialog, make sure
<guilabel>Enable Document Accessibility
</guilabel> ((<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>) is checked.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Working with Untagged Documents</title>
<para>
When you open an untagged document, you will be presented with a dialog box asking you to specify the reading order and the reading mode options. The default reading order is 
<guilabel>Infer reading order from document
</guilabel>. This setting works well for most documents.
</para>
<para>
The default reading mode will vary depending on the length of the document; for short documents, the default is <guilabel>Read the entire document</guilabel>; for long documents the default is <guilabel>Read currently visible pages only</guilabel>. <application>Orca</application> tends to work better when <guilabel>Read the entire document</guilabel> is selected.
</para>
<para>
If you find that a document seems to be missing parts of the text, try changing the reading options. To do so, get into the Document menu and select <guilabel>Change Accessibility Reading Options...</guilabel> or use the shortcut <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>5</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Page Layout</title>
<para>
The best page layout for reading a document with <application>Orca</application> is <guilabel>Single Page</guilabel>. When <guilabel>Continuous</guilabel> is chosen, moving focus to text as the page is scrolling 
can cause that text not to be read. You can change the page layout to <guilabel>Single Page</guilabel> by getting into the View menu and selecting the Page Layout submenu.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Navigating Tables</title>
<para>
As far as we know there isn't currently a whole lot of keyboard support for tables in
<application>Acrobat Reader</application>. We hope Adobe will remedy this soon.
</para>
<para>
Basically, there are the arrow keys. Their behavior is to move you first within the cell with focus, then to the next cell with data in it. Note that currently, Up and Down Arrow do not seem to move you vertically among cells - at least that has been the experience 
with the tables we have tried. Instead, Up and Down seem to move you horizontally until you run out of cells on the current row.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Making Application-Specific Settings</title>
<para>
To customize the settings for a particular application, you will first need to run that application. Make sure the application has focus, then press <keycombo><keycap>ORCA_MODIFIER</keycap>
<keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap>
</keycombo> (by default, this will be 
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Control</keycap>
<keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> for the Desktop keyboard layout).
</para>
<para>
This brings up a tabbed dialog window very similar to the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog, but with the following differences:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
<listitem>
<para>
There is no initial General pane.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
The Speech System and Speech Synthesizer combo
boxes on the Speech pane will be grayed out (made inactive).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Any existing application-specific key bindings will appear at the top of the list on the Key Bindings pane.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
There may be a new application-specific settings pane at the end of the set of tabbed panes. Note that pressing the End key from the tab list will get you directly to the right-most tab.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
Adjust your application-specific settings in the same way you set your general <application>Orca</application> preferences.
For example, you may have Key Echo disabled generally in <application>Orca</application> but would like to specifically have it enabled for the <application>gcalctool</application> (GNOME Calculator) application. Here's where you could easily set that.
</para>
<para>
When you have your application settings customized the way you want, press the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button. These settings will be written to your 
<userinput>~/.orca/app-settings</userinput> directory in a file called 
<userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;.py</userinput>, where <userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;</userinput> is the name of the application.
</para>
<para>
These files are automatically written by <application>Orca</application>. The contents of the file will be overwritten each time you change your application settings for that
application.
</para>
<para>
If you want to have some extra application-specific settings or code that you don't want to lose, then you should put it in a file called <userinput>~/.orca/app-settings/&lt;APPNAME&gt;-customizations.py</userinput>. This file will be automatically read when the settings for the 
<userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;</userinput> application are loaded.
</para>
<para>
Note that this is an advanced feature that we don't expect many people to use. It's just there if you really want it.
</para>
<para>
There is currently one known bug (some people would call it a feature) that we are trying to track down and fix:
</para>
<note>
<para>
If you adjust one or more application-specific key bindings, the new values will not take effect until you've pressed the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button. The work-around is to either restart <application>Orca</application>, or Alt-Tab 
away to some other application and then Alt-Tab back to the one that you've just changed the key bindings for.
</para>
</note>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Braille</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> uses 
<ulink url='http://mielke.cc/brltty/'>BrlTTY</ulink> for Braille support. On Linux systems, BrlTTY is used to access the text mode console content. On a typical Braille-enabled installation of Linux, BrlTTY is already running and providing access to the text consoles. When Orca starts, it connects to BrlTTY. If you switch from a text console to your X Windows session, your Braille display will automatically follow and display the content that Orca is presenting to you.
</para>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> attempts to work with various releases of BrlTTY. It works well with BrlTTY v3.7.2, and we've also been working with the BrlTTY team to get it going for BrlTTY v3.8. The remainder of this document provides information related to using <application>Orca</application> with <application>BrlTTY</application> 3.8.
</para>

<para>
Below are descriptions of the necessary tasks to install/setup BrlTTY in Ubuntu and Solaris. For both, you need to first obtain 
<ulink url='http://mielke.cc/brltty/releases/
brltty-3.8.tar.gz'>brltty-3.8.tar.gz</ulink> from the BrlTTY site.
</para>

<section>
<title>BrlTTY 3.8 on Ubuntu</title>
<para>
First, configure your build environment to build BrlTTY. Much of this setup is done for you automatically in the Ubuntu distribution with products such as G++ already present. In addition, <emphasis>you must</emphasis> 
also install tcl, Pyrex, and the Python developer environment. To do this, execute the following commands as <userinput>root</userinput>:
</para>
<para></para>
<screen>
<![CDATA[apt-get build-dep brltty
apt-get install tcl8.4 python-pyrex python-dev
]]>
</screen>
<para>
Then, when you build BrlTTY, avoid configuring the package with --prefix=/usr. Use the standard procedure instead, executing the following commands as <userinput>root</userinput>:
</para>
<para></para>
<screen>
<![CDATA[gunzip -c brltty-3.8.tar.gz | tar xvf -
cd brltty-3.8
./autogen
./configure
make
make install
]]>
</screen>
<para>
Run BrlTTY as <userinput>root</userinput>:
</para>
<para></para>
<screen>
<![CDATA[/bin/brltty -bauto -d/dev/ttyUSB0
]]>
</screen>
<para>
If you want, you can remove the existing 
<userinput>/sbin/brltty</userinput> and replace it with the <userinput>/bin/brltty</userinput>, either by copying the <userinput>/bin/brltty</userinput> to <userinput>/sbin/brltty</userinput> or just by making a 
symbolic link. Do so at your own risk.
</para>
<para />
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Keyboard Commands</title>
<para>
This is the list of common <application>Orca</application> keyboard commands. Note that you can always enter <application>Orca</application>'s Learn mode while running <application>Orca</application> by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo>. When in Learn mode, <application>Orca</application> will intercept all keyboard and Braille input events and will tell you what the effect of them would be. To exit Learn mode, press the <keycombo><keycap>Escape</keycap></keycombo> key. If you are using a laptop computer, you will want to see the <ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Orca/LaptopKeyboardCommands">laptop keyboard commands</ulink> page at live.gnome.org.
</para>

<section>
<title>Adjusting Speech Parameters</title>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Right Arrow</keycap>
</keycombo>: increase speech rate
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Left Arrow</keycap>
</keycombo>: decrease speech rate
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Up Arrow</keycap>
</keycombo>: raise the pitch
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Down Arrow</keycap>
</keycombo>: lower the pitch
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Flat Review Commands</title>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-7</emphasis>: Move the flat review cursor to the previous line and read it.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-8</emphasis>: Read the current line.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-9</emphasis>: Move the flat review cursor to the next line and read it.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-4</emphasis>: Move the flat review cursor to the previous word and read it.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-5</emphasis>: Read the current word.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-6</emphasis>: Move the flat review cursor to the next word and read it.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-1</emphasis>: Move the flat review cursor to the previous character and read it.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-2</emphasis>: Read the current character.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-3</emphasis>: Move the flat review cursor to the next character and read it.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-/</emphasis>: Perform a left mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-*</emphasis>: Perform a right mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
<note>
<para>
The above commands apply when working with objects as well as when working with text. For example, if the flat review cursor were positioned on a menu bar, pressing the "read current line" command (<emphasis role="strong">Numpad-8</emphasis>) would 
speak the names of all visible menus. Similarly, pressing "read next word" would speak the object to the right of the flat review cursor on the same line, or move flat review to the next line if no more objects 
were found.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bookmark Commands</title>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>[1-6]</keycap>
</keycombo>: add a bookmark in this numbered slot. If a bookmark already exists it will be replaced.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>[1-6]</keycap>
</keycombo>: go to the position pointed to by the bookmark bound to this numbered slot.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>[1-6]</keycap>
</keycombo>: "Where am I" information for this bookmark relative to the current pointer location.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>B</keycap>
</keycombo> and 
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>B</keycap>
</keycombo>: move between the given bookmarks for the given application or page.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>B</keycap>
</keycombo>: save the defined bookmarks for the current application or page.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Miscellaneous Functions</title>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Numpad</keycap>
<keycap>+</keycap>
</keycombo>: "say all" command; reads from the current position of the caret to the end of the document.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Numpad</keycap>
<keycap>Enter</keycap>
</keycombo>: "where am I" command; speaks information such as the title of the current application window as well as the name of the control that currently has focus.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F1</keycap>
</keycombo>: enter Learn mode (press 
<keycap>Escape</keycap> to exit)</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F</keycap>
</keycombo>: speak font and attribute information for the current character.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Space</keycap>
</keycombo>: launch the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Space</keycap>
</keycombo>: reload user settings and reinitialize services as necessary. Also launch the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog for the current 
application.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>S</keycap>
</keycombo>: toggle speech on and off.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F11</keycap>
</keycombo>: toggle table-reading mode between single cell or entire row.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Q</keycap>
</keycombo>: quit <application>Orca</application>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Commands for Debugging</title>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F3</keycap>
</keycombo>: report information on the currently active script.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F4</keycap>
</keycombo>: cycle through <application>Orca</application>'s various debug levels.
</para>
<note>
<para>
In order for the next three commands to be of use, <application>Orca</application> needs to be started from a virtual console or via <application>gnome-terminal</application>. Output is sent only to the console (i.e., it is not sent to speech or Braille).
</para>
</note>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F5</keycap>
</keycombo>: prints a debug listing of all known applications to the console where <application>Orca</application> is running.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F7</keycap>
</keycombo>: prints debug information about the ancestry of the object with focus.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo>
<keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>F8</keycap>
</keycombo>: prints debug information about the current application.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<title>Orca is not speaking. What is going wrong?</title>
<para>
See 
<ulink url='http://live.gnome.org/Orca/GnomeSpeech'>
Troubleshooting Speech</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>My desktop has stopped responding. What do I do?
</title>
<para>
If you can get to a terminal (or press 
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> to open the "Run Command" dialog box), try restarting <application>Orca</application> by issuing another <application>Orca</application> command in a terminal window. This will force any existing <application>Orca</application> process to exit and will then restart <application>Orca</application>. This 
sometimes has the effect of unhanging the desktop (which is usually due to an ill-behaved application).
</para>
<para>
If you cannot get to a terminal window, try 
pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Backspace</keycap>
</keycombo>: shut down the X Window System server. This should return you to the login screen.
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="themes-0">
<title>Desktop Appearance Enhancement</title>
<para>
This chapter describes the methods you can use to change the appearance of the GNOME Desktop in order to enhance the accessibility of the desktop for users with visual 
impairments.
</para>

<section id="themes-1">
<title>Customization Options</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
There are several ways to customize the appearance of the GNOME Desktop to suit your 
specific needs:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Themes</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Themes are the most effective way to change the appearance of the desktop in a 
consistent manner. See <xref linkend="themes-2"/> for more information about themes and how to use them to achieve the type of desktop environment that you 
require.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Desktop and Application-Specific Configuration Settings
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
You can customize different components of the desktop to achieve the display settings that you require. You can configure the desktop and applications in addition to using themes or as an alternative to themes. See <xref linkend="themes-7"/> for more information.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
The following table summarizes the changes that you can make to the GNOME Desktop and where you can make the changes. This guide does not provide detailed instructions about how to customize the desktop. For detailed instructions about how to use the customization tools that the desktop provides, refer to the Help for each tool or to the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?prefs">User Guide</ulink>.
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="themes-TBL-1">
<title>Quick Reference to Customizing the Appearance of the Desktop
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33.04*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="14.50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>To change the...</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Use...
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Overall appearance of the desktop using high-contrast colors, low-contrast colors, or large print.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>The <application>Theme</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Appearance of the desktop background only.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
The <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool and the file manager <guilabel>Backgrounds and Emblems</guilabel> menu item.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Font displayed on the desktop background and
in all desktop applications.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>The <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Default font settings of the <application>Text Editor</application>,  <application>Terminal</application> or 
<application>Help</application> application.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Normally these applications use the default 
application font that is specified in the 
<application>Font</application> preference tool but can be overridden in the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog for the application.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="themes-2">
<title>Using Themes to Customize the Desktop</title>
<para>
This section describes how to use themes to customize the appearance of the GNOME Desktop.
</para>

<section id="themes-3">
<title>Introduction to Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
A theme is a group of coordinated settings that specifies how a desktop component or a group of desktop components appears. You can use themes to modify and control the appearance of the desktop in a consistent manner. When you apply a theme, the system
modifies many desktop components simultaneously to achieve the desired effect.
For example, if you apply a theme that increases the font size across the desktop, the theme also modifies the size of panels and icons on the desktop for optimum compatibility with the font size.
</para>
<para>
A theme contains settings that affect different parts of the desktop: 
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Controls</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The controls setting for a theme determines the visual appearance of all windows, applications, panels, and panel applications. The controls setting also determines the visual appearance of the GNOME-compliant 
interface items that appear on windows, applications, panels, and panel applications such as menus, icons, and buttons. Some of
the control options that are available in the desktop are designed for special accessibility needs.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Window Border</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The window frame setting determines the appearance of the border around windows only.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Icon</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The icon setting determines the appearance of icons on panels and on the desktop background.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section id="themes-4">
<title>Choosing Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>desktop</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To choose a theme, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance
</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The themes
are listed under the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on a theme in the list box to choose a new theme. The system automatically applies the theme to the desktop. 
</para>
<para>
There are several themes available that suit different accessibility needs, as described in the following table:
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="themes-TBL-2">
<title>Themes Designed for Accessibility Requirements
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Theme Name</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Inverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>Large Print</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
This theme suggests an increased font size of 18pt. The background and foreground colors are the same as those specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> desktop theme. To apply the suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Large Print</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
This theme suggests an increased font size of 18pt using dark text on a light background. To apply the suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Large Print Inverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
This theme suggests an increased font size of 18pt using light text on a dark background. To apply the suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
To view the controls, window frame, and icon settings that are associated with a theme, select a theme in the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, then click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog contains a tabbed section for each setting category. Each tabbed section lists the options that are available and the current setting for the theme is highlighted. 
</para>
</section>

<section id="themes-20">
<title>Modifying the Controls Setting for a Theme</title>
<para>
To modify the controls setting that is associated with a theme, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, select the theme that you want to modify.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Controls</guilabel> tab to display the controls options that are available.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the controls option that you want to associate with the current theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The following table lists 
the controls options that are suitable for accessibility needs: 
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table frame="topbot">
<title>Controls Options Designed for Accessibility Requirements
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Control Option</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Uses low-contrast colors for the background and foreground text. 
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool. The background and foreground colors are the same as those 
specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> desktop theme.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using high-contrast colors. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrintInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using high-contrast colors. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Uses low-contrast colors for the background and foreground text. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="themes-5">
<title>Modifying the Window Border Setting for a Theme
</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>window border</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To modify the window border setting that is associated with a theme, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, select the theme that you want to modify. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Window Border</guilabel> tab to display the window frame options that are available. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the window frame option that you want to associate with the current theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The <guilabel>Atlanta</guilabel> option is designed for accessibility. 
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="themes-19">
<title>Modifying the Icon Setting for a Theme</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>icon</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To modify the icon setting that is associated with a theme, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, select the theme that you want to modify. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tab to display the icon options that are available. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the icon option that you want to associate with the theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The following table lists the icon options that are suitable for accessibility needs:
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table frame="topbot">
<title>Icon Options Designed for Accessibility Requirements
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Icon Option</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark-on-light icons using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Provides light-on-dark icons using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Uses low-contrast colors for the background and foreground text. 
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<!--<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
The background and foreground colors are the same as 
those specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> 
desktop theme. To increase the font size, you must use 
the <application>Font</application> Preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using 
high-contrast colors. To increase the font size, you 
must use the <application>Font</application> Preference 
tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrintInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using 
high-contrast colors. To increase the font size, you 
must use the <application>Font</application> Preference 
tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Uses low-contrast colors for the background and 
foreground text. To increase the font size, you must use
the <application>Font</application> Preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>-->
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="themes-6">
<title>Creating Your Own Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>creating own</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
For information about how to create your own themes, see the <ulink type="help" 
url="ghelp:system-admin-guide?themes-0">
System Administration Guide</ulink>. 
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="themes-7">
<title>Customizing Specific Components of the Desktop
</title>
<para>
This section describes how to customize specific components of the GNOME Desktop individually.
</para>

<section id="themes-8">
<title>Customizing the Desktop Background</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop background</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The themes do not affect the desktop background. Therefore, to modify the desktop background to complement your desktop, you must customize the desktop background separately using the <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool. To start the <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
<guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and choose a background from the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</section>

<section id="themes-9">
<title>Customizing Desktop Background Objects</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop background objects</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The size of the icons that are displayed on the desktop background is controlled by the <application>File Management</application> preference tool. To change the size of the icons, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>File Manager</application> window, choose the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu item.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Views</guilabel> tabbed section.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Icon View Defaults</guilabel> group, select the zoom level that you require in the <guilabel>Default Zoom Level</guilabel> drop-down list.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="themes-10">
<title>Customizing Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<anchor id="themes-13"/>
<anchor id="themes-14"/>
<para>
This section describes how to customize
the font settings for the desktop and frequently-used applications.
</para>
<para>
If you have difficulty with the default font type and font size that is used on the desktop and desktop background, you can customize the font settings to suit your needs. 
</para>
<para>
You can specify individual font settings for the following desktop components and applications: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Entire desktop (excluding the desktop background)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Desktop background only</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Terminal</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Text Editor</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Help</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Web Browser</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section id="themes-11">
<title>Customizing Desktop Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The <application>Font</application> preference tool allows you to specify the default fonts for the desktop.
</para>
<para>
To start the <application>Font</application> preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <guilabel>
Fonts</guilabel> tab contains the following options: 
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Application Font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a default font to use for the text that is displayed on the desktop, including the text displayed on the windows and dialogs associated with GNOME-compliant applications and panel applications.
</para>
<note>
<para>
If you use the <application>Theme</application> preference tool to select a theme and you click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button, the font that is associated with the theme overrides the font from the <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Document Font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for displaying documents.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Desktop Font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for the text that is displayed on the desktop background only.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Window Title Font</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for the text that is displayed in the titlebar area of windows.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Fixed Width Font</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for editing documents.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Font Rendering</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>
To specify how to render fonts on the desktop, select one of the following options:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Monochrome</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Best Shapes</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Best Contrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Subpixel Smoothing</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<note>
<para>
If you use large fonts, you may need to change the size of panes in some applications, such as the file manager and Help browser. 
</para>
</note>
<para>
For more information about the <application>Font</application> preference tool, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?prefs-font">
User Guide</ulink>. 
</para>
</section>

<section id="themes-cust">
<title>Customizing Application Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>custom desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>set choose individual font</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
By default, GNOME applications use the default font specified in the <application>Font</application> preference tool. Some applications allow this default 
font to be customized. These applications are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#yelp">
Help Browser</ulink> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gedit?
gedit-prefs-fontsandcolors">
Text Editor</ulink> </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-terminal#
gnome-terminal-prefs-general">
Terminal</ulink> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:epiphany#
ephy-customize">Web Browser</ulink> 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="themes-15">
<title>Meeting Specific Accessibility Needs</title>
<para>
The following sections summarize the steps you need to take to improve the accessibility of the desktop in a particular area. 
</para>

<section id="themes-16">
<title>Achieving a High- or Low-Contrast Desktop</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>high contrast desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>low contrast desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To achieve a high- or low-contrast desktop, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <application>Theme</application> preference tool to select the high-contrast or low-contrast desktop theme that you require.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool to customize your desktop background as follows:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Set the <guilabel>Desktop Wallpaper</guilabel> to <guilabel>No Wallpaper</guilabel>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Set the <guilabel>Desktop Colors</guilabel> to <guilabel>Solid Color</guilabel>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select a background color that suits your needs.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>Terminal</application> application, ensure that the <guilabel>Use colors from system theme</guilabel> option is selected in the <guilabel>Colors</guilabel> tabbed section of the <guilabel>Editing
Profile</guilabel> dialog.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>gedit</application> (Text Editor) application, ensure that the <guilabel>Use default theme colors</guilabel> option is selected in the <guilabel>Fonts &amp; Colors</guilabel> tabbed section of the 
<guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="themes-17">
<title>Achieving a Large Print Desktop</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>large print desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To achieve a large-print desktop, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <application>Theme</application> preference tool to select the <guilabel>Large Print</guilabel> theme.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button to increase the size of the font that is used on the desktop and on window frames.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Desktop Font</guilabel> option in the <application>Font</application> preference tool to increase the font that is displayed on desktop background objects.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Increase the font size that is used to display the contents of the <application>Terminal</application> 
application window. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
If the <guilabel>Use default theme font</guilabel> option is selected in the <application>gedit</application> (Text Editor) <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog, <application>gedit</application> uses the font size that is specified in the large-print theme that you selected. However, if the <guilabel>Use default theme font
</guilabel> option is not selected, increase the font size that is used to display the contents of the <application>gedit</application> text editor window. See the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gedit?gedit-prefs-fontsandcolors">gedit manual</ulink> for more information.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
If you use applications that use panes, such as the file manager and Help browser, you may need to change the size of panes to accommodate the large print. See the online help for the appropriate application for 
more information.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>
