<chapter id="orca">
<title>Orca Screen-Reader and Magnifier</title>
<para>
This chapter describes <application>Orca</application>, a screen reader and magnifier application provided with GNOME.
</para>

<section>
<title>Orca Configuration GUI</title>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI allows you to customize the behavior and features of <application>Orca</application>, such as speech, braille, and magnification. For example, you can select which speech synthesis engine you want to use, whether braille is enabled or not, and which magnification preferences you want. You can select which general keyboard layout you want (desktop or laptop) and you can also examine and modify the existing keyboard layout with fine-grained control. To bring up the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI, press <keycombo><keycap>ORCA_MODIFIER</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, where ORCA_MODIFIER is <keycap>Insert</keycap> when you use the desktop key bindings and <keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap> when you use the laptop key bindings. See also the [[Orca/AppSpecificSettings| Application Specific Settings]] page for how to set settings specific to a single application.
</para>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI is a dialog containing several tabbed pages, each of which is described in the following sections.
</para>

<section>
<title>General Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata 
fileref="figures/General_Tab.png" 
format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - General Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The <guilabel>General</guilabel> page allows you to customize general aspects of <application>Orca</application>. These include the following:
</para>

<section>
<title>Keyboard Layout</title>
<para>
The keyboard layout section allows you to specify if you will be working on a laptop (small) or desktop (large, with a numeric keypad) keyboard. You select which layout you want by selecting one of the following options:
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Desktop</emphasis> - if selected, the Desktop Keyboard Layout (link kb table) will be used.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Laptop</emphasis> - if selected, the Laptop Keyboard Layout (link kb table) will be used.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Show Orca main window</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata 
fileref="figures/MainWindow.png" 
format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Main window
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> main window provides you with a graphical way to display the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI (also accessible with <keycombo><keycap>ORCA_MODIFIER</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, where ORCA_MODIFIER is <keycap>Insert</keycap> when you use the desktop key bindings and <keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap> when you use the laptop key bindings). The main window also provides a <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> option, also available with <keycombo><keycap>ORCA_MODIFIER</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>). Many users do not like the <application>Orca</application> main window because it shows up in the window manager's tab order when you press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> to switch windows. By deselecting the "Show Orca main window" button, you can tell <application>Orca</application> to not show the <application>Orca</application> main window.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Quit Orca without Confirmation</title>
<para>
Normally, when you press <keycombo><keycap>ORCA_MODIFIER</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> to quit <application>Orca</application> or press the <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> button in the <application>Orca</application> main window, <application>Orca</application> will pop up a confirmation dialog asking you if you want to quit. Unchecking this option prevents the confirmation window from appearing.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Disable gksu keyboard grab</title>
<para>
When running commands from the launch menu, many distributions use an application known as <application>gksu</application> to authorize the user to run these commands; <application>gksu</application> is the GUI that asks you for your password. When it runs, <application>gksu</application> enables what is known as a "keyboard grab," which is a feature to prevent keyboard actions from going to any other application on the desktop, including <application>Orca</application>.  The result of a keyboard grab is that <application>Orca</application> will not receive any keyboard events, preventing <application>Orca</application> from functioning normally.
</para>
<para>
By selecting the "Disable gksu keyboard grab" button, you will turn off the keyboard grab behavior, allowing <application>Orca</application> to function normally with system administration applications.
</para>
<note>
<para>
The keyboard grab is a security attempt by <application>gksu</application> to prevent nefarious applications from "sniffing" the keyboard and grabbing secret information.  Please be advised that disabling the gksu keyboard grab feature can expose you to such nefarious behavior. If you do not feel comfortable with this, you can always use the root account for system administration purposes. To do so, you need to enable the root account for login, and then logout and log back in as root whenever you want to perform a system administration command.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Present tooltips</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell <application>Orca</application> to present information about tooltips when they appear as the result of mouse hovering. Specific actions to force tooltips to appear, such as pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> when an object has focus, will always result in tooltips being presented, regardless of this setting.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak object under mouse</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell <application>Orca</application> to present information about the object under the mouse when you move it around the screen. Note that this can cause <application>Firefox</application> and <application>Thunderbird</application> versions 2.x and earlier to crash; this is not a problem with <application>Firefox</application> and <application>Thunderbird</application> versions 3.x and later.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Start Orca when you login</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell the system to automatically launch <application>Orca</application> when you log in.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speech Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata 
fileref="figures/Speech_Tab.png" 
format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Speech Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The speech page allows you to customize how <application>Orca</application> uses speech synthesis.
</para>
</section>

</section>
</chapter>
