<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.2">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "2.2">
  <!ENTITY date "March 2003">
  <!-- Information about the entities
       The legal.xml file contains legal information, there is no need to edit the file. 
       Use the appversion entity to specify the version of the application.
       Use the manrevision entity to specify the revision number of this manual.
       Use the date entity to specify the release date of this manual.
       Use the app entity to specify the name of the application. -->
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo> 
  <title>Introduction to GNOME V&manrevision;</title>
    <copyright> 
      <year>2001</year> 
      <year>2003</year> 
      <holder>Alexander Kirillov</holder> 
    </copyright>
    <copyright> 
      <year>2000</year> 
      <year>2001</year> 
      <holder>Red Hat, Inc.</holder> 
    </copyright>
    <copyright> 
      <year>2000</year> 
      <year>2001</year> 
      <holder>David A. Wheeler</holder> 
    </copyright>
    <publisher> 
      <publishername> GNOME Documentation Project </publishername> 
    </publisher> 

   &legal;

 <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>Alexander</firstname>
    <surname>Kirillov</surname>		
	<affiliation> 
	  <orgname>GNOME Documentation Project</orgname> 
	  <address> <email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>David</firstname>
    <surname>Mason</surname>		
	<affiliation> 
	  <orgname>Red Hat, Inc.</orgname> 
	  <address> <email>dcm@redhat.com</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>David</firstname>
	<surname>Wheeler</surname>		
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>Introduction to GNOME V&manrevision;</revnumber> 
	<date>&date;</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">
               Alexander Kirillov
	    	<email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email>,
	    David C. Mason,  David A. Wheeler
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>Introduction to GNOME V2.0</revnumber> 
	<date>June 2002</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">
               Alexander Kirillov
	    	<email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email>,
	    David C. Mason,  David A. Wheeler
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	  <para>Updated for GNOME 2.0. Some descriptions and
	  screenshots are borrowed from <citetitle>GNOME Desktop 2.0
	  User Guide</citetitle> (May 2002), by Sun GNOME
	  Documentation Team <email>gdocteam@sun.com></email>,
	  published by GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>Introduction to GNOME</revnumber> 
	<date>April 2001</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">Alexander Kirillov
	    <email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email>, 
            David C. Mason,  David A. Wheeler
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	  <para>This version described GNOME 1.4</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
    </revhistory> 



  <releaseinfo>
      This document was  last updated in &date;. It describes GNOME
      2.2.   
    </releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice> <title>Feedback</title> <para> To report a bug or
      make a suggestion regarding this document, follow the directions
      in the <ulink url="ghelp:gnome-feedback" type="help">GNOME
      Feedback Page</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice> 

  </articleinfo>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="whatisGnome">
    <title>What Is GNOME?</title>
    <para>    
      GNOME is a user-friendly graphical desktop environment for UNIX and
      UNIX-like systems.  GNOME includes a panel (for starting
      applications and displaying status), a desktop (where data and
      applications can be placed), a set of standard desktop tools and
      applications, and a set of conventions that make it easy for
      applications to cooperate and be consistent with each other.
      Users of other operating systems or environments should feel
      right at home using the powerful graphics-driven environment
      GNOME provides. GNOME runs on a number of UNIX-like operating
      systems, including Linux, FreeBSD, and Solaris. 
    </para>
   <para> GNOME is completely open source (free software) developed by
      hundreds of programmers around the world. Both the source code
      and ready-to-run binaries of GNOME are available for download on
      the Internet; they are distributed under the terms of the <ulink
      type="help" url="ghelp:gpl"> GNU General Public
      License</ulink> (and its cousins, <ulink type="help"
      url="ghelp:lgpl">Lesser General Public License</ulink> and
      <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl">Free Documentation
      License</ulink> for libraries and documentation
      respectively). In particular, this means that everyone is free
      to use, copy or distribute GNOME. If you would like to learn
      more about the GNOME project please visit the <ulink
      url="http://www.gnome.org" type="http">GNOME website</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
      GNOME is highly configurable, enabling you to set your desktop
      the way you want it to look and feel.  GNOME supports many human
      languages, and more are added every month.  GNOME even supports
      several drag and drop protocols for maximum interoperability
      with non-GNOME applications.
   </para>

   <para>
    GNOME comes from the acronym for the GNU Network Object Model
    Environment (GNOME).  GNOME is a part of the larger GNU project,
    started in 1984 to develop a completely free UNIX-like operating
    system.  For more information, visit the <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org" type="http">GNU website</ulink>.  
    </para>
    <para>
      This guide describes GNOME 2.2 which is the latest (as of March 
      2003) release of GNOME. 
    </para>
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="about">
    <title>Purpose of This Document</title>
    <para>
      This document gives you a short introduction to GNOME. It is not
      intended to cover all details of GNOME; if you need more
      information, you should read the detailed manuals listed in <xref
      linkend="otherinfo"/>. Also, this document assumes you already have
      GNOME installed; if you need help installing GNOME, please check
      the instructions on the <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org"
      type="http">GNOME website</ulink>.
    </para>
 
    <para> This document was written by the members of the GNOME
      Documentation Project (GDP). If you have any comments or
      suggestions about this document or if you can offer any other
      help in improving or translating GNOME documentation, please
      send an e-mail to <email>docs@gnome.org</email>, or visit the <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp/" type="http">GDP
      website</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para> The authors of this document assume that you are
      using the default configuration of GNOME. GNOME is highly
      configurable, so it is easy to change not only the look but also
      the behavior of GNOME; however, we recommend that you do so only
      after you already have some experience with GNOME.
    </para>
  </sect1>
<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="conventions">
    <title>Mouse Conventions Used in This Document</title> 
    <para>
      Before  describing GNOME, let us introduce some terms used not 
      only in this guide but in all GNOME documents. Most importantly,
      we need to clarify the use of mouse buttons and clicks. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Most GNOME documents assume that you are using a standard (for
      UNIX) 3-button mouse and talk about left, right, and middle
      mouse buttons; if a document says <quote>click</quote> without
      explicitly specifying the button, the left button is
      assumed. <!-- Some documents use notations <quote>mouse button
      1</quote>, <quote>mouse button 2</quote> and <quote>mouse button
      3</quote> (or MB1, MB2, MB3 for short) for left, middle, and
      right buttons respectively. -->
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are using a two-button mouse, you can emulate the middle
      mouse button by pressing left and right buttons simultaneously;
      if you have a wheel mouse, the wheel can be used in place of the
      middle mouse button.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can switch the roles of the buttons using the <application>Mouse
      preference tool</application> in the <guisubmenu>Desktop
      Preferences</guisubmenu> submenu of
      <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu. Many left-handers
      choose to reverse the right and left buttons. If you have done
      so, you need to use the right mouse button whenever a document
      instructs you to click, and use the <emphasis>left</emphasis> mouse
      button whenever a document talks about
      <quote>right-clicking</quote> or mouse button 3.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you use a mouse with an unusual placement of buttons, a
      trackball, or some other input device, you need to find out
      which buttons correspond to <quote>right</quote>,
      <quote>left</quote> and <quote>middle</quote>; this information
      can usually be found in the manual which came with your
      device. Usually, the <quote>left</quote> button (MB1) is the one
      under your index finger. 
    </para>

  </sect1>


<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="firstglance">
    <title>First Glance at GNOME: Desktop and Panel</title> 
    <para>
      <xref linkend="desktop-fig"/> shows an example of GNOME
      running. GNOME is very configurable, so your screen may look
      quite different.
    </para>
<!-- figure -->
    <figure id="desktop-fig">
     <title>Sample GNOME Display.</title>
     <screenshot>	  
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject><imagedata
		fileref="figures/typical_anno_desktop.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject> 
	    <phrase>Figure of GNOME desktop, with menu panel, usual
	    panel, Nautilus window, and standard desktop icons: home
	    folder, Start here and Trash </phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
   </figure>
<!-- /figure --> 
<!-- =======Subsection ============ -->
<sect2 id="panel">
      <title>Panel</title>
      <para>
	The two long bars at the top and bottom of <xref
	linkend="desktop-fig"/> are <emphasis>panels</emphasis>. The
	top one is called the menu panel, the bottom one is an edge
	panel (you can have more than one  edge panel). 
	  Panels can contain a number of useful objects, such as 
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and
	  <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>  menus</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu gives you
	      access to all GNOME applications installed on your
	      system. <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu contains useful
	      commands such as <guimenuitem>Search for
	      files</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Run
	      command</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Open
	      recent</guimenuitem> (documents),  and <guimenuitem>Log
	      Out</guimenuitem> command. In the screenshot above, you
	      can see both these menus on left side of the top
	      panel. </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Other menus</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Panels can also contain other menus. Most important of
	      them is the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> (sometimes also
	      called <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>) which combines
	      <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and
	      <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu. The panel can also
	      contain other menus  created
	      by the user.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Launchers</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>These are buttons that start various programs.
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Applets</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>These are tiny programs designed to
	      work inside the panel. For example,  the
	      <application>clock</application> applet in the middle 
	      of the top panel    shows the current time, and the
	      <application>Window List</application> applet in the
	      left side of the bottom panel shows the list of all application
	      windows  on your desktop (this will be discussed in
	      detail in <xref linkend="tasklist"/>). 
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      


      <para> As with all GNOME components, panels are highly
	configurable: you can add or remove application launchers and
	applets, edit the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu, change
	the panel background, or even remove and create new
	panels. This will be discussed in <xref
	linkend="customizing-panel"/>.
      </para>
      <note>
	<title>NOTE</title>
	<para>
	  The top panel in <xref linkend="desktop-fig"/> is called the
	  <emphasis>menu</emphasis> panel and has slightly different
	  properties than other panels. For example, you can not move
	  it to a different location.
	 </para>
	</note>
      <para>
	To configure an object, get help on it, or remove it
	from the panel, right-click on it and choose the appropriate
	item from the context menu. To hide the panel when you are not
	using it, click on one of the <guibutton>Hide
	buttons</guibutton>.  They are the small arrows at the ends of the
	panel.
      </para>
      <para>More panel operations are available from the
	<guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu, which you can open by
	right-clicking in any vacant space on the panel (for example,
	in the hide arrows).  To learn more about using panel, choose
	<guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem> from the
	<guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu. 
	</para>
    </sect2>
<!-- =======Subsection ============ -->
    <sect2 id="desktop"> 
      <title>Desktop</title> 
      <para>
	Everything outside the panel is called the <quote>desktop
	background</quote>. You can place icons for files,
	applications, and other items on the desktop background (a default
	collection of icons is installed with GNOME).  You can then
	double-click on an item to use it:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>   
	    If the item is a program, that program will start.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If it is a data file, the appropriate program will start
	    up with that data loaded.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>  

	  <para>
	    If it is a folder, the <application>File
	    Manager</application> will start and show the contents of
	    that directory. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The easiest way to place an item on the desktop is to drag a
	file from a file manager window, as described in detail in
	the <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:user-guide/wgosnautilus.xml">Nautilus 
	manual</ulink>. Once the item is placed on the desktop, you
	can move it around the desktop using the left mouse button, or
	you can click on it with the right mouse button to bring up
	the context menu which allows you to delete the item or change
	its properties.
      </para>
      <para>
	By default, your desktop contains the following objects:
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Home folder</term>
	    <listitem><para>This icon provides access to your home
	    folder. 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Start Here</term>
	    <listitem><para>
		This object provides access to special functions of
		GNOME file manager,
		<application>Nautilus</application>. These special
		functions include menu editing (see <xref
		  linkend="customizing-menus"/>), desktop preference
	    tools (see <xref 
		  linkend="customizing-desktop"/>), and  access to
	    machines on your local   
		local network (if you have any).  
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Trash can</term>
	    <listitem><para> Double-clicking on the trash can icon
		shows all files you have removed using the file
		manager. This gives you an opportunity to restore a
		file which was removed by mistake. You can also empty
		the trash can which permanently and irrevocably
		deletes all these files.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

<!-- =======Subsection ============ -->
    <sect2 id="mouse"> 
      <title>Using the Mouse</title> 
      <para>    
	As you have already seen, you can do almost anything just by
	clicking with your mouse. Here are some conventions which work
	almost anywhere in GNOME:
      </para> 

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"> 
	<listitem><para> 
	    Clicking on  an item with the left mouse button selects
	    (hilights) it. If you need to select several objects, hold down
	    the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while clicking. 
	  </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para> 
	    Double-clicking on an item runs the default action for
	    this item (running an application, opening the file, etc.) 
	  </para></listitem> 
	<listitem><para> 
	    Clicking on an item with the right mouse button brings up
	    the context menu, which contains all the commands and
	    information available for this item. If you have selected
	    a group of items, right-clicking on any of them will bring
	    up the context menu which applies to all of these items.
	  </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    You can
	    select text anywhere on the screen using the left mouse
	    button, and then insert this text into any other place on
	    the screen which accepts text input, by clicking with the
	    <link linkend="conventions">middle mouse button</link>.
	  </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	In addition, right-clicking on any vacant place on your
	desktop background brings up the <guimenu>Desktop
	Background</guimenu> menu, which allows you to change the
	desktop background image or other properties, or add a new object to
	the desktop.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- =======Subsection:Logging out ============ -->
    <sect2 id="logout"> 
      <title>Logging Out</title> 
      
      <para> To log out of GNOME, click on the
	<guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu and choose <guimenuitem>Log
	Out</guimenuitem>.<!-- GNOME will prompt you for confirmation;
	it will also give you an option to save the session &mdash;
	--> GNOME will automatically save the current session (that
	is, information about currently open applications and their
	location on the screen), so that when you log in next time, the
	same applications will be in the same places. Note this only
	works for applications which are fully GNOME-compliant.
      </para>
    </sect2>
	
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: working with windows =============== -->
<sect1 id="windows">
    <title>Working With Windows</title>
    <para>
      As most modern desktop environments, GNOME allows you to have
      several windows on your screen, with a different application
      running in each window. This section describes various windows
      operations: moving, resizing, closing, hiding. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Many of these operation are controlled by buttons located in the
      window titlebar. Descriptions in this section assume
      that you are using the default configuration of GNOME, so the
      buttons in the window titlebar look as  shown in
      <xref linkend="windowborder"/>.  
    </para>


<!-- figure -->
    <figure id="windowborder">
     <title>Window Titlebar Using Default Theme</title>
     <screenshot>
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject><imagedata
		fileref="figures/titlebar_anno_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject> 
	    <phrase>Titlebar in default style, focused. Window ops button in
	    the left side, minimize, maximize, and close buttons on
	    the right. </phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>

    </screenshot>
   </figure>
<!-- /figure --> 

    <note>
      <title>Note for advanced users</title>
      <para>
	All the windows operations are actually managed by a piece of
	software called <emphasis>window manager</emphasis>. By
	default, GNOME uses <application>Metacity</application> window
	manager, which is included with GNOME. GNOME can also be used
	with other window managers, such as
	<application>Sawfish</application> (which was used in GNOME
	1.4). To switch to <application>Sawfish</application> window
	manager, open a terminal window and enter the following
	command: <command>killall metacity; sawfish&amp;</command>. If
	everything worked smoothly, save current session by entering
	the command  <command>gnome-session-save</command> so that
	next time you login, <application>Sawfish</application> is
	started automatically. 
      </para>
    </note>      

    <para>
      So, what can you do with windows?
    </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	  Closing, Minimizing, and Maximizing Windows
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> To <emphasis>close</emphasis> a window, click on
	      the <guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button (with the
	      small <quote>x</quote>) in the right side of window
	      titlebar. If the application has any unsaved data, it
	      will prompt you to save it. You can also use keyboard
	      shortcut
	      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F4</keycap></keycombo>. 
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      To <emphasis>maximize</emphasis> a window, i.e. make it
	      fill the entire screen (except for the part taken by the
	      panels), click on the <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton>
	      button (middle button on the right side). Clicking on
	      this button once again will restore the window to its
	      original size.
	    </para>
	    <para> To <emphasis>minimize</emphasis> (sometimes also
	      called hide or iconify) a window, click on the
	      <guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button. The window will
	      disappear from the screen. However, it is not lost: the
	      application in this window continues running, no data is
	      lost &mdash; it is just temporarily hidden. All
	      minimized windows are shown in the <link
	      linkend="tasklist"><application>Window List</application>
	      applet</link> and can be restored as described below.
	    </para>
	    <para> A convenient alternative to minimizing windows is
	      to <quote>shade</quote> it, or <quote>roll up</quote> a
	      window into its own titlebar, so the titlebar is the
	      only part of the window left on the screen. You can roll
	      up and unroll a window by double-clicking on the
	      titlebar.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	     Raising and Lowering Windows
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Windows on your screen can overlap, so that one of
	      the windows is <quote>on top</quote> of another. You can
	      <quote>raise</quote> a window (i.e., put it on top of
	      all others) by clicking anywhere in that window. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	     Focus
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Of all the windows on your screen, only one is active
              (in computer parlance, <quote>focused</quote>), which means
              that anything you type on the keyboard will be sent to the
              application running in that window. (It does not mean that the
	      applications in other windows are idle &mdash; they can
	      be running as well.) To help you see which window has
	      focus, the titlebar of this window has a different color
	      (the left side is blue, as opposed to gray for all other
	      windows). By default, clicking in a window both raises it
              and gives focus to it. 
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You can also use the <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
	    <keycap>Tab</keycap> </keycombo> shortcut to switch
	    between windows. This cyclically switches between all existing
	    windows. The window to which you switch is raised and
	    given focus.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	     Moving and Resizing Windows
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> To move a window, drag its titlebar to a new
	      location using the left mouse button. You can also move
	      a window by clicking anywhere inside the window while
	      holding down the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key.
	    </para>
	    <para> 
	      To resize a window, place the mouse cursor on any of the
	      window borders  or corners. The
	      mouse cursor will change to an arrow pushing a line or
	      corner, allowing you to drag the border or corner to a new
	      position. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <sect2 id="tasklist">
      <title>Window List Applet</title>
      <para>
	All the windows on your desktop (including the minimized ones)
	are shown in the <application>Window List</application>
	applet, located on your panel. For each window, a mini-icon
	and the beginning of the window title is shown. To restore a
	minimized window, just click on its title in the
	<application>Window List</application>
	applet. Right-clicking on the window title brings up the
	context menu which allows you to shade a
	window, close it, etc. <!-- NEEDS WORK 
        or kill the application running in the
	window. The last option should only be used when an
	application is frozen and does not respond to <quote>close
	window</quote> command. If you kill an application, you lose
	all unsaved data! -->
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="wm-menus">
      <title>Window  Menu</title>
      <para>
	GNOME also provides a menu for
	each window; this menu contains all the operations for this
	window described above, and then some. To access this menu,
	click on the <guibutton>Window Menu</guibutton> button at the
	left side of the window titlebar, or use keyboard shortcut
	<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
 <!--   <sect2 id="wm-desktop-menu">
      <title>Root Menu</title>
      <para>
        Finally, <application>Sawfish</application> also provides a 
	so-called <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu. It can be accessed by
	clicking on any empty space of the desktop with the <link
	linkend="conventions">middle mouse button</link>. It contains
	the following items:
      </para>
      <variablelist> 
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Provides list of all windows, including minimized
	      ones. Selecting one of these windows restores it (if it
	      was minimized), and raises it over other windows. Very
	      convenient if you have so many windows that the one you
	      need is completely covered by others.  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Workspaces</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Allows you to switch from one workspace to another,
	    create and delete workspaces. See the <citetitle>GNOME Desktop
	    User Guide</citetitle>  for details. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem> 
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Programs</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Same as the <guisubmenu>Applications</guisubmenu> submenu
	      of the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>.   
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Customize</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Allows the user to customize
	      <application>Sawfish</application> (see <xref
	      linkend="customizing-wm"/> for details).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Provides links to the <application>Sawfish</application>
	      website, the <application>Sawfish</application> manual
	      (beware: this is not a user's manual but rather a manual
	      for people who write extensions/customizations to
	      <application>Sawfish</application> using the LISP
	      programming language), link to the <citetitle>GNOME User
	      Guide</citetitle>, and to the <ulink type="http"
	      url="http://www.gnome.org">GNOME website</ulink>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
	-->      
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="nautilus">
    <title>Nautilus: GNOME File Manager</title>
    <para>
      GNOME includes a <quote>graphical shell</quote>,
      <application>Nautilus</application>. It combines a file manager,
      a web browser, an FTP client, and much more. It also provides access
      to tools for customizing GNOME (thus replacing the 
      <application>GNOME Control Center</application> which was
      included in GNOME 1.4 and earlier releases).
    </para>

    <para>To open a new <application>Nautilus</application> window,
      choose <guimenuitem>Home folder</guimenuitem> from the
      <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu, or double-click on any
      folder icon on your desktop, such as the <guiicon>Home</guiicon>
      icon.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="nautilus-fm">
      <title>Managing Your Files With Nautilus</title>
<!-- figure -->
    <figure id="figure-nautilus">
     <title>Nautilus Window</title>
     <screenshot>
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject><imagedata
		fileref="figures/naut_iconview_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject> 
	    <phrase>Nautilus Window, in icon mode</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>

    </screenshot>
   </figure>
<!-- /figure --> 

      <para>
	As most modern graphic file managers,
        <application>Nautilus</application> shows the contents of a
        selected folder using icons to represent files and
        subfolders. Double-clicking on any file or folder opens it
        (for data files, it starts the appropriate application which
        opens this file, as configured in the <application>File Types and
        Programs </application> preference tool). Right-clicking on a
        file or folder produces a context menu.  Using this menu, you
        can delete or rename the file, view and change file properties
        or permissions, and more.
      </para>

      <para> <application>Nautilus</application> also provides an easy
	way to move and copy files between folders. To move a file
	from one folder to another, open these folders in separate
	<application>Nautilus</application> windows (you can use the
	<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>New
	window</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command).  Select the file
	you want to move, and drag it from one window into another
	using the mouse. You can also drag a file or folder to the
	desktop. To copy a file, press-and-hold the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
	key while dragging the file. You can also copy and move files
	using keyboard shortcuts
	<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>, 
	<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>X</keycap></keycombo>, and
	<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>
	(see <ulink url="ghelp:user-guide/wgosnautilus.xml"
	type="help">Nautilus manual</ulink> for details).  
      </para>
      <para>
	To delete files, drag them to the trash can icon on your
	desktop. 
      </para>
      <para> <application>Nautilus</application> provides many more
	tools to manipulate your files. It is also highly
	customizable, so you can easily change the way files are
	displayed (for example, you can choose a custom icon for a
	given file). For a detailed description of all these
	possibilities, read the <ulink url="ghelp:user-guide/wgosnautilus.xml"
	type="help"><citetitle>Nautilus manual</citetitle></ulink>,
	available from the <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu of
	<application>Nautilus</application>. 
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="nautilus-floppies">
      <title>
	Accessing Floppies and Other Removable Media</title>
      <para>
	To access files on floppy disks, CD-ROMs and other removable
	media, insert the disk in drive. Depending on configuration of
	your sytem, it may automatically recognize an inserted disk
	and put an icon for it on the desktop (in technical language,
	this is called <quote>automounting</quote>). Otherwise,
	right-click on any vacant spot on the desktop and choose the
	required media from the <guisubmenu>Disks</guisubmenu> submenu
	of the <guimenu>Desktop Background</guimenu> menu.  (This
	assumes your system is correctly configured, that is, you have
	the appropriate entry in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>
	file.)  This will place an icon for the disk on the
	desktop. Double-clicking on this icon  will open a
	<application>Nautilus</application> window showing the
	contents of the selected media.
      </para>
      <warning>
	<title>WARNING</title> 
	<para>
	  Before removing a floppy disk or other removable media
	  from the drive, you must
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		   Close all windows  accessing files on this
		disk, including <application>Nautilus</application>
		windows, terminal windows, and others
	      </para>
	  </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Unmount the disk by right-clicking on the disk icon on
		the desktop and choosing <guimenuitem>Unmount
		volume</guimenuitem> from the context menu. 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	  If you remove the disk without unmounting it first, you may
	  lose data!
	</para>
      </warning>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="nautilus-cool">
      <title>Other Features of Nautilus</title>
      <para>
	In addition to the basic features listed above,
	<application>Nautilus</application> has many other advanced
	and exciting capabilities. Here we list some of them,
	referring the reader to the <citetitle>Nautilus
	manual</citetitle> for detailed descriptions.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><application>Nautilus</application> can be customized
	    in many ways. In particular, you can change the background and
	    icons used for files and folders, and the fonts used for captions.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>You can assign a custom icon to a specific file, or
	    rescale the icon for a specific file, so that the most
	    important files really stand out. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>You can assign an <quote>emblem</quote> (such as
	    <guilabel>New</guilabel> or <guilabel>Favorite</guilabel>)
	    to a file. This emblem will be put on top of the file icon.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Files can be sorted by name, type, modification date,
	    or the emblem you assigned to them. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><application>Nautilus</application> can also be used
	    as a Web browser (with limited capabilities) and FTP client:
	    just enter the URL (for example,
	    <systemitem>ftp://ftp.gnome.org</systemitem>) in the
	    <guilabel>Go To</guilabel> field.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <application>Nautilus</application> can also be used
	    as a music player: just open a folder containing music files
	    in MP3 format, and  <application>Nautilus</application>
	    switches to music player  mode. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="customizing">
    <title>Customizing GNOME</title>
    <para>
      GNOME is highly configurable &mdash; you can change almost
      anything: background color, key bindings, location of panels,
      contents of the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>, and more. To see
      examples of different customizations of the GNOME desktop, take a
      look at the screenshots in <ulink type="http"
      url="http://vhost.dulug.duke.edu/~louie/screenshots/2.2/">GNOME
      users gallery</ulink> and notice how different they look.
    </para>
<!-- STOP HERE -->
    <para>The following sections list
      some of the most common customizations.  In addition, you can
      change properties of various items &mdash; most notably, panels
      and icons on your desktop &mdash; by clicking on them with the
      right mouse button and choosing
      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      Almost every GNOME application has its own preferences settings
      (look for <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> in the menus), so you can change,
      for example, colors used by the <application>GNOME
      Terminal</application> or make it transparent &mdash; the
      possibilities are unlimited!
    </para>
    <sect2 id="customizing-desktop">
      <title>Desktop Preferences</title>
      <para>
	To customize the appearance of your desktop and user
	interface, use special <emphasis>desktop preference
	tools</emphasis>, which can be found in the <guisubmenu>Desktop
	Preferences</guisubmenu> submenu of the <guimenu>Applications
	</guimenu> menu. You can also access the preferences tools by
	double-clicking on the <guiicon>Start Here</guiicon> icon on your
	desktop. This will open a <application>Nautilus</application>
	window. Double-click on <guiicon>Preferences</guiicon> and
	then on the tool you require.
    </para>
    <para>
      Below you will find an overview of the most commonly
      used preferences tools.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><guilabel>Background</guilabel></term>
	<listitem> 
	<para>
	    This tool allows you to change desktop background. You can
	    select solid color, gradient (visual effect where one
	    color blends gradually into another color), or an image
	    file.  
	</para>
	  <tip>
	    <title>TIP</title>
	    <para>
	      You can also change the desktop background color by
	      right-clicking on the desktop background and choosing
	      <guimenuitem>Change Desktop Background</guimenuitem>, or
	      by dragging a color from another window or dialog to
	      the desktop background. 
	    </para>
	  </tip> 
      </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	  <term><guilabel>Theme</guilabel>
	  </term>
	  <listitem> 
	    <para>
	      This tool allows you to change the desktop theme. A
	      <emphasis>theme</emphasis> is a collection of settings
	      that determine the look of your desktop and all GNOME
	      applications. It consists
	      of the following components:
	    </para>
	    <variablelist>
	      <varlistentry>
		<term>Controls</term> <listitem><para> This component
		(sometimes also called <quote>widget</quote> theme)
		determines the appearance of menus, panels, toolbars,
		buttons, and other elements of user interface in all
		GNOME applications.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </varlistentry>
	      <!-- ========== -->
	      <varlistentry>
		<term>Window borders</term>
		<listitem><para>
		    This component determines the appearance of
		window borders, titlebar, and buttons placed in the
		titlebar. 
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	      </varlistentry>
	      <!-- ========== -->
	      <varlistentry>
		<term>Icon theme</term> 
		<listitem>
		  <para> This component determines the set of icons
		    used by GNOME file manager and other applications
		    for files of various types. These icons are also
		    used on the desktop, for files you place there and
		    for standard objects such as home directory or
		    <guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> location.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	      </varlistentry>
	    </variablelist>
	    <note>
	      <title>NOTE</title>
	      <para>
		Users upgrading from GNOME 2.0 will notice that the
		layout of this tool and terminology has changed: GNOME
		2.2 uses the word <quote>theme</quote> to refer to the
		complete collection of appearance settings, so a theme
		now consists of several components. In GNOME 2.0, this
		was called a <quote>metatheme</quote>.
	      </para>
	    </note>
	    <para>
              The theme tool allows you to select one of the themes
	      installed as part of your GNOME distribution. You can
	      also create a custom theme by selecting individual theme
	      components (Icon, Window border). To do so, click on
	      <guibutton>Details</guibutton> button. Finally, you can
	      download and install more themes from the Internet. In
	      particular, you can find many themes at the <ulink
	      type="http" url="http://art.gnome.org/">GNOME
	      theme</ulink> website. Please note that this site (as
	      well as many other Interent resources) use more
	      technical (and more precise) terminology: the
	      <guilabel>Controls</guilabel> component is called a
	      <quote>GTK2 theme</quote>, and <guilabel>Window
	      borders</guilabel> component is called a <quote>Metacity
	      theme</quote>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term><guilabel>Font</guilabel>
	  </term>
	  <listitem> 
	  <para>
	      This tool allows you to choose the default font which will
	      be used by  menus, dialogs, and other user interface
	      elements. You can also choose fonts to be used for icon
	      captions on the desktop and for windows titlebars. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </sect2>
<!--    <sect2 id="customizing-wm">
      <title>Customizing the Window Manager</title>
      <para>
	To customize the <application>Sawfish</application> window
	manager, middle-click on the desktop and choose the
	<guimenuitem>Customize</guimenuitem> submenu. This submenu
	contains a number of customization tools. The same tools can
	also be accessed using <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Applications</guimenu> 
	  <guisubmenu>Desktop Preferences</guisubmenu> 
	  <guisubmenu>Advanced</guisubmenu>
	  <guisubmenu>Sawfish</guisubmenu>
	</menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para>
	The most popular customization tool is
	<guilabel>Appearance</guilabel>, which allows you to select
	the window manager theme (which determines the appearance of
	the window frame, titlebar, and buttons) and the font to use in the window
	titlebar. Other tools (such as the <guilabel>Bindings</guilabel>
	tool which allows you to specify keybindings for various
	window operations) are only recommended for advanced users.
      </para>
    </sect2> -->
    <sect2 id="customizing-panel">
      <title>Customizing Panels</title>
      <para>
	You can customize the GNOME panels as follows:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To remove a panel, right-click on a vacant space on the
	      panel and choose <guimenuitem>Remove this
	      panel</guimenuitem> from the panel context menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To create a new panel, right-click on a vacant space on
	      any existing panel and choose <guimenuitem>Create 
	      panel</guimenuitem> from the panel context menu.
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To move an existing panel to a new location, drag it
	      with the middle mouse button. 
	    </para>
	    <note>
	      <title>NOTE</title>
	      <para>The menu panel can not be  moved.</para>
	    </note>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To modify a panel's properties (background, size,
	      auto-hide),  right-click on a vacant space on the
	      panel and choose <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>
	      from the panel context menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To remove an object (menu, applet, or application launcher)
	      from the panel, right-click on the object and choose
	      <guimenuitem>Remove from panel</guimenuitem> from the
	      object context menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To add a new object to the panel, right-click on a
	      vacant space on the panel and choose
	      <guimenuitem>Add to panel</guimenuitem> 
	      from the panel context menu. Alternatively, to add an
	      application from one of the menus as a launcher to the
	      panel,  right-click on the menu
	      item and choose <guimenuitem>Add this launcher to
	      panel</guimenuitem> from the context menu.  
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To move a panel object, drag it with the middle mouse
	      button. You can even drag an object from one panel to
	      another. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To configure a panel object, right-click on it and choose
	      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> from the context
	      menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="customizing-menus">
      <title>Customizing Menus</title>
      <para>
	To modify the appearance of menus, use
	<application>Theme</application> and
	<application>Font</application> preference tools described in
	<xref linkend="customizing-desktop"/>.  You can also customize
	the <emphasis>contents</emphasis> of the
	<guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu. To do this, open 
	<guilabel>Start Here</guilabel> object on the desktop and
	double-click on <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> icon. This
	will show the contents of the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
	menu as if it were a folder. Now you can move, add, and delete
	items in this menu in the same way you move or delete
	files. For more information, see <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:user-guide/wgoseditmainmenu.xml">Working With
	Menus</ulink> chapter of <citetitle>GNOME User
	Guide</citetitle>. 
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="apps">
    <title>GNOME Applications and Utilities</title>
    <para>
      GNOME comes with many applications and utilities; in addition,
      GNOME allows you to use any third party applications such as
      <application>Netscape</application>, KDE applications, or other
      applications and utilities installed on your system. You can
      also use  GNOME 1.x applications under GNOME 2.2 (if you have
      installed appropriate GNOME 1.x libraries). Note, however, that
      GNOME 1.x applications will not use font and theme settings of
      GNOME 2.2, so their appearance will differ from that of GNOME
      2.2 applications. 
    </para>

    <para>
      Below is a partial list of some of the most useful tools and
      applications found in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and
      <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menus. You can access these menus by
      clicking on the corresponding button in the <guilabel>Menu
      Panel</guilabel>, or by using keyboards shortcut
      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo>. 
    </para>

  
  <sect2 id="actions">
      <title>Actions Menu</title>
      <para>
	This menu contains the following utilities. 
      </para>
      
      
      <variablelist>	
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Run Program</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      This allows you to manually enter a command to run,
	      saving you from starting full-blown terminal emulator.  
	    </para>
	    <tip>
	      <title>TIP</title>
	      <para>
		You can also start the <application>Run
		Program</application> dialog by using the <keycombo>
		<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>
		shortcut.
	      </para>
	    </tip>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Search for Files</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>This utility allows you to search for files and
	    folders on your system.  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Screenshot</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      This utility takes a screenshot of your desktop and saves it in a
	      file. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Open Recent</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      This utility shows the list of files you have recently
	      accessed. You can choose one of these files to open it
	      using the appropriate application. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Lock Screen</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      This utility locks the screen, starting a
	      screensaver. In order to unlock the screen and continue
	      the work, you will need to enter your password. This is
	      useful when you need to leave the computer running  unattended
	      for some time. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Log Out</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      This finishes your GNOME session, stopping all running
	      applications and returning you to login screen. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="applications">
      <title>Core GNOME Applications</title>
      <para>
	Applications menu contains all GNOME applications installed on
	your system. In addition, it also shows many non-GNOME
	applications which are installed on your system. Here we list
	those GNOME applications which form part of GNOME Desktop
	environment. These applications are included in the standard
	GNOME distributions and must be available on any system
	running GNOME. 
      </para>
	
      <variablelist>	
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Accessories</guisubmenu>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> These include productivity applications
	    such as:
            </para>     
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>Calculator</application>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para> <application>Character
		  Map</application>, which allows you to select any
		  symbol in virtually any human alphabet (provided
		  that you have fonts to show these symbols). This is
		  a quick way to insert in text you are typing a
		  symbol that can not be directly entered from the
		  keyboard.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>File Roller</application>, a utility
		  for viewing, unpacking and creating compressed
		  archive files.  
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>Text Editor</application>
		  (gedit), a lightweight text editor capable of
		  handling multilanguage texts. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>Dictionary</application>, allowing you
		  to look up a word in one of the many freely available
		  dictionaries on the Internet. 
		</para></listitem>

	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>


	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Desktop Preferences</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This submenu contains preferences tools used to
	      customize your desktop; see <xref
	      linkend="customizing"/> for details. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Games</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>	
	      Lots of them &mdash; just try!
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!--########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><application>Eye of
		    GNOME</application> image viewer
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Ggv Postscript Viewer</application>,
		  which can also be used for viewing PDF files. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Programming</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem> 
	    <para><application>Bug Report tool</application>.  Use this
	    tool to make suggestions and report bugs in GNOME
	    applications.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Here you will find a <application>CD player</application>,
	    <application>Volume Control</application>, and 
	    <application>Sound Recorder</application>.
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>System Tools</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This submenu contains various tools used for managing
	      your system, such as:
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><application>System Monitor</application>. This
		  application can be used to view all processes (tasks)
		  currently running on your system and the resources
		  (memory and processor time)
		  they use. You can also use the <application>System
		    Monitor</application> to kill a stalled or otherwise
		  misbehaving application. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Configuration
		  Editor</application>. This tool is only recommended
		  for advanced users. It allows you to change
		  <emphasis>all</emphasis> settings used by GNOME
		  applications (unlike <link
		  linkend="customizing-desktop">preferences
		  tools</link> which only cover some of the
		  settings). However, it provides little assistance
		  or safeguards; it can easily make your system
		  completely unusable if you do not know what you are
		  doing.   
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Floppy Formatter</application>, a tool 
                  for formatting floppy disks.
		  </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Terminal</application>, which gives you
		  access to the most powerful (but not the most user
		  friendly) interface ever created &mdash; the command
		  line prompt.
		  </para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <para> This submenu may also contain tools for managing
	      software installed on your system, such as
	      <application>Red Carpet</application> (if you are using
	      the distribution of GNOME prepared by Ximian, Inc.).
	      <application>Red Carpet</application> provides an
	      extremely easy, almost one-click, way to update your
	      GNOME installation.  This 
	      requires that you have system administrator (root)
	      privileges.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This starts the GNOME help browser,
	      <application>Yelp</application>, described in <xref
	      linkend="Gnome-docs"/>. 
	     </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Home Folder</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This opens a new <application>Nautilus</application>
	      window showing the contents of your home folder.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>



    <sect2 id="other-applications">
      <title>Other Applications</title>
      <para>
	In addition to the core applications listed above, there is
	also a variety of GNOME applications that can be installed
	separately. Most likely, you will find many of them already
	installed on your system and shown in the
	<guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu.  Here we list the most
	important of them. A full list of software available for
	GNOME with links to individual projects' web pages and
	download locations can be found in <ulink type="http"
	url="http://www.gnome.org/softwaremap/">GNOME Software
	Map</ulink>.  
      </para>

	
      <variablelist>	
	<!-- ########## -->

	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
		  <application>Galeon</application>, a fast  web
		  browser based on Mozilla
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
		  <application>Evolution</application>, an email
		  client, calendar and contact manager. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para> <application>X-Chat</application>, an 
		  Internet Relay Chat (IRC) client.
		</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
		  <application>GNOME-ICU</application> for talking
		  with other people using ICQ protocol.
		</para></listitem> 
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>gftp</application>, a graphical
		  tool for file transfers, supporting FTP, HTTP, and
		  SSH protocols. Note that the GNOME file manager,
		  <application>Nautilus</application>, also has
		  built-in FTP capabilities.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
		  <application>The GIMP</application>, professional
		  grade image editing program.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
		  <application>gThumb</application>, a program for
		  viewing and organizing collections of images (for
		  examples, digital camera photos). 
		</para>
	      </listitem>


	    </itemizedlist>


	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para> <application>XMMS</application>, player for
		  audio CDs and aduio files in  MP3 and Ogg
		  Vorbis formats.
		</para>
 	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para> <application>Rhythmbox</application>, an audio
		  player for MP3 and Ogg Vorbis files. It also has
		  powerful capabilities for organizing large music
		  collections, creating and editing playlists,
		  searching for songs by artist, name, or other
		  parameters, and more.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para> <application>Totem</application> video player,
		  based on Xine project. It can hanlde most of video
		  formats and codecs available. It can also be used
		  for viewing Video CDs and DVDs. Viewing DVDs
		  requires special decryption software, whose legal
		  status is unclear in the US. For this reason, this
		  software is usually not installed by default but can
		  be downloaded separately if it is legal in your
		  locality.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
		  <application>Gnumeric</application>, a full-featured
		  Excel-compatible sreadsheet.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
		  <application>AbiWord</application>, a fast and light
		  word processor. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	    </itemizedlist>

	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>
 </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section:	======================== -->
<sect1 id="trouble">
    <title>Help &mdash;  I Am in Trouble!</title>
    <para>
      Everyone runs into trouble sooner or later. Here is some
      advice on how to handle the  most common problems:
    </para>
    
    <sect2 id="kill-an-app">
      <title>Killing a Stalled Application</title>
      <para>
	If an application is stalled or frozen &mdash; that is, if it
	does not respond to your mouse clicks and keyboard commands,
	you can either wait and hope that it wakes up, or kill it. If
	you decide to kill it (NOTE: You will lose all unsaved data),
	start the <application>System Monitor</application>
	(from <menuchoice> <guisubmenu>Applications</guisubmenu>
	<guisubmenu>System Tools</guisubmenu> </menuchoice>). Select
	the application you want to kill and click on <guibutton>End
	process</guibutton> button at the bottom. You can also
	right-click on the application name and choose
	<guimenuitem>End process</guimenuitem>; if it doesn't help,
	right-click and choose <guimenuitem>Kill
	process</guimenuitem>. Using the <application>GNOME System
	monitor</application> also allows you to find and kill all
	helper processes started by this application.
	</para>
      <para>
	If a GNOME application freezes or crashes (unexpectedly dies)
	repeatedly, you should file a bug report as described in the
	<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">GNOME feedback
	page</ulink>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="kill-X11">
      <title>My Whole System Froze!</title> 

      <para> If your whole system is frozen and is not responding, do not
      hurry to push the power  button on the computer
      &mdash; this is usually the worst solution. Most probably, it is
      not the operating system itself that is frozen (UNIX systems are
      known for stability), but just the graphical part, the X Window
      System. In this case, you can try to restart the X Window System by
      simultaneously pressing
     <keycombo>
    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Backspace</keycap>
   </keycombo>.   This should work for
      the implementation of the X Window system used on Linux and *BSD,
      XFree86 (unless it was disabled by your system
      administrator). Of course, in this way you also lose all unsaved
      data, but at least you do not risk harming the whole file
      system.
      </para>
    </sect2>

<!--    <sect2 id="Gnome-messedup">
      <title>My Whole GNOME Configuration Is Messed Up!</title>
      <para> 
	If you have a serious  problem with your GNOME settings &mdash;
	for example, if your panel is missing &mdash; the radical solution
	is to remove all your GNOME configuration files and start from
	scratch. This is an emergency solution, as you lose all
	configuration settings and will need to configure your menus,
`	panels, etc. again from scratch, that is, from the default GNOME
	configuration. However, this only affects your GNOME configuration,
	so your data files and settings for non-GNOME applications
	remain intact. 
      </para>
      <para> To remove all your GNOME configuration settings and return
	to the original GNOME configuration, log out then log in again
	holding down the keys <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and
	<keycap>Shift</keycap>. (Do so immediately after entering your
	password in the login dialog.)  You will be presented with a dialog,
	offering you the choice of resetting the saved session (that is,
        the applications open when you last logged out); resetting
        your GNOME configuration settings; or both.  
      </para>
    </sect2> -->
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="otherinfo">
    <title>Where to Find More Information</title>
    <sect2 id="Gnome-docs">
      <title>GNOME Help System</title>
      <para>
	GNOME includes detailed documentation for the majority
	of applications, utilities and other components, such as the panel
	or the Nautilus file manager. To view a manual for an application,
	choose the <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu in the
	application, or press <keycap>F1</keycap>. To
	view help about the  panel or panel objects, right-click on it
	and choose <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem> from the context
	menu. This will automatically launch the GNOME help browser,
	<application>Yelp</application>, showing the appropriate
	manual. 
      </para>
      <para>
	You can also start  <application>Yelp</application>  by
	choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
	  <guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu> </menuchoice>. This will show the
	top-level help system page, listing all GNOME documents
	conveniently organized by topic.
      </para>

      <para> In addition to the manuals for individual applications,
	GNOME documentation also includes:
      </para>
      <variablelist> 
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide">
	    <citetitle>GNOME Desktop 2.2 User Guide</citetitle>
	     </ulink>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> This user
	    guide provides a general overview of GNOME and detailed
	    documentation for core GNOME
	    components (such as the desktop, panel, Nautilus, and desktop
	    preferences tools).  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:intro-to-gnome">
	    <citetitle>Introduction to GNOME</citetitle>
	     </ulink>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>This is the document you are reading.  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide">
	    <citetitle>GNOME 2.2 System Administrator Guide</citetitle>
	     </ulink>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> This guide provides in-depth discussion of GNOME
	    internals. In particular, it explains where GNOME stores
	    various configuration settings (both per-user and
	    system-wide). It also contains instructions on setting
	    system-wide GNOME preferences. It is mostly intended for
	    system administrators; however, advanced users may also
	    find it useful.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
<!--	<varlistentry>
	  <term> <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:unix-primer">
	    <citetitle>If you are new to UNIX/Linux...</citetitle>
	    </ulink>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This short document gives the minimal necessary
	      information about UNIX and UNIX-like operating systems,
	      including such things as filenames, paths and
	      directories, permissions, symbolic links and most
	      confusing of them all, the notion of
	      <quote>mounting</quote>. If you have never used a UNIX system
	      before, be sure to read this.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry> -->
      </variablelist>

      <para><application>Yelp</application> can also be used for
      viewing non-GNOME documentation, such as man pages and info
	pages (see below).  
      </para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gnome-www"> 
      <title> GNOME Resources on the Internet</title>
      <para> 
	In addition to documentation shipped with GNOME, there is also
	a wealth of information available on the Internet. A good
	starting point is the <ulink type="http"
        url="http://www.gnome.org">GNOME website</ulink>. There you
        will find instructions for installing GNOME, reviews and tips,
        developer information, and more.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you can not find an answer to your question there, you may
	ask other GNOME users in one of the forums on <ulink
	type="http" url="http://gnomesupport.org/forums/">GNOME User's
	Board</ulink>. Before asking a question, please make sure
	that it  has not been answered in avaialble documents such
	as <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide">GNOME User
	Guide</ulink>.  
     </para>
      <para>
	Finally, if you use IRC (Internet Relay Chat), you can find
	other GNOME users and developers and ask questions on the 
	<systemitem>#gnome</systemitem> and
	<systemitem>#gnome-help</systemitem>  channels on
	<systemitem>irc.gnome.org</systemitem>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="not-Gnome-docs">
      <title>Everything Not GNOME</title>
      <para>
	You should realize that GNOME is just part of your computer
	system. If you want to unleash the full potential of your
	computer, you need to understand not just GNOME but also the
	underlying operating system (UNIX/Linux/FreeBSD), various
	tools and utilities included with it, and its graphics system
	(the X Window System). Each of these components usually comes with
	its own documentation. Most of UNIX commands and utilities are
        documented in so-called <quote>manual pages</quote>, or man pages
        for short. You can view them using the
	<application>Yelp</application> help browser
        (see <xref linkend="Gnome-docs"/>). This documentation is usually
        very detailed and more technical than most users would like.
        Another documentation format used by utilities from the
	GNU project is called <quote>info pages</quote>. They, too,
	can be viewed using <application>Yelp</application>. Many
	applications also have documentation in other formats. Sometimes
        it is not easy to find documentation for a given application &mdash;
        try looking in the directories  <filename>/usr/share/doc</filename>
	and <filename>/usr/doc</filename>.
      </para>
      <para> Documentation for the operating system itself varies from one
        system to another. The best advice is to check the printed manual
        which came with your system. For Linux, a good source of information
        is the Linux Documentation Project (LDP); you can read  their
        documentation on the Internet at <ulink type="http"
	url="http://www.tldp.org">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>.
	Virtually all Linux distributions also include copies of LDP
	documents; usually they are found at
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/LDP</filename> or
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/HOWTO</filename>.
      </para>
      <para> 
	And of course, there are a number of books available about all
	flavors of UNIX/Linux, GNOME, and about anything else you might
        be interested in. Check your local bookstore. 
      </para> 
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="feedback">
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>
	If you have found a bug in one of the GNOME applications, or have
	some comments or suggestions regarding GNOME applications or
	documentation, please let us know! Instructions for submitting
	bug reports and comments are given in the <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>







