<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.0">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "2.0">
  <!ENTITY date "June 2002">
  <!-- Information about the entities
       The legal.xml file contains legal information, there is no need to edit the file. 
       Use the appversion entity to specify the version of the application.
       Use the manrevision entity to specify the revision number of this manual.
       Use the date entity to specify the release date of this manual.
       Use the app entity to specify the name of the application. -->
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo> 
  <title>Introduction to GNOME V&manrevision;</title>
    <copyright> 
      <year>2001</year> 
      <year>2002</year> 
      <holder>Alexander Kirillov</holder> 
    </copyright>
    <copyright> 
      <year>2000</year> 
      <year>2001</year> 
      <holder>Red Hat, Inc.</holder> 
    </copyright>
    <copyright> 
      <year>2000</year> 
      <year>2001</year> 
      <holder>David A. Wheeler</holder> 
    </copyright>
    <publisher> 
      <publishername> GNOME Documentation Project </publishername> 
    </publisher> 

   &legal;

 <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>Alexander</firstname>
    <surname>Kirillov</surname>		
	<affiliation> 
	  <orgname>GNOME Documentation Project</orgname> 
	  <address> <email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>David</firstname>
    <surname>Mason</surname>		
	<affiliation> 
	  <orgname>Red Hat, Inc.</orgname> 
	  <address> <email>dcm@redhat.com</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>David</firstname>
	<surname>Wheeler</surname>		
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>Introduction to GNOME V&manrevision;</revnumber> 
	<date>&date;</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">
               Alexander Kirillov
	    	<email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email>,
	    David C. Mason,  David A. Wheeler
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	  <para>Updated for GNOME 2.0. Some descriptions and
	  screenshots are borrowed from <citetitle>GNOME Desktop 2.0
	  User Guide</citetitle> (May 2002), by Sun GNOME
	  Documentation Team <email>gdocteam@sun.com></email>,
	  published by GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>Introduction to GNOME</revnumber> 
	<date>April 2001</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">Alexander Kirillov
	    <email>kirillov@math.sunysb.edu</email>, 
            David C. Mason,  David A. Wheeler
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	  <para>This version described GNOME 1.4</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
    </revhistory> 



  <releaseinfo>
      This document was  last updated in June 2002. It describes GNOME
      2.0.   
    </releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice> <title>Feedback</title> <para> To report a bug or
      make a suggestion regarding this document, follow the directions
      in the <ulink url="ghelp:gnome-feedback" type="help">GNOME
      Feedback Page</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice> 

  </articleinfo>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="whatisGnome">
    <title>What Is GNOME?</title>
    <para>    
      GNOME is a user-friendly graphical desktop environment for UNIX and
      UNIX-like systems.  GNOME includes a panel (for starting
      applications and displaying status), a desktop (where data and
      applications can be placed), a set of standard desktop tools and
      applications, and a set of conventions that make it easy for
      applications to cooperate and be consistent with each other.
      Users of other operating systems or environments should feel
      right at home using the powerful graphics-driven environment
      GNOME provides. GNOME runs on a number of UNIX-like operating
      systems, including Linux, FreeBSD, and Solaris. 
    </para>
   <para> GNOME is completely open source (free software) developed by
      hundreds of programmers around the world. Both the source code
      and ready-to-run binaries of GNOME are available for download on
      the Internet; they are distributed under the terms of <ulink
      type="help" url="ghelp:gpl"> GNU General Public
      License</ulink> (and its cousins, <ulink type="help"
      url="ghelp:lgpl">Lesser General Public License</ulink> and
      <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl">Free Documentation
      License</ulink> for libraries and documentation
      respectively). In particular, this means that everyone is free
      to use, copy or distribute GNOME. If you would like to learn
      more about the GNOME project please visit the <ulink
      url="http://www.gnome.org" type="http">GNOME website</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
      GNOME is highly configurable, enabling you to set your desktop
      the way you want it to look and feel.  GNOME supports many human
      languages, and more are added every month.  GNOME even supports
      several drag and drop protocols for maximum interoperability
      with non-GNOME applications.
   </para>

   <para>
    GNOME comes from the acronym for the GNU Network Object Model
    Environment (GNOME).  GNOME is a part of the larger GNU project,
    started in 1984 to develop a completely free UNIX-like operating
    system.  For more information, visit the <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org" type="http">GNU website</ulink>.  
    </para>
    <para>
      This guide describes GNOME 2.0 which the latest (as of June 
      2002) release of GNOME. 
    </para>
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="about">
    <title>Purpose of This Document</title>
    <para>
      This document gives you a short introduction to GNOME. It is not
      intended to cover all details of GNOME; if you need more
      information, you should read detailed manuals listed in <xref
      linkend="otherinfo"/>. Also, this document assumes you already have
      GNOME installed; if you need help installing GNOME, please check
      the instructions on <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org"
      type="http">GNOME website</ulink>.
    </para>
 
    <para> This document was written by the members of GNOME
      Documentation Project (GDP). If you have any comments or
      suggestions about this document or if you can offer any other
      help in improving or translating GNOME documentation, please
      send an e-mail to <email>docs@gnome.org</email>, or visit <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp/" type="http">GDP
      website</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para> The authors of this document assume that you are
      using the default configuration of GNOME (that is, default GTK
      theme and <application>Sawfish</application> window manager with
      <guilabel>Crux</guilabel> theme). GNOME is highly
      configurable, so it is easy to change not only the look but also
      the behavior of GNOME; however, we recommend that you do so only
      after you already have some experience with GNOME.
    </para>
  </sect1>
<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="conventions">
    <title>Mouse Conventions Used in This Document</title> 
    <para>
      Before  describing GNOME, let us introduce some terms used not 
      only in this guide but in all GNOME documents. Most importantly,
      we need to clarify the use of mouse buttons and clicks. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Most GNOME documents assume that you are using a standard (for
      UNIX) 3-button mouse and talk about left, right, and middle
      mouse buttons; if a document says <quote>click</quote> without
      explicitly specifying the button, the left button is
      assumed. <!-- Some documents use notations <quote>mouse button
      1</quote>, <quote>mouse button 2</quote> and <quote>mouse button
      3</quote> (or MB1, MB2, MB3 for short) for left, middle, and
      right buttons respectively. -->
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are using a two-button mouse, you can emulate the middle
      mouse button by pressing left and right buttons simultaneously;
      if you have a wheel mouse, the wheel can be used in place of the
      middle mouse button.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can switch the roles of the buttons using <application>Mouse
      preference tool</application> in <guisubmenu>Desktop
      Preferences</guisubmenu> submenu of
      <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu. Many left-handers
      choose to reverse the right and left buttons. If you have done
      so, you need to use the right mouse button whenever document
      instructs you to click, and use <emphasis>left</emphasis> mouse
      button whenever a document talks about
      <quote>right-clicking</quote> or mouse button 3.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you use a mouse with some unusual placement of buttons, a
      trackball, or some other input device, you need to find out
      which buttons correspond to <quote>right</quote>,
      <quote>left</quote> and <quote>middle</quote>; this information
      can usually be found in the manual which came with your
      device. Usually, <quote>left</quote> button (MB1) is the one
      under your index finger. 
    </para>

  </sect1>


<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="firstglance">
    <title>First Glance at GNOME: Desktop and Panel</title> 
    <para>
      <xref linkend="desktop-fig"/> shows an example of GNOME
      running. GNOME is very configurable, so your screen may look
      quite different.
    </para>
<!-- figure -->
    <figure id="desktop-fig">
     <title>Sample GNOME Display.</title>
     <screenshot>	  
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject><imagedata
		fileref="figures/typical_anno_desktop.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject> 
	    <phrase>Figure of GNOME desktop, with menu panel, usual
	    panel, Nautilus window, and standard desktop icons: home
	    folder, Start here and Trash </phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
   </figure>
<!-- /figure --> 
<!-- =======Subsection ============ -->
<sect2 id="panel">
      <title>Panel</title>
      <para>
	The two long bars at the top and bottom of <xref
	linkend="desktop-fig"/> are <emphasis>panels</emphasis>. The
	top one is called the menu panel, the bottom one is an edge
	panel (you can have more than one  edge panel). 
	  Panels can contain a number of useful objects, such as 
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guibutton>GNOME Menu</guibutton> button</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>This is the button with the stylized footprint (in
	      the example of <xref linkend="desktop-fig"/>, it is the
	      left-most button on the top panel). Clicking this button
	      brings up a menu containing all GNOME applications and
	      commands, including the logout command.
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Other menus</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Panels can also contain other menus, either submenus of
	    the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu> or menus created by
	    user. In the example above, the top panel contains
	    <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and
	    <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menus. Both of them are
	    actually submenus of the  <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>.
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Application launchers</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>These are buttons that start various programs.
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <!-- ############## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Panel applets</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>These are are tiny programs designed to
	      work inside the panel. For example, the
	      <application>clock</application> applet on the far right
	      of the top panel    shows the current time, and
	      <application>Window List</application> applet (in the
	      left side of the bottom panel) shows the list of all application
	      windows  on your desktop (this will be discussed in
	      detail in <xref linkend="tasklist"/>). 
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      


      <para> As with all GNOME components, panels are highly
	configurable: you can add or remove application launchers and
	applets, edit the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>, change panel
	background, or even remove and create new panels. This will be
	discussed in <xref linkend="customizing-panel"/>. 
      </para>
      <note>
	<title>NOTE</title>
	<para>
	  The top panel in <xref linkend="desktop-fig"/> is called
	  <emphasis>menu</emphasis> panel and is slightly different
	  properties than other panels. For example, you can not move
	  it to a different location.
	 </para>
	</note>
      <para>
	To configure an object, get help on it, or remove it
	from the panel, right-click on it and select the appropriate
	item from the popup menu. To hide the panel when you are not
	using it, click on one of the <guibutton>Hide
	buttons</guibutton> (with small arrows) at the ends of the
	panel.
      </para>
      <para>More panel operations are available from the
	<guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu, which you can open by
	right-clicking in any vacant space on the panel (for example,
	in the hide arrows) and selecting
	<guisubmenu>Panel</guisubmenu> from the menu. The
	<guimenu>Panel</guimenu> menu also contains <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:panel">Panel manual</ulink>, which describes
	all these options in detail.  </para>
    </sect2>
<!-- =======Subsection ============ -->
    <sect2 id="desktop"> 
      <title>Desktop</title> 
      <para>
	Everything outside the panel is called
	<quote>desktop</quote>. You can place icons for files, applications,
        and other items on the desktop (a default collection of icons is
        installed with GNOME), after which you can double-click on an item
        to use it:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>   
	    If the item is a program, that program will start.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If it is a data file, the appropriate program will start
	    up with that data loaded.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>  

	  <para>
	    If it is a folder (directory), <application>File
	    Manager</application> will start and show the contents of
	    that directory. Your desktop will probably have a icon
	    showing a house and labeled
	    <guilabel><replaceable>yourname</replaceable>'s
	    Home</guilabel>. Double-clicking on this icon will start
	    the <application>File Manager</application> at your home
	    directory.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The easiest way to place an item on the desktop is to drag a
	file from the, as described in detail in <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:nautilus">Nautilus manual</ulink>. Once the item is
	placed on the desktop, you can move it around the desktop
	using the left mouse button, or you can click on it with the
	right mouse button to bring up the popup menu which allows you
	to delete the item or change its properties.
    </para>
    </sect2>

<!-- =======Subsection ============ -->
    <sect2 id="mouse"> 
      <title>Using the Mouse</title> 
      <para>    
	As you have already seen, you can do almost anything just by
	clicking with your mouse. Here are some conventions which work
	almost anywhere in GNOME:
      </para> 

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"> 
	<listitem><para> 
	    Clicking on  an item with the left mouse button selects
	    (hilights) it. If you need to select several objects, hold down
	    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while clicking. 
	  </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para> 
	    Double-clicking on an item runs the default action for
	    this item (running an application, opening the file, etc.) 
	  </para></listitem> 
	<listitem><para> 
	    Clicking on an item with the right mouse button brings up
	    the context menu, which contains all the commands and
	    information available for this item. If you have selected
	    a group of items, right-clicking on any of them will bring
	    up the context menu which applies to all of these items.
	  </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    You can
	    select text anywhere on the screen using the left mouse
	    button, and then insert this text into any other place on
	    the screen which accepts text input, by clicking with the
	    <link linkend="conventions">middle mouse button</link>.
	  </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	In addition, right-clicking on any vacant
	place on your desktop brings up the <guimenu>Desktop
	Background</guimenu> menu, which allows you to change desktop
	background or other properties, or add a new object to the
	desktop. Clicking on the desktop with the middle mouse button
	produces the <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu, provided by the
	window manager (see <xref linkend="windows"/>).  </para>
    </sect2>

<!-- =======Subsection:Logging out ============ -->
    <sect2 id="logout"> 
      <title>Logging Out</title> 
      
      <para> To log out of GNOME, click on the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>
	button and select <guimenuitem>Log out</guimenuitem>. GNOME
	will prompt you for confirmation; it will also give you an
	option to save the session &mdash; that is, information about
	currently open applications and their location on the screen
	will be saved, so that when you login next time, the same
	applications will be in the same places (this only works for
	applications which are fully GNOME-compliant).
      </para>
    </sect2>
	
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: working with windows =============== -->
<sect1 id="windows">
    <title>Working With Windows</title>
    <para>
      The graphical system used by all UNIX-like operating systems, X
      Window System, allows you to have several windows on your
      screen, with a different application running in each window. By
      itself, however, X Window System can only do very low-level
      operations, so it is always used in combination with another
      piece of software, called <emphasis>window manager</emphasis>. A
      window manager provides windows' frames, titlebar, and buttons,
      allows you to move, close, and resize windows, etc. GNOME can
      work with many window managers. The most popular are <ulink
      type="http" url="http://sawmill.sourceforge.net">
      <application>Sawfish</application></ulink> (included as part of
      GNOME distribution) and <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnome.org/softwaremap/projects/Metacity">
      <application>Metacity</application></ulink>. Each window manager
      can use many different styles of window decorations and buttons
      (this is referred to as <quote>window manager
      theme</quote>). Since it is impossible to cover them all, in
      this section we only describe the default window manager shipped
      with GNOME, <application>Sawfish</application>, and its default
      theme, <guilabel>Crux</guilabel>. An example of the window
      titlebar using <guilabel>Crux</guilabel> theme is shown in <xref
      linkend="cruxborder"/>
    </para>

<!-- figure -->
    <figure id="cruxborder">
     <title>Window Titlebar Using  Crux Theme.</title>
     <screenshot>
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject><imagedata
		fileref="figures/titlebar_anno_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject> 
	    <phrase>Titlebar in Crux style, focused. Close button in
	    the left side, minimize, maximize, and shade buttons on
	    the right. </phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>

    </screenshot>
   </figure>
<!-- /figure --> 
    <para>
      So, what can you do with windows?
    </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	  Closing, Minimizing, and Maximizing Windows
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> To <emphasis>close</emphasis> a window, click on
	      the <guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> button (with the
	      small <quote>x</quote>) in the window titlebar. If the
	      application has any unsaved data, it will prompt you to
	      save it.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      To <emphasis>maximize</emphasis> a window, i.e. make it
	      fill the entire screen (except for the part taken by the
	      panels), click on the <guibutton>Maximize</guibutton>
	      button (middle button on the right side). Clicking on
	      this button once again will restore the window to its
	      original size.
	    </para>
	    <para> To <emphasis>minimize</emphasis> (sometimes also
	      called hide or iconify) a window, click on the
	      <guibutton>Minimize</guibutton> button. The window will
	      disappear from screen. However, it is not lost: the
	      application in this window continues running, no data is
	      lost &mdash; it is just temporarily hidden. All
	      minimized windows are shown in the <link
	      linkend="tasklist"><application>Window List</application>
	      applet</link> and can be restored as described below.
	    </para>
	    <para> A convenient alternative to minimizing windows is
	      <emphasis>shading</emphasis> them. When you shade a window, it
	      <quote>rolls up</quote> into its own titlebar, so the
	      titlebar is the only part of the window left on
	      screen. To shade a window, click on
	      <guibutton>Shade</guibutton> button; to unshade, click
	      on this button again. You can also shade and unshade
	      window by  double-clicking on the titlebar.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	     Raising and Lowering Windows
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Windows on your screen can overlap, so that one of
	      the windows is <quote>on top</quote> of another. You can
	      <quote>raise</quote> a window (i.e., put it on top of
	      all others) by clicking on the window titlebar. You can
	      also switch a window from raised to lowered and back by
	      right-clicking in the titlebar, or by right-clicking
	      anywhere inside the window while holding down
	      <keycap>Alt</keycap> key.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	     Focus
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> Of all the windows on your screen, only one is active
              (in computer parlance, <quote>focused</quote>), which means
              that anything you type on the keyboard will be sent to the
              application running in that window. (It does not mean that the
	      applications in other windows are idle &mdash; they can
	      be running as well.) To help you see which window has
	      focus, the titlebar of this window has different color
	      (left side is blue, as opposed to gray for all other
	      windows). To change focus to another window, just click
	      anywhere in that window. You can also click in the
	      window titlebar to focus and raise the window
	      simultaneously.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You can also use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
	    <keycap>Tab</keycap> </keycombo> shortcut to switch
	    between windows. This cyclically switches all existing
	    windows. The window to which you switch is raised and
	    given focus.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	     Moving and Resizing Windows
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> To move a window, drag its titlebar to a new
	      location using left mouse button (i.e., click in the
	      title bar and move the mouse without releasing the
	      button). You can also move a window by clicking anywhere
	      inside the window while holding down the
	      <keycap>Alt</keycap> key.
	    </para>
	    <para> 
	      To resize a window, place the mouse cursor on any of the
	      window borders  or corners. The
	      mouse cursor will change to an arrow pushing a line or
	      corner, allowing you to drag the border or corner to a new
	      position. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <sect2 id="tasklist">
      <title>Window List Applet</title>
      <para>
	All the windows on your desktop (including the minimized ones)
	are shown in the <application>Window List</application>
	applet, located on your panel. For each window, a mini-icon
	and beginning of the window title is shown. To restore a
	minimized window, just click on its title in the
	<application>Window List</application>
	applet. Right-clicking on the window title brings up the
	popup menu which allows you to shade a
	window, close it, etc. <!-- NEEDS WORK 
        or kill the application running in the
	window. The last option should only be used when an
	application is frozen and does not respond to <quote>close
	window</quote> command. If you kill an application, you lose
	all unsaved data! -->
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="wm-menus">
      <title>Window  Menu</title>
      <para>
	<application>Sawfish</application> also provides a menu for
	each window; this menu contains all the operations for this
	window described above, and then some. To access this menu,
	right-click on the <guibutton>Close</guibutton> button, or
	click anywhere inside the window with  the <link
	linkend="conventions">middle mouse button</link> while holding
	down the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="wm-desktop-menu">
      <title>Root Menu</title>
      <para>
        Finally, <application>Sawfish</application> also provides
	so-called <guimenu>Root</guimenu> menu. It can be accessed by
	clicking on any empty space of the desktop with the <link
	linkend="conventions">middle mouse button</link>. It contains
	the following items:
      </para>
      <variablelist> 
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Provides list of all windows, including minimized
	      ones. Selecting one of these windows restores it (if it
	      was minimized) and raises it over other windows. Very
	      convenient if you have so many windows that the one you
	      need is completely covered by others.  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Workspaces</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Allows you to switch from one workspace to another,
	    create and delete workspaces. See <citetitle>GNOME Desktop
	    User Guide</citetitle>  for details. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem> 
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Programs</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Same as <guisubmenu>Applications</guisubmenu> section 
	      of the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>.   
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Customize</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Allows the user to customize
	      <application>Sawfish</application> (see <xref
	      linkend="customizing-wm"/> for details).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Provides links to <application>Sawfish</application>
	      website, <application>Sawfish</application> manual
	      (beware: this is not a user's manual but rather a manual
	      for people who write extensions/customizations to
	      <application>Sawfish</application> using LISP
	      programming language), link to <citetitle>GNOME Users
	      Guide</citetitle>, and to <ulink type="http"
	      url="http://www.gnome.org">GNOME website</ulink>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
	      
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="nautilus">
    <title>Nautilus: GNOME File Manager</title>
    <para>
      GNOME includes a <quote>graphical shell</quote>,
      <application>Nautilus</application>. It combines file manager,
      web browser, FTP client, and much more. It also provides access
      to tools for customizing GNOME (thus replacing
      <application>GNOME Control Center</application> which was
      included in GNOME 1.4 and earlier releases).
    </para>

    <para>To open a new <application>Nautilus</application> window,
      choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Home folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the
      <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>, or double-click on any folder
      icon on your desktop, such as <guiicon>Home</guiicon> icon.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="nautilus-fm">
      <title>Managing Your Files With Nautilus</title>
<!-- figure -->
    <figure id="figure-nautilus">
     <title>Nautilus Window</title>
     <screenshot>
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject><imagedata
		fileref="figures/naut_iconview_window.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject> 
	    <phrase>Nautilus Window, in icon mode</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>

    </screenshot>
   </figure>
<!-- /figure --> 

      <para>
	As most modern graphic file managers,
        <application>Nautilus</application> shows the contents of a
        selected folder using icons to represent files and
        subfolders. Double-clicking on any file or folder opens it
        (for data files, it starts the appropriate application which
        opens this file, as configured in <application>File Types and
        Programs </application> preference tool). Right-clicking on a
        file or folder produces a popup menu.  Using this menu, you
        can delete or rename the file, view and change file properties
        or permissions, and more.
      </para>

      <para> <application>Nautilus</application> also provides an easy
	way to move and copy files between folders. To move a file
	from one folder to another, open these folders in separate
	<application>Nautilus</application> windows (you can use
	<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>New
	window</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command).  Select the file
	you want to move, and drag it from one window into another
	using the mouse. You can also drag a file or folder to the
	desktop. To copy file, press-and-hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
	while dragging the file.
      </para>
      <para>
	To delete files, drag them to the trash can icon on your
	desktop. 
      </para>
      <para> <application>Nautilus</application> provides many more
	tools to manipulate your files. It is also highly
	customizable, so you can easily change the way files are
	displayed (for example, you can choose a custom icon for a
	given file). For detailed description of all these
	possibilities, read <citetitle>Nautilus manual</citetitle>,
	available from <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu of
	<application>Nautilus</application>. 
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="nautilus-floppies">
      <title>
	Accessing Floppies and Other Removable Media</title>
      <para>
	To access files on floppy disks, CD-ROMs and other removable
	media, right-click on any vacant spot on the desktop and
	choose the required media from the
	<guisubmenu>Disks</guisubmenu> submenu of the 
	<guimenu>Desktop Background</guimenu> menu (assuming that your
	system is correctly configured, that is, you have the
	appropriate entry in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>
	file). This will open a <application>Nautilus</application>
	window showing the contents of the selected media. 
      </para>
      <warning>
	<title>WARNING</title> 
	<para>
	  Before removing a floppy disk or other removable media
	  from the drive, you must
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		   Close all windows  accessing files on this
		disk, including <application>Nautilus</application>
		windows, terminal windows, and others
	      </para>
	  </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Unmount the disk by right-clicking on the disk icon on
		the desktop and choosing <guimenuitem>Unmount
		volume</guimenuitem> from the popup menu. 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	  If you remove the disk without unmounting it first, you may
	  lose data!
	</para>
      </warning>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="nautilus-cool">
      <title>Other Features of Nautilus</title>
      <para>
	In addition to the basic features listed above,
	<application>Nautilus</application> has many other advanced
	and exciting capabilities. Here we list some of them,
	referring the reader to <citetitle>>Nautilus
	manual</citetitle> for detailed descriptions.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><application>Nautilus</application> can be customized
	    in many ways. In particular, you can change background and
	    icons used for files and folders and  font used for captions.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>You can assign custom icon to a specific file, or
	    rescale the icon for a specific file, so that the most
	    important files really stand out. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>You can assign an <quote>emblem</quote> (such as
	    <guilabel>New</guilabel> or <guilabel>Favorite</guilabel>)
	    to a file, which will be put on top of the file icon.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Files can be sorted by name, type, modification date,
	    or the emblem you assigned to them. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><application>Nautilus</application> can also be used
	    as Web browser (with limited capabilities) and FTP client:
	    just enter the URL (for example,
	    <systemitem>ftp://ftp.gnome.org</systemitem>) in the
	    <guilabel>Go To</guilabel> field.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <application>Nautilus</application> can also be used
	    as a music player: just open a folder containing music files
	    in MP3 format, and  <application>Nautilus</application>
	    switches to music player  mode. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="customizing">
    <title>Customizing GNOME</title>
    <para>
      GNOME is highly configurable &mdash; you can change almost
      anything: background color, key bindings, location of panels and
      contents of the <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>, and more. To see
      examples of different customizations of GNOME desktop, take a
      look at the screenshots on <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.0/screenshots/index.html">GNOME
      website</ulink> and notice how different they look.
    </para>
    <para>The following sections list
      some of the most common customizations.  In addition, you can
      change properties of various items &mdash; most notably, panels
      and icons on your desktop &mdash; by clicking on them with the
      right mouse button and selecting
      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> from the popup menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      Almost every GNOME application has its own preferences settings
      (look for <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> in the menus), so you can change,
      for example, colors used by the <application>GNOME
      Terminal</application> or make it transparent &mdash; the
      possibilities are unlimited!
    </para>
    <sect2 id="customizing-desktop">
      <title>Desktop Preferences</title>
      <para>
	To customize the appearance of your desktop and user
	interface, use special <emphasis>desktop preference
	tools</emphasis>, which can be found in <guisubmenu>Desktop
	Preferences</guisubmenu> submenu of <guimenu>Applications
	</guimenu> menu. You can also access the preferences tools by
	double-clicking on <guiicon>Start Here</guiicon> icon on your
	desktop. This will open a <application>Nautilus</application>
	window. Double-click on <guiicon>Preferences</guiicon> and
	then on the tool you require.
    </para>
    <para>
      Here we would like to give  an overview of the most commonly
      used preferences tools.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Background</term>
	<listitem> 
	<para>
	    This tool allows you to change desktop background. You can
	    select solid color, gradient (visual effect where one
	    color blends gradually into another color), or an image
	    file.  
	</para>
	  <tip>
	    <title>TIP</title>
	    <para>
	      You can also change desktop background color by
	      right-clicking on desktop background and choosing
	      <guimenuitem>Change Desktop Background</guimenuitem>, or
	      by dragging a color from another window or dialog to
	      desktop background. 
	    </para>
	  </tip> 
      </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	  <term><guilabel>Theme</guilabel>
	  </term>
	  <listitem> 
	    <para>
	      This tool allows you to change the desktop theme (to be
	      precise, GTK2 theme). A <emphasis>theme</emphasis> is a
	      collection of settings that determine the look of all menus,
	      panels, toolbars, scrollbars, checkbuttons and other elements
	      of graphical user interface for all GNOME applications. 
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      You can select one of the themes installed as part of your
	      GNOME distribution, or download and install more themes
	      from the Internet. In particular, you can find many GTK
	      themes at <ulink type="http"
		url="http://sunshineinabag.co.uk/">Sunshine In a
		Bag</ulink> website (look for GTK2 themes).
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Please note that GTK2 theme will not change the appearance
	      of window decorations  (borders, titlebars, and buttons in
	      window titlebar); this is determined by your window
	      manager settings and can be changed as described in <xref
		linkend="customizing-wm"/>. Also, GTK 2 theme only
	      controls GNOME 2 applications. If you are using GNOME 1.x
	      applications in GNOME 2, their appearance will not be
	      affected (it is determined by GTK1 theme which is
	      configured independently from GTK 2 themes).
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term><guilabel>Font</guilabel>
	  </term>
	  <listitem> 
	  <para>
	      This tool allows you to choose the default font which will
	      be used by all menus, dialogs, and other user interface
	      elements. This overrides the font specified by your
	      desktop theme.   
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
<!--	<varlistentry>
	<term><guilabel>Session</guilabel></term>
	  <listitem> 
	    <para>NEEDS WORK
	      In this section you can define
	      the startup programs (that is, programs that are run every
	      time you log in), enable or disable login hints and logout
	      confirmation dialog. 
	</para>
      </listitem>
      </varlistentry> -->
    </variablelist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="customizing-wm">
      <title>Customizing Window Manager</title>
      <para>
	To customize <application>Sawfish</application> window
	manager, middle-click on the desktop and choose
	<guimenuitem>Customize</guimenuitem> submenu. This submenu
	contains a number of customization tools. The same tools can
	also be accessed using <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Applications</guimenu> 
	  <guisubmenu>Desktop Preferences</guisubmenu> 
	  <guisubmenu>Advanced</guisubmenu>
	  <guisubmenu>Sawfish</guisubmenu>
	</menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Most popular customization tool is
	<guilabel>Appearance</guilabel>, which allows you to select
	the window manager theme (which determines the appearance of
	window frame, titlebar, and buttons) and font to use in window
	titlebar. Other tools (such as <guilabel>Bindings</guilabel>
	tool which allows you to specify keybindings for various
	window operations) are only recommended for advanced users.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="customizing-panel">
      <title>Customizing Panels</title>
      <para>
	You can customize GNOME panels as follows:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To remove a panel, right-click on a vacant space on the
	      panel and choose <guimenuitem>Remove this
	      panel</guimenuitem> from the panel popup menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To create a new panel, right-click on a vacant space on
	      any existing panel and choose <guimenuitem>Create 
	      panel</guimenuitem> from the panel popup menu.
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To move an existing panel to a new location, drag it
	      with the middle mouse button. 
	    </para>
	    <note>
	      <title>NOTE</title>
	      <para>The menu panel can not be  moved.</para>
	    </note>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To modify panel properties (background, size,
	      auto-hide),  right-click on a vacant space on the
	      panel and choose <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>
	      from the panel popup menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To remove an object (menu, applet, application launcher)
	      from the panel, right-click on the object and choose
	      <guimenuitem>Remove from panel</guimenuitem> from the
	      object popup menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To add a new object to the panel, right-click on a
	      vacant space on the panel and choose
	      <guimenuitem>Add to panel</guimenuitem> 
	      from the panel popup menu. Alternatively, to add an
	      application from one of the menus as a launcher to the
	      panel,  right-click on the menu
	      item and choose <guimenuitem>Add this launcher to
	      panel</guimenuitem> from the popup menu.  
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To move a panel object, drag it with the middle mouse
	      button. You can even drag an object from one panel to
	      another. 
	    </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>
	      To configure a panel object, right-click on it and choose
	      <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> from the popup
	      menu. 
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="apps">
    <title>GNOME Applications and Utilities</title>
    <para>
      GNOME comes with many applications and utilities; in addition,
      GNOME allows you to use any third party applications such as
      <application>Netscape</application>), KDE applications, or other
      applications and utilities installed on your system. You can
      also use  GNOME 1.x applications under GNOME 2 (if you have
      installed appropriate GNOME 1.x libraries).
    </para>

    <para>
      Below is a partial list of some of the most useful tools and
      applications which you can find in <guimenu>GNOME
      Menu</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <title>NOTE</title>
      <para>
	The contents of <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu> depends on the
	applications installed on your system. In addition, if you are
	using a copy of GNOME packaged by someone other than GNOME
	project (for example, packaged as part of your a Linux
	distribution), the menu is likely to be slightly different
	from the one described here. For example, distributors can add
	some distribution-specific applications to the menu, or even
	completely reorganize the menus. In this case refer to
	documentation which came with your distribution. 
      </para>
    </note>

  
  <sect2 id="actions">
      <title>Actions Menu</title>
      <para>
	This submenu contains the following utilities. 
      </para>
      
      
      <variablelist>	
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Run Program</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      This allows you to manually enter a command to run,
	      saving you from starting full-blown terminal emulator.  
	    </para>
	    <tip>
	      <title>TIP</title>
	      <para>
		You can also start <application>Run
		Program</application> dialog by using <keycombo>
		<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>
		shortcut.
	      </para>
	    </tip>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Search for Files</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>This utility allows you to search for files and
	    folders on your system.  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guimenuitem>Take Screenshot</guimenuitem>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      Takes a screenshot of your desktop and saves it in a
	      file. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="applications">
      <title>Applications Menu</title>

	
      <variablelist>	
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Accessories</guisubmenu>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> These include office and productivity applications
	    such as </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>Gnumeric</application>,
		  a full-featured Excel-compatible spreadsheet
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>AbiWord</application>, a lightweight
		  word processing application.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>GNOME Calculator</application>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para> Several text editors, from simple and
		  easy to use <application>Gnome editor</application>
		  (gedit) to the (arguably) the most powerful text
		  editor ever created, <application>Emacs</application>
		  (which is not a GNOME application)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>Dictionary</application>, allowing you
		  to look up a word in one of freely available
		  dictionaries on the Internet. 
		</para></listitem>

	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>


	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Desktop Preferences</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This submenu contains preferences tools used to
	      customize your desktop; see <xref
	      linkend="customizing"/> for details. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Games</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>	
	      Lots of them &mdash; just try!
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!--########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para> 
		  <application>Gimp</application> &mdash;
		  image editing program for power users; rivals
		  <application>Photoshop</application>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Image viewers such as <application>Eye of
		    GNOME</application>, <application>GQview</application> and
		  <application>gThumb</application>   
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>GNOME Postscript Viewer</application>,
		  which can also be used for viewing PDF files. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Here you will find <application>Galeon</application> web
	      browser. If you haven't used it before, give it a try
	      &mdash; you will never want to go back to
	      <application>Netscape</application>. 
	    </para>
	    <para>Depending on the
	      software installed on your system, you are also likely to find
	      here
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>		
                 <application>Netscape</application> web
	      browser
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem><para> <application>X-Chat</application>, an 
		  Internet Relay Chat (IRC) client 
		</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>
		  <application>GNOME-ICU</application> for talking
		  with other people using ICQ protocol
		</para></listitem> 
	      <listitem><para>
		  <application>gftp</application>, a graphical
		  tool for file transfers, supporting FTP, HTTP, and
		  SSH protocols. Note that GNOME file manager,
		  <application>Nautilus</application>, also has
		  built-in FTP capabilities.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Programming</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem> 
	    <para><application>Bug report tool</application>.  Use this
	    tool to make suggestions and report bugs in GNOME
	    applications.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Here you will find <application>CD player</application>,
	    <application>Volume Control</application>, and an MP3
	    player <application>XMMS</application>.
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>System Tools</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This submenu contains various tools used for managing
	      your system, such as 
	    </para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para><application>System Monitor</application>. This
		  application can be used to view all processes (tasks)
		  currently running on your system and the resources
		  (memory and processor time)
		  they use. You can also use <application>System
		    Monitor</application> to kill a frozen or otherwise
		  misbehaving application. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Configuration
		  Editor</application>. This tool is only recommended
		  for advanced users. It allows you to change
		  <emphasis>all</emphasis> settings used by GNOME
		  applications (unlike <link
		  linkend="customizing-desktop">preferences
		  tools</link> which only cover some of the
		  settings). However, it provides little assistance
		  or safeguards, so it is easy to make your system
		  completely unusable if you do not know what you are
		  doing.   
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Archive Generator</application>, tool
		  for creating archive files. 
		  </para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <application>Floppy Formatter</application>
		  </para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

	  <para> This submenu also contains tools for managing
	      software installed on your system, namely
	      <application>GnoRPM</application> and <application>Red
	      Carpet</application> (if you are using the distribution
	      of GNOME prepared by Ximian, Inc.).
	      <application>GnoRPM</application> allows you to view all
	      software packages installed on your system (if you are
	      using a distribution of Linux based on RPM packages,
	      such as Red Hat, SuSe, or Mandrake); it also allows you
	      to remove, update, or install new packages.
	      <application>Red Carpet</application> provides an
	      extremely easy, almost one-click, way to update your
	      GNOME installation.  Both of these utilities, however,
	      require that you have system administrator (root)
	      privileges.
	    </para>

	    <para>
	      And finally, the same submenu also contains various
	      terminal emulators (<application>xterm</application>,
	      <application>Color xterm</application>, 
	      <application>GNOME Terminal</application>) letting you use
	      the most powerful (although not most user friendly) interface
	      ever created &mdash; the command line prompt. 
	    </para>

	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This starts GNOME help browser,
	      <application>Yelp</application>, described in <xref
	      linkend="Gnome-docs"/>. 
	     </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- ########## -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guisubmenu>Home Folder</guisubmenu></term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This opens a new <application>Nautilus</application>
	      window showing the contents of your home folder.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="trouble">
    <title>Help &mdash;  I Am in Trouble!</title>
    <para>
      Everyone runs into trouble sooner or later. Here is some
      advice on how to handle the  most common problems:
    </para>
    
    <sect2 id="kill-an-app">
      <title>Killing a Stalled Application</title>
      <para>
	If an application is stalled or frozen &mdash; that is, if it
	does not respond to your mouse clicks and keyboard commands,
	you can either wait and hope that it wakes up, or kill it. If
	you decide to kill it (NOTE: You will lose all unsaved data),
	start the <application>GNOME System monitor</application>
	(from <menuchoice> <guimenu>GNOME Menu</guimenu>
	<guisubmenu>Applications</guisubmenu> <guisubmenu>Sytem
	Tools</guisubmenu> </menuchoice>). Select the application you
	want to kill and click on <guibutton>End process</guibutton>
	button at the bottom. You can also right-click on the
	application name and choose <guimenuitem>End
	process</guimenuitem>; if it doesn't help, right-click and
	choose choose <guimenuitem>Kill process</guimenuitem>. Using
	<application>GNOME System monitor</application> also allows
	you to find and kill all helper processes started by this
	application.
	</para>
      <para>
	If a GNOME application freezes or crashes (unexpectedly dies)
	repeatedly, you should file a bug report as described in
	<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">GNOME feedabck
	page</ulink>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="kill-X11">
      <title>My Whole System Froze!</title> 

      <para> If your whole system is frozen and is not responding, do not
      hurry to push the power  button on the computer
      &mdash; this is usually the worst solution. Most probably, it is
      not the operating system itself that is frozen (UNIX systems are
      known for stability), but just the graphical part, X Window
      System. In this case, you can try to restart X Window System by
      simultaneously pressing
     <keycombo>
    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Backspace</keycap>
   </keycombo>.   This should work for
      the implementation of X Window system used on Linux and *BSD,
      XFree86 (unless it was disabled by your system
      administrator). Of course, in this way you also lose all unsaved
      data, but at least you do not risk to mess up the whole file
      system.
      </para>
    </sect2>

<!--    <sect2 id="icons-messedup">
      <title>My GNOME Desktop Icons Are All Messed up!</title>
      <para> 
	This sometimes happens when upgrading from an older version of
	GNOME. In this case, try this trick: delete the file
	<filename>~/.GNOME/metadata.db</filename> (note the dot!), where
	<filename>~</filename> is your home directory, then log out and
	login again. If this didn't help, read on.
      </para>
    </sect2> -->

    <sect2 id="Gnome-messedup">
      <title>My Whole GNOME Configuration Is Messed Up!</title>
      <para> 
	If you have a serious  problem with your GNOME settings &mdash;
	for example, if your panel is missing &mdash; the radical solution
	is to remove all your GNOME configuration files and start from
	scratch. This is an emergency solution, as you lose all
	configuration settings and will need to configure your menus,
	panels, etc. again from scratch, that is, from the default GNOME
	configuration. However, this only affects GNOME configuration,
	so your data files and settings for non-GNOME applications
	remain intact. 
      </para>
      <para> To remove all your GNOME configuration settings and return
	to the original GNOME configuration, logout then log in again
	holding down keys <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and
	<keycap>Shift</keycap> (immediately after entering your
	password in the login dialog). You will be presented a dialog,
	offering you the choice to reset the saved session (that is,
        which applications were open when you last logged out); reset
        your GNOME configuration settings; or both.  
      </para>
      <para>
	Finally, if you have really severe problems and your system
	freezes or becomes otherwise unusable as soon as you login,
	you have one last option. You can  select
	<guimenuitem>Failsafe</guimenuitem> session type instead of
	the default <guimenuitem>GNOME</guimenuitem> in the login
	screen. Both GNOME and KDE Login Managers support this. In
	this session type, GNOME is not started; instead, you are
	presented with a single terminal window. This is almost
	guaranteed to start OK, and if you know how to use
	command-line tools to find and fix your problem, you have a
	chance. Otherwise, ask an expert.
      </para> 
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!-- ==================Section: ======================== -->
<sect1 id="otherinfo">
    <title>Where to Find More Information</title>
    <sect2 id="Gnome-docs">
      <title>GNOME Help System</title>
      <para>
	GNOME includes detailed documentation for the majority
	of applications, utilities and other components, such as Panel
	or Nautilus file manager. To view a manual for an application,
	choose <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu in the application; to
	view help about the  panel or panel objects, right-click on it
	and choose <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem> from the popup
	menu. This will automatically launch GNOME help browser,
	<application>Yelp</application>, showing appropriate
	manual. 
      </para>
      <para>
	You can also start  <application>Yelp</application>  by
	choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
	  <guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu> </menuchoice>. This will show the
	top-level help system page, listing all GNOME documents
	conveniently organized by topic.
      </para>

      <para> In addition to the manuals for individual applications,
	GNOME documentation also includes:
      </para>
      <variablelist> 
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome2-user-guide">
	    <citetitle>GNOME Desktop 2.0 User Guide</citetitle>
	     </ulink>
          </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para> This user
	    guide provides general overview of GNOME and detailed
	    documentation for core GNOME
	    components (desktop, panel, Nautilus,  and desktop
	    preferences tools).  
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term> <ulink type="help" url="gnome-help:unix-primer">
	    <citetitle>If you are new to UNIX/Linux...</citetitle>
	    </ulink>
	  </term>     
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This short document gives the minimal necessary
	      information about UNIX and UNIX-like operating systems,
	      including such things as filenames, paths and
	      directories, permissions, symbolic links and most
	      confusing of them all, the notion of
	      <quote>mounting</quote>. If you never used UNIX system
	      before, be sure to read this.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para><application>Yelp</application> can also be used for
      viewing non-GNOME documentation, namely man pages and info
	pages (see below).  
      </para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gnome-www"> 
      <title> GNOME Resources on the Internet</title>
      <para> 
	In addition to documentation shipped with GNOME, there is also
	wealth of information available on the Internet. A good
	starting point is the <ulink type="http"
        url="http://www.gnome.org">GNOME website</ulink>. There you
        will find instructions for installing GNOME, reviews and tips,
        developer information, and more.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you can not find an answer to your question there, you
	may ask other GNOME users and developers on GNOME mailing list
        (subscription instructions can be found <ulink type="http"
	url="http://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/gnome-list">here</ulink>).
	Note, however, that this list is for GNOME-related questions
        only (do not ask how to configure X Window System, for instance),
        and it is impolite (to say the least) to ask a question without
        first checking if this question is already answered in available
        documents such as <ulink type="ghelp"
	url="ghelp:gnome2-user-guide">GNOME User Guide</ulink>. 
     </para>
      <para>
	Finally, if you use IRC (Internet Relay Chat), you can find
	other GNOME users and developers and ask questions on
	<systemitem>#gnome</systemitem> channel on
	<systemitem>irc.gnome.org</systemitem>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="not-Gnome-docs">
      <title>Everything Not GNOME</title>
      <para>
	You should realize that GNOME is just part of your computer
	system. If you want to unleash the full potential of your
	computer, you need to understand not just GNOME but also the
	underlying operating system (UNIX/Linux/FreeBSD), various
	tools and utilities included with it, and its graphics system
	(X Window System). Each of these components usually comes with
	its own documentation. Most of UNIX commands and utilities are
        documented in so-called <quote>manual pages</quote>, or man pages
        for short. You can view them using
	<application>Yelp</application> help browser
        (see <xref linkend="Gnome-docs"/>). This documentation is usually
        very detailed and more technical than most users would like.
        Another documentation format used by utilities from the
	GNU project is called <quote>info pages</quote>. They, too,
	can be viewed using <application>Yelp</application>. Many
	applications also have documentation in other formats. Sometimes
`        it is not easy to find documentation for a given application &mdash;
        try looking in the directories  <filename>/usr/share/doc</filename>
	and <filename>/usr/doc</filename>
      </para>
      <para> Documentation for operating system itself varies from one
        system to another. The best advice is to check the printed manual
        which came with your system. For Linux, a good source of information
        is the Linux Documentation Project (LDP); you can read  their
        documentation on the Internet (at <ulink type="http"
	url="http://www.linuxdoc.org">http://www.linuxdoc.org</ulink>).
	Virtually all Linux distributions also include copies of LDP
	documents; usually they are found at
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/LDP</filename> or
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/HOWTO</filename>.
      </para>
      <para> 
	And of course, there is a number of books available about all
	flavors of UNIX/Linux, GNOME, and about anything else you might
        be interested in. Check your local bookstore. 
      </para> 
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="feedback">
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>
	If you have found a bug in one of GNOME applications, or have
	some comments or suggestions regarding GNOME applications or
	documentation, please let us know! Instructions for submitting
	bug reports and comments are given in <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>








