<chapter id="low-vision">
<title>Low Vision or Blindness</title>
<para>From low vision to blindness, the range of visual limitations is broad. Symptoms of low vision include dimness, haziness, extreme far-sightedness or near-sightedness, color blindness, and tunnel vision, among others. People with these disabilities are concerned with being able to see text or images on a computer screen and being able to perform tasks that require eye-hand coordination, such as moving a computer mouse. Text size and color can make a big difference in legibility for people who have low vision.</para>
<para>The technologies that can assist those with low vision or blindness are:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Screen Magnifier</emphasis> - this is like a magnifying glass. People using them are able to control what area of the computer screen they want enlarged, and can move that focus to view different areas of the screen. They are also known as screen enlargers or large print programs.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Screen Reader</emphasis> - this makes on-screen information available as synthesized speech or a refreshable Braille display. They can only translate text based information. Graphics can be translated if there is alternative text describing the visual images. They are also known as blind access utilities or screen reviewers.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Desktop Appearance Enhancement</emphasis> - users can configure the desktop to be easy to read, for example by increasing text size and using high contrast themes.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section id="ats-2">
<title>Screen Reader and Magnifier</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>Screen Reader and Magnifier</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>Orca</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>The <application>Orca Screen Reader
and Magnifier</application> application enables users with limited vision,
or no vision, to use the GNOME Desktop and associated applications. <application>Orca</application> provides the following functionality: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Screen reader</para>
<para>The screen reader enables non-visual access to standard applications
in the GNOME Desktop,
using speech and Braille output.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Magnifier</para>
<para>The magnifier provides automated focus tracking and fullscreen magnification
to aid low-vision users.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The following sections provide information about Orca and how to use it.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction to Orca</title>
    <section>
      <title>What is Orca?</title>
      <para>Orca is a flexible, extensible, and powerful assistive
      technology for people with visual impairments. Using various
      combinations of speech synthesis, braille, and magnification,
      Orca helps provide access to applications and toolkits that
      support the AT-SPI (e.g., the GNOME desktop). Orca is also
      free open source software.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Why the name Orca?</title>
      <para>One of the first DOS screen readers was Flipper by
      Omnichron corporation in Berkeley, CA. It was named Flipper
      in part because the blind wife of the programmer envisioned
      computers as being programmed by flipping switches (an
      accurate image of a bygone era). Then came another DOS screen
      reader from Henter-Joyce in Florida - "Jobs access With
      Speech" (or JAWS). Meanwhile in the UK we had the company
      Dolphin systems making their own DOS screen reader.</para>
      <para>While there isn't otherwise an obvious connection
      between blindness and creatures from the sea, there is
      certainly a long tradition around it.</para>
      <para>Hence the lore is that it is just keeping with the sea
      animal naming theme of screen readers. Plus, Orca is a lot
      tougher sounding than Nemo, Ariel, Willy, or Mr.
      Limpet.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>What's the schedule?</title>
      <para>Orca is part of the GNOME platform and Orca's releases
      are coupled with the releases of the GNOME platform.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>How do I request a new feature?</title>
      <para>
      <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/buglist.cgi?query=product:orca+">
      Bugs</ulink> and feature/enhancement requests (RFEs) should be
      reported to the 
      <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org">GNOME Bug Tracking
      System</ulink>. Patches are always welcome, and instructions
      for creating patches can be found in the 
      <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/tools/svn.html">GNOME
      introduction to Subversion (svn)</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Where is the discussion list?</title>
      <para>You can get in touch with developers and other users by
      
      <ulink url="mailto:orca-list@gnome.org">sending an
      e-mail</ulink> to the 
      <ulink url="http://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/orca-list">
      Orca mailing list</ulink> ( 
      <ulink url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/orca-list">
      Archives</ulink>).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Is braille supported?</title>
      <para>Yes! Braille is supported via BrlTTY and it is
      integrated well with Orca. BrlTTY offers support for nearly
      every refreshable braille display known to man. Please refer
      to the 
      <ulink url="ghelp:orca#braille">Braille page</ulink> for more
      information.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Is contracted braille supported?</title>
      <para>Orca currently only supports uncontracted braille.
      Future support for contracted braille, however, is in our
      plans. Please refer to 
      <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=354470">
      GNOME bug 354470</ulink> to track the progress on this
      front.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>What voices are available?</title>
      <para>Orca provides interfaces to both 
      <userinput>gnome-speech</userinput> and 
      <userinput>emacspeak</userinput> speech services. As such, the available
      voices for Orca are only restricted by the speech engines
      supported by the available speech services. For free speech
      engines, you typically have a choice of the eSpeak, Festival,
      and FreeTTS speech engines. For commercial engines, you have
      a choice of additional engines such as Fonix DECtalk,
      Loquendo, Eloquence, Cepstral, IBMTTS, and others may be on
      the way soon. Keep an eye on the 
      <userinput>gnome-speech</userinput> package for more progress in this
      area.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>What languages are supported?</title>
      <para>The 
      <ulink url="http://l10n.gnome.org/teams">GNOME Translation
      teams</ulink> are composed of many passionate volunteers from
      around the world. These teams do a great job and keep an
      up-to-date status report. Please see the 
      <ulink url="http://l10n.gnome.org/module/orca">Orca
      translation status page</ulink> for the large number of
      languages into which Orca has been translated. Note that the
      support for a language also depends upon a speech synthesis
      engine that supports the language whether BrlTTY has braille
      tables for the language or not.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>How well does magnification work?</title>
      <para>Orca currently uses the 
      <userinput>gnome-mag</userinput> magnification service. As of this
      writing (GNOME 2.18), 
      <userinput>gnome-mag</userinput> has incorporated some support for
      smoother full screen magnification, which relies upon newer
      extensions in the X Window System server. These extensions do
      not always function well on all platforms, so smooth full
      screen magnification may not always work.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>How is web access coming along?</title>
      <para>We are targeting Firefox 3 for providing compelling web
      access. The work is progressing step by step and both the
      Orca and Firefox teams are working feverishly to get it
      done.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using Orca</title>
    <section>
      <title>Initial Set-up</title>
      <para>When you run Orca for the first time, it will
      automatically enter setup mode. If you want to run setup at
      some later point, you can pass the 
      <userinput>--setup</userinput> option to Orca the next time you run it.
      Furthermore, while Orca is running, you can press 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo> to bring up the Orca setup window. Finally, Orca
      provides a text setup utility that you can start by passing
      the 
      <userinput>--text-setup</userinput> option to Orca. All of these options
      will create a 
      <userinput>~/.orca/user-settings.py</userinput> file that holds your
      preferences and will also enable the accessibility
      infrastructure. You need to log out and log back in for the
      accessibility infrastructure settings to take effect.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>How do I run Orca?</title>
      <para>Run Orca by typing 
      <userinput>orca</userinput>into a Terminal. You can do so
      from a virtual console window if you do not yet have access
      to the GUI. Orca will automatically enter text setup mode if
      you run it from a virtual console window or your GUI
      environment is not yet set up for accessibility.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Quitting Orca</title>
      <para>To quit orca, press 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Q</keycap>
      </keycombo>. A confirmation dialog will appear. Select "yes"
      to quit. If the system seems unresponsive, you can do a
      couple things:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run 
          <userinput>orca --quit</userinput> from a terminal window, such as a
          virtual console (press 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            <keycap>F1</keycap>
          </keycombo> on most Linux platforms to get to a virtual
          console and then 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            <keycap>F7</keycap>
          </keycombo> to get back to the desktop). This will kill
          orca and clean up after it. You can then rerun orca using
          the Orca command.</para>
          <para>Press 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            <keycap>Backspace</keycap>
          </keycombo> to kill your login session and get back to the
          graphical login prompt.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Customizing Orca</title>
    <section>
      <title>How do I define my own keybindings?</title>
      <para>You can currently redefine your key bindings for Orca
      in two main ways. The first way is to be able to choose
      between the destkop and laptop layouts, which can be selected
      on the "General" page of the Orca Configuration GUI (press 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo> to bring up the Orca preferences GUI). For
      finer-grained control, you can also redefine indivual key
      bindings on the "Key Bindings" page of the Orca Configuration
      GUI.</para>
      <note>
        <para>The remainder of this answer might be out of
        date.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Here's an example you can add to your 
      <userinput>~/.orca/user-settings.py</userinput> file. It sets up a
      global keybinding for 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>T</keycap>
      </keycombo> (
      <keycap>Insert</keycap> is the Orca modifier) to speak and
      braille "Hello World."</para>
      <screen>
<![CDATA[# Set up custom keybindings.
import orca.braille
import orca.input_event
import orca.keybindings
import orca.orca
import orca.speech
from orca.orca_i18n import _
def sayHello(script, inputEvent=None):
    message = _("Hello World")
    # Say/braille something.
    #
    orca.speech.speak(message)
    orca.braille.displayMessage(message)
    # Consume the event so it will not go to an application.
    #
    return True
sayHelloHandler = orca.input_event.InputEventHandler(
    sayHello,
    _("Says hello to this fine world."))
myKeyBindings = orca.keybindings.KeyBindings()
myKeyBindings.add(orca.keybindings.KeyBinding(
    "t",
    1 << orca.settings.MODIFIER_ORCA,
    1 << orca.settings.MODIFIER_ORCA,
    sayHelloHandler))
orca.settings.keyBindingsMap["default"] = myKeyBindings
]]>
</screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Use a keyboard command to make Orca speak or braille
      the current date and time</title>
      <para>Place the following lines in 
      <userinput>~/.orca/orca-customizations.py</userinput>. If this file
      does not exist, create it.</para>
      <screen>
<![CDATA[import orca.input_event
import orca.keybindings
import orca.orca
import orca.speech
import orca.braille
import re
]]>
<![CDATA[
myKeyBindings = orca.keybindings.KeyBindings()
]]>
<![CDATA[
def sayTime(script, inputEvent=None):
    import time
    message = time.strftime("%a, %d %b %Y %H:%M:%S", time.localtime())
    orca.speech.speak(message)
    orca.braille.displayMessage(message)
    return True
]]>
<![CDATA[
sayTimeHandler = orca.input_event.InputEventHandler(
    sayTime,
    "Presents the time.")
]]>
<![CDATA[
myKeyBindings.add(orca.keybindings.KeyBinding(
    "d",
    1 << orca.settings.MODIFIER_ORCA,
    1 << orca.settings.MODIFIER_ORCA,
    sayTimeHandler))
]]>
<![CDATA[
orca.settings.keyBindingsMap["default"] = myKeyBindings
]]>
</screen>
      <para>Note that in this case 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>D</keycap>
      </keycombo> will be used to report current information about
      the time and date.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>How do I set up my own custom script area?</title>
      <para>The short answer is that if you create an empty 
      <userinput>~/.orca/orca-scripts/__init__.py</userinput> and place your
      custom scripts in 
      <userinput>~/.orca/orca-scripts</userinput>, Orca will pick up any
      scripts from there before looking in the installed
      area.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Orca Configuration GUI</title>
      <para>The Orca Configuration GUI allows you to customize the
      behavior and features of Orca, such as speech, braille, and
      magnification. For example, you can select which speech
      synthesis engine you want to use, whether braille is enabled
      or not, and which magnification preferences you want. You can
      select which general keyboard layout you want (desktop or
      laptop) and you can also examine and modify the existing
      keyboard layout with fine grained control. To bring up the
      Orca Configuration GUI, press 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>&lt;ORCA MODIFIER&gt;</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo>, where 
      <userinput>&lt;ORCA MODIFIER&gt;</userinput> is 
      <keycap>Insert</keycap> when you use the desktop key bindings,
      and 
      <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> when you use the laptop key
      bindings.</para>
      <para>The Orca Configuration GUI is a multi-page dialog
      containing several sections, each of which is described in
      the following sections.</para>
      <section>
        <title>General Page</title>
        <para>The "General" page allows you to customize general
        aspects of Orca. These include the following:</para>
        <section>
          <title>Keyboard layout</title>
          <para>The keyboard layout section allows you to specify
          if you will be working on a laptop (small) or desktop
          (large, with a numeric keypad) keyboard. You select which
          layout you want by selecting one of the following
          option:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Desktop - if selected, the Desktop Keyboard
              Layout will be used.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Laptop - if selected, the Laptop Keyboard
              Layout will be used</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Show Orca main window</title>
          <para>The Orca main window provides you with a graphical
          way to display the Orca Configuration GUI (also
          obtainable via 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Space</keycap>
          </keycombo>) and to quit Orca (also achievable via 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>). Many users do not like the Orca main window
          because it shows up in the window manager's tab order
          when you press 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            <keycap>Tab</keycap>
          </keycombo> to switch windows. By deselecting the "Show
          Orca main window" button, you can tell Orca to not show
          the Orca main window.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Quit Orca without Confirmation</title>
          <para>Normally, when you press 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo> to quit Orca or press the 
          <guibutton>Quit</guibutton>button in the Orca main
          window, Orca will pop up a confirmation dialog asking you
          if you want to quit. Unchecking this option prevents the
          confirmation window from appearing.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Disable gksu keyboard grab</title>
          <para>When running system administration commands from
          the launch menu, many distributions use an application
          known as 
          <application>gksu</application>to authorize the user to
          run these commands ( 
          <application>gksu</application>is the GUI that asks you
          for your password). When it runs, 
          <application>gksu</application>enables what is known as a
          "keyboard grab," which is a feature to prevent keyboard
          actions from going to any other application on the
          desktop, including Orca. The result of a keyboard grab is
          that Orca will not receive any keyboard events,
          preventing Orca from functioning normally.</para>
          <para>By selecting the 
          <guibutton>Disable gksu keyboard grab</guibutton>button,
          you will turn off the keyboard grab behavior, allowing
          Orca to functional normally with system administration
          applications.</para>
          <note>
            <para>The keyboard grab is a security attempt by 
            <application>gksu</application>to prevent nefarious
            applications from "sniffing" the keyboard and obtaining
            your password. Please be advised that disabling 
            <application>gksu</application>'s keyboard grab feature
            can expose you to such nefarious behavior.</para>
            <para>If you do not feel comfortable with this, you can
            always use the root account for system administration
            purposes. To do so, you need to enable the root account
            for login, and the logout and log back in as root
            whenever you want to perform a system administration
            command.</para>
          </note>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Present tooltips</title>
          <para>When checked, this option will tell Orca to present
          information about tooltips when they appear as the result
          of mouse hovering. Specific actions to force tooltips to
          appear, such as pressing 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>F1</keycap>
          </keycombo> when an object has focus, will always result
          in tooltips being presented, regardless of this
          setting.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Speech Page</title>
        <para>The speech page allows you to customize how Orca uses
        speech synthesis.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Enable speech</title>
          <para>The first control of note on the speech page is the
          
          <guilabel>enable speech</guilabel> check box. This check
          box toggles whether or not Orca will make use of a speech
          synthesizer. This option, along with the ability to
          enable braille and enable magnifier support, allow Orca
          to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of
          users.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Speech System and Speech Synthesizer</title>
          <para>The next two controls deal with selecting the
          speech system and synthesizer. Orca provides support for
          a growing number of speech systems. At the time of this
          writing, these include GNOME-speech, Emacspeak, and an
          experimental backend for Speech Dispatcher. Depending
          upon how your machine is configured, you may have all or
          none of these options. Typically, you will have just
          GNOME-speech.</para>
          <para>First, determine which speech system you would like
          to use - GNOME-speech works best at this time. After
          making your selection, tab to the speech synthesizer
          combo box and choose from the list of available
          synthesizers.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Voice Settings</title>
          <para>If your synthesizer supports it, Orca can utilize
          multiple voices in order to identify special cases within
          an application, such as hyperlinks or upper case text.
          The voice settings and person combo boxes can be adjusted
          to customize these settings to your liking. For example,
          assume you were using Fonix DECtalk and wanted the betty
          voice to denote upper case. To accomplish this, you could
          do the following:</para>
          <orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
            <listitem>
              <para>Tab to the voice settings combo box, and down
              arrow until the upper case voice is selected.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Tab to the person combo box, and down arrow to
              choose the Betty voice.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <para>The next three sliders in the tab order allow
          adjustment of the synthesizer's rate, pitch and volume
          respectively.</para>
          <para>Note that you can quickly raise/lower the pitch by
          pressing 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Up Arrow</keycap>
          </keycombo> and 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Down Arrow</keycap>
          </keycombo>. You can also modify the speaking rate by
          pressing 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Left Arrow</keycap>
          </keycombo> and 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>Right Arrow</keycap>
          </keycombo>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Punctuation Level</title>
          <para>The 
          <guilabel>punctuation level</guilabel> radio button group
          is used to adjust the amount of punctuation spoken by the
          synthesizer . The available levels are none, some, most,
          and all.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Verbosity</title>
          <para>The verbosity setting determines the amount of
          information that will be spoken in certain situations.
          For example, if it is set to verbose, the synthesizer
          will speak shortcut keys for items in pull down menus.
          When it is set to brief, these shortcut keys are not
          announced.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Table Row Speech</title>
          <para>The table row speech option determines the way in
          which Orca will read items within tables. The available
          settings are speak current row, or speak current cell.
          The ability to adjust this behavior can be useful in many
          situations. For example, consider the process of browsing
          email messages in Evolution. In this instance it may be
          preferable to set table speech to current row, so that
          while arrowing through the list of messages, all relevant
          info, such as the sender, subject, and whether the
          message has attachments is read automatically. While the
          current row setting is active, it is still possible to
          read individual cells by using the left and right
          arrows.</para>
          <para>Note that you can quickly toggle this behavior by
          pressing 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Insert</keycap>
            <keycap>F11</keycap>
          </keycombo>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Speak Indentation</title>
          <para>When working with code or editing documents, it is
          often desirable to be aware of justification as well as
          indentation. Selecting the 
          <guilabel>speak indentation and
          justification</guilabel> check box will cause Orca to
          provide this information.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Speak Blank Lines</title>
          <para>Some users desire to hear "blank" when navigating
          to a blank line in a document. Other users do not. If the
          
          <guilabel>speak blank lines</guilabel> check box is
          selected, Orca will speak blank lines.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Braille Page</title>
        <para>The braille page allows you to customize various
        aspects about the use of braille. Orca does not
        automatically start BrlTTY for you -- you typically need to
        do that yourself, and it is something that is usually done
        at boot time.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Enable Braille Support</title>
          <para>The first control on the braille page is the 
          <guilabel>enable braille support</guilabel> check box.
          This check box toggles whether or not Orca will make use
          of a braille display. This option, along with the ability
          to enable braille and enable magnifier support, allow
          Orca to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety
          of users. By default, this check box is enabled. If
          BrlTTY is not running, Orca will recover gracefully and
          will not communicate with the braille display. If you
          configure BrlTTY later on, you need to restart Orca in
          order for it to use braille.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Enable Braille Monitor</title>
          <para>Orca's braille monitor provides an onscreen
          representation of what takes place on the braille
          display. This feature is mostly for demonstration
          purposes, but is also useful for Orca developers who do
          not have access to a braille display.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Abbreviated Role Names</title>
          <para>The 
          <guilabel>abbreviated role names</guilabel> check box
          determines the manner in which role names are displayed
          and can be used to help conserve real estate on the
          braille display. The "abbreviated role names" option can
          be better understood if we consider the following
          example. Let us assume that a slider had focus, and that
          the abbreviated role names box was not checked. In that
          case, the word "slider" would be shown on the display, to
          reflect the fact that the current control was indeed a
          slider. If the abbreviated role names box was checked,
          the word "slider" would be abbreviated to "sldr".</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Verbosity</title>
          <para>The 
          <guilabel>verbosity</guilabel> radio button group
          determines the amount of information that will be
          brailled in certain situations. For example, if it is set
          to verbose, keyboard shortcut and role name information
          is displayed. This information is not displayed in brief
          mode.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Key Echo Page</title>
        <para>The key echo page allows you to specify the behavior
        of Orca when pressing keys on the page and whether words
        are spoken as you complete them.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Enable Key Echo</title>
          <para>The first control on the key echo page is the 
          <guilabel>enable key echo</guilabel> check box. When this
          box is selected, five additional check boxes become
          available. These are 
          <guilabel>Enable alphanumeric and punctuation
          keys</guilabel>, 
          <guilabel>Enable modifier keys</guilabel>, 
          <guilabel>Enable locking keys</guilabel>, 
          <guilabel>Enable function keys</guilabel>, and 
          <guilabel>Enable action keys</guilabel>.</para>
          <para>The alphanumeric and function key groups are
          relatively self explanatory.</para>
          <para>Modifier keys are those such as 
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>, 
          <keycap>Control</keycap>, and 
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>.</para>
          <para>Locking keys include 
          <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>, 
          <keycap>Scroll Lock</keycap>, and 
          <keycap>Num Lock</keycap>.</para>
          <para>The action keys group consists of keys that perform
          some logical action, as 
          <keycap>Backspace</keycap>, 
          <keycap>Return</keycap>and 
          <keycap>Tab</keycap>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Enable Echo by Word</title>
          <para>The last toggle on the key echo page is the 
          <guilabel>enable echo by word</guilabel> check box. The
          echo by word control is always available, regardless of
          whether any of the key echo options are checked.</para>
          <para>In summary, the key echo scheme can offer a great
          deal of flexibility. For example, one user might choose
          to enable all key echo options, while another might
          prefer to use word echo, but only have locking keys
          announced.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Magnifier Page</title>
        <para>The magnifier page allows you to enable/disable
        magnification and specify how magnification is
        performed.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Enable Magnifier</title>
          <para>The first control on the magnifier page is the 
          <guilabel>enable magnifier</guilabel> check box. This
          check box toggles whether or not Orca will provide
          magnification. This option, along with the ability to
          enable speech and enable braille support, allow Orca to
          be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of
          users.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Cursor Settings</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enable cursor</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Color</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Custom size and width</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Cross-hair Settings</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enable cross-hair and size</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enable cross-hair clip</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Zoomer Settings</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Scale factor</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Invert colors</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Zoomer position</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Top, left, right, bottom</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Smoothing</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Mouse tracking mode</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Source display - X Window System DISPLAY of
              what should be magnified. Typically 
              <userinput>:0</userinput>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Target display - X Window System DISPLAY of
              where to put the magnified area. Typically 
              <userinput>:0</userinput>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Key Bindings Page</title>
        <para>The key bindings page allows you to examine and
        modify the key bindings for Orca.</para>
        <section>
          <title>Orca Modifier Key(s)</title>
          <para>The first control on the key bindings page allows
          you to eaxmine which key (or keys) acts as the "Orca
          modifier". The Orca modifier is the key that you press
          and hold in conjunction with other keys to give commands
          to Orca. For desktop keyboards, the Orca modifier
          defaults to 
          <keycap>Insert</keycap>. For laptop keyboards, the Orca
          modifier defaults to the 
          <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> key.</para>
          <para>You cannot modify the Orca modifier key(s) using
          the Configuration GUI at this time.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Key Bindings Table</title>
          <para>The key bindings table provides a list of Orca
          operations and the keys that are bound to them.</para>
          <para>The "Function" column header is a description of
          the Ora operation to be performed.</para>
          <para>The "Key Binding" header is the primary way to
          invoke the function from the keyboard. Note that the
          function description may include the word Orca. This
          indicates that the Orca modifier key should be held down
          along with the other keys.</para>
          <para>The "Alternate" header provides an alternate
          mechanism for invoking the function from the
          keyboard.</para>
          <para>To modify either the "Key Binding" or the
          "Alternate" bindings, arrow to the cell and press 
          <keycap>Return</keycap>. Then, press a key combination
          and press 
          <keycap>Return</keycap> to confirm the new combination.
          When you do so, the new keystroke will be saved and the
          check box in the last column (the 
          <guilabel>Modified</guilabel> column) will indicate that
          the key binding has been modified.</para>
          <para>To unmodify a modified keybinding, merely arrow to
          the modified column, uncheck the checkbox, and press the 
          <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>button ( 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            <keycap>A</keycap>
          </keycombo>).</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Text Attributes Page</title>
        <para>Orca will speak known text attribute information
        about an object when you press 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Insert</keycap>
          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo> ( 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>
          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo> for laptop systems).</para>
        <para>Because the number of text attributes is large, and
        not everyone cares about every attribute, the "Text
        Attributes" tab of the configuration GUI allows you to
        customize which text attributes Orca will present.</para>
        <para>On this tab is a text attribute list, where each row
        consists of three columns:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
          <listitem>
            <para>A checkbox which the user can set to indicate
            whether this text attribute should be spoken or
            not.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the text attribute.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>An editable "Spoken unless" string value. By
            default, not all text attributes will have this set. If
            present, what it means (assuming the user wants this
            text attribute spoken) is that the value of the
            attribute will only be spoken if it's a different value
            than this value.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>For example, by default the "underline" text
        attribute has a value of "none". If the user has this
        attribute checked and the user presses 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Insert</keycap>
          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo> and the text in question is not underlined, then
        this attribute is not spoken. If you always want this
        attribute to be spoken irrespective of whether the text is
        underlined, then the attribute should be checked and the
        "Spoken unless" value cleared.</para>
        <para>There is also a "Reset" 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>
          <keycap>R</keycap>
        </keycombo> button combination present that will set the
        list values back to their initial state when the dialog was
        first displayed.</para>
        <para>When you initially display the text attribute pane,
        all your checked attributes are put at the top of the list.
        They are given in the order that they will be spoken and
        brailled.</para>
        <para>If you decide to check others or wish to adjust the
        order, there are four buttons to help you do this:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>"Move to top" 
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <keycap>T</keycap>
            </keycombo> - moves the selected attribute to the top of
            the list.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>"Move up one" 
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <keycap>U</keycap>
            </keycombo> - moves the selected attribute up one
            row.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>"Move down one" 
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <keycap>D</keycap>
            </keycombo> - moves the selected attribute down one
            row.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>"Move to bottom" 
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <keycap>B</keycap>
            </keycombo> - moves the selected attribute to the bottom
            of the list.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Text attributes can also be set on an individual
        application basis. The text attribute pane is also part of
        the application specific settings dialog that is started
        when you give a particular application focus and press 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Insert</keycap>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
          <keycap>Space</keycap>
        </keycombo>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Application-specific information</title>
    <section>
      <title>Accessible Applications</title>
      <para>Orca is designed to work with applications and toolkits
      that support the assistive technology service provider
      interface (AT-SPI). This includes the GNOME desktop and its
      applications, OpenOffice, Firefox, and the Java platform.
      Some applications work better than others, however, and the
      Orca community continually works to provide compelling access
      to more and more applications.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using Adobe's Acrobat Reader</title>
      <para>We are currently working on a script for Adobe's
      Acrobat Reader, and the initial version has been contributed
      to Orca v2.17.5. Note that there is still work to do, and we
      are very encouraged by Adobe's commitment to
      accessibility.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Installation</title>
        <para>If you get Adobe Acrobat Reader directly from the 
        <ulink url='http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html'>
        Adobe site</ulink>, you may find that the software will not
        launch. The symptoms: If launched from the Applications
        menu, it appears that nothing has happened. If launched
        from a terminal window, you receive a long series of syntax
        error messages. Should this occur, you will need to edit
        your /usr/bin/acroread file as described in this 
        <ulink url='http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=233514'>
        Ubuntu forum thread</ulink>.</para>
        <para>If you instead choose to install Acrobat Reader from
        your distribution's packages, be sure to install both
        acroread and acroread-plugins. Without the plugins package,
        you will not have the access to the "Reading" category in
        the 
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
          <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> dialog.</para>
        <para>Note: If you use Ubuntu and cannot locate the
        acroread package, you will likely need to edit your
        /etc/apt/sources.list to include the 'multiverse'
        repository. Then run 
        <userinput>apt-get update</userinput>. Having done so, you should
        then be able to install both acroread and
        acroread-plugins.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Enabling Accessibility and Caret Navigation</title>
        <para>Once you've installed Reader, you need to enable
        accessibility:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the "Accessibility" category of the 
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
              <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> dialog, make sure "Always display the
            keyboard selection cursor" (<keycombo>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <keycap>D</keycap>
            </keycombo>) is checked.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the "Reading" category of the 
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
              <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> dialog, make sure "Enable document
            accessibility" (<keycombo>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <keycap>E</keycap>
            </keycombo>) is checked.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Working with Untagged Documents</title>
        <para>When you open an untagged document, you will be
        presented with a dialog box asking you to specify the
        reading order and the reading mode options. The default
        reading order is "Infer reading order from document." This
        setting works well for most documents, but not all of
        them.</para>
        <para>The default reading mode will vary depending upon the
        length of the document: For short documents, the default is
        "Read the entire document"; for long documents it is "Read
        the currently visible pages only." Orca seems to provide
        much better access when "Read the entire document" is
        selected.</para>
        <para>If you find that a document seems to be missing parts
        of the text, try changing the reading options. To do so,
        get into the Document menu and select "Change Accessibility
        Reading Options..." or use the shortcut 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          <keycap>5</keycap>
        </keycombo>.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Page Layout</title>
        <para>The best page layout for reading a document with Orca
        is "single page". When "continuous" is chosen, moving focus
        to text as the page is scrolling can cause that text not to
        be read. You can change the page layout to "single page" by
        getting into the View menu and selecting the Page Layout
        submenu.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Navigating Tables</title>
        <para>Regarding tables: As far as we know there's not
        currently a whole lot of keyboard support for tables in
        Acrobat Reader. This, by the way, is not an Orca thing; it
        is an Acrobat Reader thing.</para>
        <para>Basically, there are the arrow keys. Their behavior
        is to move you first within the cell with focus, then to
        the next cell with data in it. Note that currently, Up and
        Down Arrow do not seem to move you vertically among cells
        -- at least that has been the experience with the tables we
        have tried. Instead, Up and Down seem to move you
        horizontally until you run out of cells on the current
        row.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Making Application Specific Settings</title>
      <para>To customize the settings for a particular application,
      you will first need to run that application. Make sure that
      that application has focus, then press 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>ORCA_MODIFIER</keycap>
        <keycap>Control</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo> (by default, this will be 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Control</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo> for the desktop keyboard layout).</para>
      <para>This brings up a tabbed dialog window very similar to
      the generic Orca Preferences dialog, but with the following
      differences:</para>
      <orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
        <listitem>
          <para>There is no initial General pane.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Speech System and Speech Synthesizer combo
          boxes on the Speech pane will be grayed out (made
          inactive).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any existing application specific key bindings will
          appear at the top of the list on the Key Bindings
          pane.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>There may be a new application specific settings
          pane at the end of the set of tabbed panes. Note that
          pressing the End key from the tab list will get you
          directly to that rightmost tab.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>Adjust your application specific Orca settings in a
      similar way to the way to set your general Orca preferences.
      For example, you may have key echo disabled generally in Orca
      but would like to specifically have it enabled for the
      gcalctool (GNOME Calculator) application. Here's where you
      could easily set that.</para>
      <para>When you have your application settings customized the
      way that you want, press the OK button. These settings will
      be written away under your 
      <userinput>~/.orca/app-settings</userinput> directory in a file called 
      <userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;.py</userinput>, where 
      <userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;</userinput> is the name of the
      application.</para>
      <para>These files are automatically written by Orca. The
      existing contents of that file will just be blown away each
      time you change your application settings for that
      application.</para>
      <para>If you want to have some extra application specific
      settings or code that you don't want to lose, then you should
      put it in a file called 
      <userinput>
      ~/.orca/app-settings/&lt;APPNAME&gt;-customizations.py</userinput>.
      This file will be automatically read when the settings for
      the 
      <userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;</userinput> application are loaded.</para>
      <para>Note that this is an advanced feature that we don't
      expect most Orca users to use. It's just there if you really
      want it.</para>
      <para>There is currently one known bug (some people would
      call it a feature) that we are trying to track down and
      fix:</para>
      <note>
        <para>If you adjust one or more application specific key
        bindings, the new values will not take immediate effect
        after you've pressed the OK button on the dialog. The
        workaround is to either restart Orca, or to Alt-Tab away to
        some other application and then Alt-Tab back to the one
        that you've just changed the key bindings for.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Braille</title>
    <para>Orca uses 
    <ulink url='http://mielke.cc/brltty/'>BrlTTY</ulink> for braille
    support. Orca does not automatically start BrlTTY for you --
    you typically need to do that yourself, and it is something
    that is usually done at boot time. Start-up options are
    described in the BRTLTTY reference manual.</para>
    <para>Orca attempts to work with various releases of BrlTTY. It
    works well with BrlTTY v3.7.2, and we've also been working with
    the BrlTTY team to get it going for BrlTTY v3.8. The remainder
    of this document provides information related to using Orca
    with BRLTTY 3.8.</para>
    <para>To get Orca working with BrlTTY v3.8 requires that the
    Python bindings for BrlAPI are built/installed as part of the
    BrlTTY build/install process. Below are descriptions of the
    necessary tasks to do this for Ubuntu and Solaris. For both,
    you need to first obtain 
    <ulink url='http://mielke.cc/brltty/releases/brltty-3.8.tar.gz'>
    brltty-3.8.tar.gz</ulink> from the BrlTTY site.</para>
    <para />
    <para />
    <section>
      <title>BrlTTY 3.8 on Ubuntu</title>
      <para>First, setup your build environment to build BrlTTY.
      Much of this setup is done for you automatically in the
      Ubuntu distribution with products such as G++ already
      present. In addition, YOU MUST also install tcl, Pyrex, and
      the Python developers environment. To do this, execute the
      following commands as 
      <userinput>root</userinput> :</para>
      <para></para>
      <screen>
<![CDATA[apt-get build-dep brltty
apt-get install tcl8.4 python-pyrex python-dev
]]>
</screen>
      <para>Then, when you build BrlTTY, avoid configuring the
      package with --prefix=/usr. Use the standard procedure
      instead, executing the following commands as 
      <userinput>root</userinput> :</para>
      <para></para>
      <screen>
<![CDATA[gunzip -c brltty-3.8.tar.gz | tar xvf -
cd brltty-3.8
./autogen
./configure
make
make install
]]>
</screen>
      <para>Run BrlTTY as 
      <userinput>root</userinput> (need notes on automatically starting
      brltty):</para>
      <para></para>
      <screen>
<![CDATA[/bin/brltty -bauto -d/dev/ttyUSB0
]]>
</screen>
      <para>If you want, you can remove the existing 
      <userinput>/sbin/brltty</userinput> and replace it with the 
      <userinput>/bin/brltty</userinput> either by copying the 
      <userinput>/bin/brltty</userinput> to 
      <userinput>/sbin/brltty</userinput>  or just by making a symbolic link.
      Do so at your own risk.</para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Keyboard Commands</title>
    <para>This is the list of common Orca keyboard commands. Note
    that you can always enter Orca's "learn mode" while running
    Orca by pressing 
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Insert</keycap>
      <keycap>F1</keycap>
    </keycombo>. When in learn mode, Orca will intercept all
    keyboard and braille input events and will tell you what the
    effect of them would be. To exit learn mode, press the 
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>escape</keycap>
    </keycombo> key. If you are using a laptop computer, you will
    want to see the 
    <ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Orca/LaptopKeyboardCommands">
    laptop keyboard commands</ulink> page at live.gnome.org.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Commands for adjusting speech parameters</title>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Right Arrow</keycap>
      </keycombo> : increase speech rate</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Left Arrow</keycap>
      </keycombo> : decrease speech rate</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Up Arrow</keycap>
      </keycombo> : raise the pitch</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Down Arrow</keycap>
      </keycombo> : lower the pitch</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Flat review commands</title>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-7</emphasis>: Move the flat
      review cursor to the previous line, and read it.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-8</emphasis>: Read the current
      line.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-9</emphasis>: Move the flat
      review cursor to the next line, and read it.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-4</emphasis>: Move the flat
      review cursor to the previous word, and read it.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-5</emphasis>: Read the current
      word.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-6</emphasis>: Move the flat
      review cursor to the next word, and read it.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-1</emphasis>: Move the flat
      review cursor to the previous character, and read it.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-2</emphasis>: Read the current
      character.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-3</emphasis>: Move the flat
      review cursor to the next character, and read it.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-/</emphasis>: Perform a left
      mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-*</emphasis>: Perform a right
      mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.</para>
      <note>
        <para>The above commands apply when working with objects as
        well as when working with text. For example, if the flat
        review cursor were positioned on a menu bar, pressing the
        "read current line" command (
        <emphasis role="strong">Numpad-8</emphasis>) would speak
        the names of all visible menus. Similarly, pressing read
        next word would speak the object to the right of the flat
        review cursor on the same line, or move flat review to the
        next line if no more objects were found.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Bookmark commands</title>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>[1-6]</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Add a bookmark in this numbered slot. If a
      bookmark already exists at this register it will be replaced
      with the new one.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>[1-6]</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Go to the position pointed to by the bookmark
      bound to this numbered slot.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>
        <keycap>[1-6]</keycap>
      </keycombo> : "Where am I" information for this bookmark
      relative to the current pointer location.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>B</keycap>
      </keycombo> and 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>
        <keycap>B</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Move between the given bookmarks for the given
      application or page.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>B</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Save the defined bookmarks for the current
      application or page.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Miscellaneous functions</title>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Numpad</keycap>
        <keycap>+</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Say all command. reads from the current position
      of the caret to the end of the document.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Numpad</keycap>
        <keycap>Enter</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Where am I command. Speaks information such as
      the title of the current application window, as well as the
      name of the control that currently has focus.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F1</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Enter learn mode (press 
      <keycap>Escape</keycap>to exit)</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Speak font and attribute information for the
      current character.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Launch the Orca Configuration dialog.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        <keycap>Space</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Reload user settings and reinitialize services
      as necessary. In the latest versions of Orca, launch the Orca
      Configuration dialog for the current application.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>S</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Toggle speech on and off.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F11</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Toggle the reading of tables, either by single
      cell, or whole row.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>Q</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Quit orca.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Commands for debugging</title>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F3</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Report information on the currently active
      script.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F4</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Cycle through Orca's various debug
      levels.</para>
      <note>
        <para>In order for the next three commands to be of use,
        Orca needs to be started from a virtual console or via
        gnome-terminal. Output is sent only to the console (i.e.,
        it is not sent to speech or braille).</para>
      </note>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F5</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Prints a debug listing of all known applications
      to the console where Orca is running.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F7</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Prints debug information about the ancestry of
      the object with focus.</para>
      <para>
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Insert</keycap>
        <keycap>F8</keycap>
      </keycombo> : Prints debug information about the application
      with focus.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <section>
      <title>Orca is not speaking. What is going wrong?</title>
      <para>See 
      <ulink url='http://live.gnome.org/Orca/GnomeSpeech'>
      Troubleshooting Speech</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>My desktop has stopped responding. What do I
      do?</title>
      <para>If you can get to a terminal (or press 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        <keycap>F2</keycap>
      </keycombo> to open the "Run Command" dialog box), try
      restarting Orca by issuing another Orca command in a terminal
      window. This will force any existing Orca process to exit and
      will then restart Orca. This sometimes has the effect of
      unhanging the desktop (which is usually due to an ill-behaved
      application).</para>
      <para>If you cannot get to a terminal window, try pressing 
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        <keycap>Backspace</keycap>
      </keycombo> to kill the X Window System server. This should
      have the effect of returning you to the login screen.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

</section>

<section id="themes-0">
<title>Desktop Appearance Enhancement</title>
<para>This chapter describes the methods you can use to change the appearance
of the GNOME Desktop
to enhance the accessibility of the desktop for users with visual impairments.</para>
<section id="themes-1">
<title>Customization Options</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>There are a number of methods to enable you to customize the appearance
of the GNOME Desktop
to suit your specific needs, as follows:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Themes</term>
<listitem>
<para>Themes are the most effective
way to change the appearance of the desktop in a consistent manner. See <xref linkend="themes-2"/> for more information about themes and how to use themes
to achieve the type of desktop environment that you require.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Desktop and application-specific configuration settings</term>
<listitem>
<para>You can customize different components of the desktop
individually to achieve the display settings that you require. You can configure
the desktop and applications in addition to using themes or as an alternative
to using themes. See <xref linkend="themes-7"/> for more information.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>The following table summarizes the changes that you can
make to the GNOME Desktop and where you can make the changes. This guide does not provide
detailed instructions about how to customize the desktop. For detailed instructions
about how to use the customization tools that the desktop provides, refer
to the Help for each tool or to the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?prefs">User Guide</ulink>.</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="themes-TBL-1">
<title>Quick Reference to Customizing the Appearance of the Desktop</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33.04*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="14.50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>To change the...</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Use...</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Overall appearance of the desktop to use high
contrast colors, low contrast colors, or large print.</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>The <application>Theme</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Appearance of the desktop background only.</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>The <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool and the file manager <guilabel>Backgrounds
and Emblems</guilabel> menu item.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Font displayed on the desktop background and
in all desktop applications.</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>The <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Default font settings of the <application>Text Editor</application>, <application>Terminal</application> or <application>Help</application> application.</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>By default, these applications use the default application font that is specified
in the <application>Font</application> preference tool but can be overridden in the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog for the application.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
<section id="themes-2">
<title>Using Themes to Customize the Desktop</title>
<para>This section describes how to use themes to customize the appearance
of the GNOME Desktop.</para>
<section id="themes-3">
<title>Introduction to Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>A theme is a group of
coordinated settings that specifies how a desktop component or a group of
desktop components appears. You can use themes to modify and control the appearance
of the desktop in a consistent manner. When you apply a theme, the system
modifies many desktop components simultaneously to achieve the desired effect.
For example, if you apply a theme that increases the font size across the
desktop, the theme also modifies the size of panels and icons on the desktop
for optimum compatibility with the font size. </para>
<para>A theme contains settings that affect different parts of the desktop
as follows: </para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Controls</term>
<listitem>
<para>The controls setting for
a theme determines the visual appearance of all windows, applications, panels,
and panel applications. The controls setting also determines the visual appearance
of the GNOME-compliant interface items that appear on windows, applications,
panels, and panel applications, such as menus, icons, and buttons. Some of
the controls options that are available in the desktop are designed for special
accessibility needs.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Window border</term>
<listitem>
<para>The window frame setting
determines the appearance of the border around windows only.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Icon</term>
<listitem>
<para>The icon setting determines
the appearance of icons on panels and on the desktop background.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
<section id="themes-4">
<title>To Choose a Theme</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>desktop</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To choose a theme, perform the following steps:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The themes
are listed under the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> 
tab.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on a theme in the list box to choose a new theme. The
system automatically applies the theme to the desktop. </para>
<para>There are several themes available that suit different accessibility
needs, as described in the following table:</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="themes-TBL-2">
<title>Themes Designed for Accessibility Requirements</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Theme Name</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides dark text on a light background using high
contrast colors.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Inverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Provides
light text on a dark background using high contrast colors.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>Large Print</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>This theme suggests an increased
font size of 18pt. The background and foreground colors are the same as those
specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> desktop theme. To apply the
suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Large Print</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>This theme suggests an increased
font size of 18pt using dark text on a light background.  To apply the
suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Large Print Inverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>This theme suggests an increased
font size of 18pt using light text on a dark background. To apply the
suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>To view the controls, window frame, and icon settings that are associated
with a theme, select a theme in the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> 
dialog, then click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog contains a tabbed section for each setting
category. Each tabbed section lists the options that are available and the
current setting for the theme is highlighted. </para>
</section>
<section id="themes-20">
<title>To Modify the Controls Setting for a Theme</title>
<para>To modify the controls setting that is associated with a theme, perform
the following steps: </para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>In the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, select
the theme that you want to modify. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button.
The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guilabel>Controls</guilabel> tab to display
the controls options that are available. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Select the controls option that you want to associate with
the current theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.
The following table lists the controls options that are suitable for accessibility
needs. </para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table frame="topbot">
<title>Controls Options Designed for Accessibility Requirements</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Control Option</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides dark text on a light background using high
contrast colors.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Provides
light text on a dark background using high contrast colors.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Uses low contrast colors for
the background and foreground text. </para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Increases the size of controls
to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool. The background and foreground colors are
the same as those specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> desktop theme.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides dark text on a light background using high
contrast colors. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts.
To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application>
preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrintInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides light text on a dark background using high
contrast colors. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts.
To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application>
preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Uses
low contrast colors for the background and foreground text. Increases the
size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you
must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
<section id="themes-5">
<title>To Modify the Window Border Setting for a Theme</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>window border</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To modify the window border setting that is associated with a theme,
perform the following steps: </para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>In the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, select
the theme that you want to modify. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button.
The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guilabel>Window Border</guilabel> tab to display
the window frame options that are available. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Select the window frame option that you want to associate
with the current theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.
The <guilabel>Atlanta</guilabel> option is an accessible option. </para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section id="themes-19">
<title>To Modify the Icon Setting for a Theme</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>icon</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To modify the icon setting that is associated with a theme, perform
the following steps: </para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>In the <guilabel>Theme Preferences</guilabel> dialog, select
the theme that you want to modify. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guibutton>Theme Details</guibutton> button.
The <guilabel>Theme Details</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tab to display the
icon options that are available. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Select the icon option that you want to associate with the
theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The following
table lists the icon options that are suitable for accessibility needs.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table frame="topbot">
<title>Icon Options Designed for Accessibility Requirements</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Icon Option</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Description</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides dark on light icons using high contrast
colors.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Provides
light on dark icons using high contrast colors.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Uses low contrast colors for
the background and foreground text. </para>
</entry>
</row>
<!--<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>The background and foreground
colors are the same as those specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> 
desktop theme. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides dark text on a light background using high
contrast colors. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrintInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Provides light text on a dark background using high
contrast colors. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Uses
low contrast colors for the background and foreground text. To increase the
font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</entry>
</row>-->
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
<section id="themes-6">
<title>To Create Your Own Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>creating your own</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>For information about how to create your own themes, see
the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:system-admin-guide?themes-0">System Administration Guide</ulink>. </para>
</section>
</section>
<section id="themes-7">
<title>Customizing Specific Components of the Desktop</title>
<para>This section describes how to customize specific components of the desktop
individually.</para>
<section id="themes-8">
<title>To Customize the Desktop Background</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop background</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The themes do not affect the
desktop background. Therefore to modify the desktop background to complement
your desktop, you must customize the desktop background separately using the <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool. To start the <application>Desktop Background</application> preference tool,choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and choose a background from the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tab.</para>
</section>
<section id="themes-9">
<title>To Customize Desktop Background Objects</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop background objects</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The size of the icons
that are displayed on the desktop background is controlled by the <application>File Management</application> preference tool. To change the size of the icons,
perform the following steps:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>From the <application>File Manager</application> window, choose the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu item.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Select the <guilabel>Views</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In the <guilabel>Icon View Defaults</guilabel> group, select
the zoom level that you require in the <guilabel>Default zoom level</guilabel> 
drop-down list.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section id="themes-10">
<title>To Customize Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<anchor id="themes-13"/>
<anchor id="themes-14"/>
<para>This section describes how to customize
the font settings for the desktop and frequently-used applications.</para>
<para>If you have difficulty with the default font type and font size that
is used on the desktop and desktop background, you can customize the font
settings to suit your needs. </para>
<para>You can specify individual font settings for the following desktop components
and applications: </para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Entire desktop excluding the desktop background</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Desktop background only</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Terminal</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Text editor</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Help</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Web Browser</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section id="themes-11">
<title>To Customize the Desktop Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>The <application>Font</application>
preference tool allows you to specify the default fonts for the desktop. </para>
<para>To start the <application>Font</application> preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> tab contains the following options: </para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Application font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Click on this button to select a default font to use for the text that
is displayed on the desktop, including the text displayed on the windows and
dialogs associated with GNOME-compliant applications and panel applications.</para>
<note>
<para>If you use the <application>Theme</application> preference tool
to select a theme and you click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button,
the font that is associated with the theme overrides the font that you select
using the <application>Font</application> preference tool.</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Document font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Click on this button to select a font to use for displaying documents.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Desktop font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>Click on this button to select a font to use for the text that is displayed
on the desktop background only.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Window title font</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>Click on this
button to select a font to use for the text that is displayed in titlebars
of your windows.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Fixed width font</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>Click on this button
to select a font to use for editing documents.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Font rendering</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>To specify how to
render fonts on the desktop, select one of the following options:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Monochrome</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Best shapes</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Best contrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Subpixel smoothing</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<note>
<para>If you use large fonts, you may need to change the size of panes
in applications that use panes such as, the file manager and the Help browser. </para>
</note>
<para>For more information about the <application>Font</application> preference
tool, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?prefs-font">User Guide</ulink>. </para>
</section>
<section id="themes-cust">
<title>To Customize Application Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>individual font</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>By default, GNOME applications use the default font specified in the <application>Font</application> preference tool.  Some applications allow this default font to be customized.  These applications are:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#yelp">Help Browser</ulink> </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gedit?gedit-prefs-fontsandcolors">Text Editor</ulink> </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-terminal#gnome-terminal-prefs-general">Terminal</ulink> </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:epiphany#ephy-customize">Web Browser</ulink> </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="themes-15">
<title>Meeting Specific Accessibility Needs</title>
<para>The following sections summarize the steps you need to take to improve
the accessibility of the desktop in a particular area. </para>
<section id="themes-16">
<title>To Achieve a High or Low Contrast Desktop</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>high contrast desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>low contrast desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>To achieve a high
or low contrast desktop, perform the following steps:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Use the <application>Theme</application> preference tool to
select the high contrast or low contrast desktop theme that you require.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Use the <application>Desktop Background</application> preference
tool to customize your desktop background as follows:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Set the <guilabel>Desktop Wallpaper</guilabel> to <guilabel>No Wallpaper</guilabel>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Set the <guilabel>Desktop Colors</guilabel> to <guilabel>Solid Color</guilabel>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Select a background color that suits your needs.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In the <application>Terminal</application> application, ensure
that the <guilabel>Use colors from system theme</guilabel> option is selected
in the <guilabel>Colors</guilabel> tabbed section of the <guilabel>Editing
Profile</guilabel> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In the <application>gedit</application> application, ensure
that the <guilabel>Use default theme colors</guilabel> option is selected
in the <guilabel>Fonts &amp; Colors</guilabel> tabbed section of the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
<section id="themes-17">
<title>To Achieve a Large Print Desktop</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>large print desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>To achieve
a large print desktop, perform the following steps:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Use the <application>Theme</application> preference tool to
select the <guilabel>Large Print</guilabel> theme.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button to increase
the size of the font that is used on the desktop and on window frames.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Use the <guilabel>Desktop font</guilabel> option in the <application>Font</application> preference tool to increase the font that is displayed
on desktop background objects.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Increase the font size that is used to display the contents
of the <application>Terminal</application> application window. </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the <guilabel>Use default theme font</guilabel> option
is selected in the <application>gedit</application> <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog, <application>gedit</application> uses the font size that
is specified in the large print theme that you selected. However, if the <guilabel>Use default theme font</guilabel> option is not selected, increase the font
size that is used to display the contents of the <application>gedit</application>
text editor window. See the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gedit?gedit-prefs-fontsandcolors"> gedit manual</ulink> for more information.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If you use applications that use panes, such as the file manager
and the Help browser, you may need to change the size of panes to accommodate
the large print. See the online help for the appropriate application for more
information.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>
